<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Desiderius A most godly, religious, and delectable dialogue, teaching the true and ready way, by which we may attayne to the perfect loue of God. First written in Spanish, and since translated by diuers persons into the Italian, French, Dutch, and Latin tongue, and now lastly into the English.</title>
            <title>Spill de la vida religiosa. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 226 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 81 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20362</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6777</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117459</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852672</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852672</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18006</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20362)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18006)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1234:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Desiderius A most godly, religious, and delectable dialogue, teaching the true and ready way, by which we may attayne to the perfect loue of God. First written in Spanish, and since translated by diuers persons into the Italian, French, Dutch, and Latin tongue, and now lastly into the English.</title>
                  <title>Spill de la vida religiosa. English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>160 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[English Secret Press], by the permission of superiours,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Roane [i.e England] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1604.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of "Spill de la vida religiosa", which is erroneously attributed to Miguel de Comalada.</note>
                  <note>The imprint is false; actually printed by the English Secret Press.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Spiritual life --  Catholic Church --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18006:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18006:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>DESIDERIVS.</p>
            <p>A MOST GOD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LY, RELIGIOVS, AND delectable Dialogue, teaching the true and ready way, by which we may attayne to the perfect Loue of God.</p>
            <p>FIRST WRITTEN IN SPA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, and ſince tranſlated by diuers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons into the Italian, French, Dutch, and Latin tongue, and now laſtly into the Engliſh.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at ROANE, by the permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Superiours, Anno 1604.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:18006:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18006:2"/>
            <head>A MOST GODLY, RELIGIOVS, <hi>and delectable Dialogue, teaching the true</hi> and ready way, by which we may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne to the perfect loue of God.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER 1.</hi> Deſire goeth on Pilgrimage.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here liued ſometimes in a vaſt and ſolitarie deſert, a holy &amp; Religious Father, whoſe chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt care, and daylie exerciſe, was with faſting, watching, and praying, continually to ſerue God. This holy Father was moued on a time with a zealous and hartie deſire, to finde out the true &amp; ready way, (if poſsibly he cold,) to true wiſdome, and the loue of God. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he reſolued with himſelfe to trauaile ouer the whole world, if happely he could finde a Maſter able to inſtruct and direct him herein. With this reſolution he departed from his Cell,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18006:3"/>and then firſt beganne his determined journey. Now after this holy Father, (whome we will call, <hi>Deſiderius</hi> or <hi>Deſire</hi>) had meaſured the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, with a long and weariſome trauaile he firſt encountred a reuerende old ſheepheard: who fedde his flocke, in a pleaſant greene meddow, beautified with variety of ſweet ſmelling flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: with the ſight of whome, being greatly comforted: hauing long trauailed, &amp; yet mette with no man, he ſaluted him in manner follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. My louing Brother, now thanked be God who hath directed me to meete you here. To whome the ſheepheard returned anſwere: I likewiſe am gladde of this our meeting: tel me, what ſeeke you in this ſolitary deſert? I ſeeke quoth <hi>Deſire</hi> a certayne Knight, who as I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand is trauailed this way.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 2.</hi> He inſtructeth Prelates and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Paſtors.</head>
               <p>THis Pilgrim, &amp; this Paſtor, thus mette to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither, <hi>Deſire</hi> attentiuely noted with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, the great care, and diligence, which this good ſheepheard vſed, towards the flocke committed to his charge, firſt, he had in his hand a rodde, or wande, on his right ſide, there hong a ſcrippe, or bagge: on his feete, he weare wodden pattens, his garment was a long coate; on his lefte ſide, at his girdle, there hong a little
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18006:3"/>horne, and on his right ſide, an other ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what greater, two great dogges followed him on each ſide, and faſt by, was his homely cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, fenſed &amp; compaſſed about with buſhes, and thornes. The ſheepheard, perſeauing how attentiuely <hi>Deſire</hi> beheld and noted him, asked of him, the cauſe thereof: and if he neuer had ſeene a ſheepheard before? DE. Truely Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I haue oft ſeene manie, but neuer one ſo well prouided as your ſelfe, wherefore pardon me: and if it be nto troubleſome to you, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare me to that I ſhall aske of you. SH. You ſhall not be offenſiue to me, if your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandes, be but ſuch as I may anſwere. DE. Wherefore doe you carrie this ſtaffe in your hande? SH. I meruaile not a little, why you aske me that, for conſidering, your ſelfe are a Sheepheard, as I am, howe can you be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the vſe of it? I vſe this ſtaffe, both for my ayde, and ſtay, that going vp and downe, with my ſheepe, I ſtumble not and fall: and alſo, therewith I order and rule my flocke, directing them therewith, to keepe their right way, and prohibiting them, to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and ſtray, but to keepe togither, not allowing each one to goe ſeuerall wayes: for if anie one chance to ſeuer from my flocke, or to follow after anie other, then my ſelfe, with this ſtaffe, enforce him &amp; driue him, vntill
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18006:4"/>he vnite himſelfe againe to his fellowes. DE. What doe you carry in this Scrippe that you weare? SH. Foure thinges: A tinder boxe to ſtrike fire, wherewith in colde winter I may warme my ſelfe, and dreſſe ſuch meate as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth my fellowes, and me, alſo bread, onyons, a box of oyntment, and ſalt, whereof eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I oft giue my ſhepe. DE. Why doe you weare wodden pattens on your feete. SH. To keepe me warme in Winter, when it is Froſt, and Snow: for if I ſhould weare more coſtly, or curious, they would ſoone be worne out with much going about. DE. What ſignifieth this long garment that you weare? SH. This is my habit, without which, no man would know me to be a ſheephearde. DE. Whereof is this garment made? SH. of ſheepe skinnes. DE. Might it not bee made of Wolues or other beaſts skinnes? No, for my ſheepe would eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie finde that by the ſmell, and ſo woulde pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently fly away from me: but ſeeing me cladde in their owne skinnes; they loue and followe me continually. DE. What haue you in the horne that hangeth on your left ſide? SH. An oyntment, wherewith I dreſſe my ſheepe that be infected with the ſcabbe. DE. What in the bigger, that hangeth on the right ſide? SH. A marking ſtone, whereby I know them from other mens ſheepe. DE. For what vſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18006:4"/>doe you keepe theſe dogges? SH. They barke in the night, and keep away the wolues, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, both my ſheepe be in more ſafety, and I my ſelfe take my reſt more quietly. DE. Why are you ſo carefull ouer this your charge? SH. Becauſe I haue a kinde and bountifull Maſter, who hath promiſed me a great rewarde, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I doe it not in regarde of rewarde, but rather for the loue I beare to him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 3.</hi> Of the ſame Argument.</head>
               <p>DESIRE now grewe into great admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with him ſelfe, and was greatly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, hearing that this ſheepheard did vndertake this charge for loue, and ſaid to him. My bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, conſidering you co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſe for the moſt part in theſe pleaſant fieldes, can you certifie me of a certayne Knight which wandereth ſolitarily, vp and downe alone? by reaſon that being expelled his poſſeſſion by his owne ſubjectes, he is conſtrayned to ſeeke ſome place of abode where he may reſt and ſettle him ſelfe. SH. What is the name of this Knight, you enquire after? DE. He is called, the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> SH. I knowe right well the place of his abode. And if thou hadſt experience to keepe my flocke as I haue, and werte euery way ſufficient for ſuch a charge, I would my ſelfe bring thee to him, that thou mighteſt not as heretofore wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18006:5"/>vp and downe to ſeeke him, hee loueth ſheepheardes, and willingly conuerſeth with them. And although he be a noble, and renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med knight, yet is he notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the ſoune of a ſheepheard. But perceauing thee, to be a man of a weake, and tender conſtitution, and vnfitte of thy ſelfe, to vndertake the charge of my flocke, not able to follow them, though this ſolitarie deſert, I thinke it meete, thou ſhouldeſt aſſay an other journey. DE. What other journey doe you aduiſe me to take? SH. Firſt muſt you paſſe through this ſolitarie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, and not farre hence, ſhall you finde a faire and ſtately Monaſterie: this Monaſterie is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited only with Virgins, of whome you ſhal learne the abode of this Knight: for ſuch is the curteſie, affabilitie, and honeſt carriage of him, that willingly, he conuerſeth with all, that ſeeke after him. This deſcourſe of the ſheepheard, pleaſed <hi>Desire</hi> not a little, and the rather, being put in hope, by him to finde out the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> Who ſaid to him, teach me, I pray you the ready way that I muſt take: leaſt that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps through ignorance, I happe to goe awry. SH. I may not my ſelfe forſake my flocke, yet will I appoint thee a conuenient companion in this thy journey, who accompaning thee, that by the aſſiſtance of God, thou ſhalt not eaſely goe out of thy way: take here with thee this my
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18006:5"/>dogge. DE. What is his name? SH. <hi>Good will.</hi> DE. Farewell my Brother. SH. And you alſo, to whome I wiſh a proſperous jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 4.</hi> Of the houſe of Humilitie.</head>
               <p>HEre <hi>Deſire</hi> leauing the Sheepheard, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertoke his journey, acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panied with his dogge; running by his ſide: which was no little comfort to him on the way, and now hauing trauailed, many dayes, and nights, he entred on a Sonday, into a moſt pleaſant greene medow, ſeated in a dry, and rocky ſoyle, whereat, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire</hi> meruailed not a little, to ſee ſo pleaſant, and ſo greene a meddow, lying in ſo ſtony, and ſo barraine a place, ouergrowne aboute, with buſhes, and thornes. And entring farther in, he found there builte, a ſtately, faire Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: the ſight whereof, pleaſed him much. But comming neare, he found the gates ſhut, and a certayne Virgin ſtanding without, modeſt as to him ſeemed, both in her attire, and behauiour: who at the ſight of <hi>Deſires</hi> dogge, beganne to be afrayd. Whome <hi>Deſire</hi> comforted, and hidde not to feare, aſſuring her, his dogge would not hurte her. And meruailing, to ſee her ſtand thus alone without, he deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of her, why ſhee ſtoode there, who an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweared him, that ſhee expected the opening
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18006:6"/>of the gates to goe in. Then demanding farther her name of her, ſhe anſwered, ſaying; I am cal-called <hi>Vaine-glorie.</hi> Now <hi>Deſire</hi> hauing long expected the opening of the gates, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceuing his attendance to be all in vaine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to call, and knocke at the gate with a hammer, hanging thereat, called <hi>Longanimitie,</hi> &amp; preſently came forth can auncient reuerende man, who opened the gate. This man was called the <hi>Feare of God,</hi> who was both porter and keeper of all this Monaſterie, whome <hi>Deſire</hi> ſeing, and finding a graue and wiſe reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rende man, was greatly cheared in beholding him, and after due reuerence done to him, ſpake to him in manner following. Good Sir (quoth he,) my comming hither, is to ſeeke out a Knight, called the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> Who as I am tolde, is trauailed through this deſert, and hath his abode now in this Monaſtery, wherefore I humbly deſire of you, to know if he be here within or no. At this demand of his, the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter rejoyced, for he loued the <hi>Loue of God</hi> euen as his owne Brother, &amp; asked of him, why h ſought ofter this Knight. DE. I ſeeke him not only becauſe I am greatly delighted with him, but alſo becauſe it is very behouefull for me to finde him; FEARE OF GOD. What? haue you any thing ſo ſecret that you dare not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale it? DE. Truely Sir. only I deſire his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18006:6"/>company and conuerſation, and wiſh I were his ſeruant to attend on him, coueting nothing more than ſuch a Maſter and inſtructer, for in all this country, I cannot finde a Maſter an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to my minde, although many haue bin willing to entertayne me. But I haue learned from many, that the <hi>Loue of god,</hi> is a moſt noble gentle, and bountifull Maſter: who in that he is rich, often beſtoweth great preferments on his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. FEARE OF GOD. True it is, he paſſed, his way acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panied but with fewe, who at this preſent is not within, but haue patience a while, &amp; I will call a Virgin to you, who is able to direct you, where you ſhall finde him out.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 5.</hi> How Vaine-glory watcheth at the gate.</head>
               <p>MEane time, now <hi>Deſire</hi> joyfully expected the comming of the Porter, and Virgin he ſpake of, &amp; not weighting long, there came to him a modeſt and ſeemely Virgin, who ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him curteouſly, was in like manner reſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againe, of whome <hi>Deſire</hi> craued her name, who anſwered, my name is called <hi>Nihili-penſio,</hi> becauſe I entermedle not in ſuperfluous &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary thinges, and demanding farther the name of the Monaſterie, ſhee told him it was the houſe of <hi>Humilitie,</hi> becauſe within, there dwelt many virgins, who liued vnder the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and rule of humilitie, he againe asked:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18006:7"/>what maide is that which ſtandeth without the gate, her name quoth ſhe, is called <hi>Vaine-glory:</hi> who ſitteth continually at this gate vntill it be opened, and then, if the Porter be negligent, &amp; looke not ſtrictly to his office, (but leaue open the gates) ſhee preſently entreth. Why do you not admit her in ſaid <hi>Deſire,</hi> conſidering both in ſpeech, habit, &amp; geſture, ſhe ſeemeth modeſt, vertuous, &amp; honeſt. You know not (quoth the <hi>Virgin</hi>) her conditions, I perceaue: For I aſſure you, ſhee is a moſt dangerous beaſte, for how much the more modeſt, &amp; religious ſhe ſemeth by her externall carriage, ſo much I holde her, to be more dangerous. What, ſaith <hi>Deſire,</hi> doth ſhe at any time hurt you? yea truly ſaid the <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gin,</hi> ſo farre as lieth in her power: her father is a wicked man, called <hi>Selfe Loue,</hi> her mother as ill, called <hi>Selfe Eſtimation,</hi> neither haue we three greater enemies in all the world, and farther, they are enemies to the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> a Knight who is Maſter of this Monaſtery, in which we liue. And that you may farther know, what hurt <hi>Vaine-glory</hi> doeth vs: I ſay, ſo ſoone as ſhee entereth in, ſhee is ſo gluttenous, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uening, that firſt ſhee goeth into our Orchards, &amp; there deuoureth, and eateth vp al our fruite, which is both faire &amp; good, which is the fruite, wee haue to liue with, neyther haue we more than one tree of it, which carrieth ſo litle, that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18006:7"/>hardly are we ſuſteyned therewith, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken away from vs, by <hi>Vaine-glory,</hi> we remaine ſo poore, that nothing is left vs. And yet worſe than this, after ſhee is once come in, ſhee is ſo crafty, and deceitfull, that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expell her, labour we neuer ſo much, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till wee call the aſſiſtance of our Mother, at whoſe only ſight, ſhee runneth away: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee thinke it good, not to admitte her at all, which to preuent, wee purpoſely keepe this Porter continually at our gate, who is a ſeuere and ſterne man, and ſtill ſhutteth the gate, that ſhee cannot enter: whome wee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate to be circumſpect, that when hee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth any, hee through negligence, leaue not open the gate. <hi>Deſire</hi> ſtoode amaſed, at the diſcourſe of this <hi>Virgin,</hi> and replied, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering ſhee is ſo dangerous an enemy to you, you cannot be too carefull, to keepe her out of your houſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 6.</hi> By what meanes, we may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tame to Humilitie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DEſire</hi> continuing his ſpeech with this Virgin, asked her who brought her into that goodly, and Religious Monaſtery, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned, and ſhining, with ſo rare vertues, Two Virgins (quoth ſhee) guided me hither,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18006:8"/>whereof the one is called <hi>Contempt of the world,</hi> a Virgin endued with ſinguler vertues the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther called <hi>Contempt of her ſelfe,</hi> exceeding the firſt by many degrees. Theſe two Virgins lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding me in, entreated our Mother and Miſtris to receaue me, which notwithſtanding ſhe had not done, but for the loue of a certayne Knight, which mette vs in our journey, &amp; came in here with vs, who beſtowed on me this habite I weare, and admitted me into the ſociety of his Virgins, and had it not beene graunted vs by ſpeciall grace, that, that Knight had entred in hither with vs, I had neuer beene receaued, but had loſt my labour. DE. What is the name of the Knight you ſpeake of? VIRGIN: The <hi>Loue of God.</hi> It pleaſed <hi>deſire</hi> much, that the <hi>Loue of God</hi> was of that account, that ſo many, and ſo great thinges where done: only for his ſake, and now he beganne more earneſtly to Deſire his preſence, and ſayde. DE. Deare ſiſter, tell me what were the parents of theſe two Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, which brought you hither, for it auaileth much to the honeſty and reputation of a man, to be borne of honeſt and vertuous parents, for commonly the tree taketh the vertue from the roote. VIR. I knowe right well their parents names, their father is one of chiefeſt authoritie in our Princes palace, who is called, <hi>To knowe,</hi> alſo I knowe as well their grand-father, whoſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18006:8"/>name is <hi>To Conſider,</hi> who is a wiſe and diſcreete man, and one that diſchargeth his office dulie: he married a wife called <hi>Wiſedome.</hi> DE. Had the Knight when hee mette you no man in his company? VIR. Yes, he had a boy with him whom he loueth dearely, this boy is, called the <hi>Loue of our neighbour.</hi> DE. Can you direct me whither this Knight is gone? VIR. I coulde direct you, but let vs goe in, and I will bring you to thoſe that can inſtruct you certainly: but tell me I pray you, why doe you carry this great dogge with you? DE. He was giuen vnto me by an other, for I my ſelfe had firſt but a little whelpe, which I bredde vp in my cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, vntill I mette a certayne ſheepheard that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed, his bigger dogge on me, to accompany me through this vaſt and ſolitarie deſert, in which (as I was told) liued many hurtful ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; dangerous wild beaſts, from which I might bee defended by the aſſiſtance of this dogge. VIRG. What is the dogges name? DE. <hi>Good will.</hi> VIRG. The dogge ſurely is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good dogge, if you knowe howe to keepe him: and aſſure your ſelfe, ſo long as you haue him, he will ſuffer no ill to befall vnto you, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neede you to feare, to ſtray out of your way. DE. But tell me I pray you? of whome may I enquire, where I may finde this Knight that I ſeeke after? VIR. Truely Brother, he
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18006:9"/>dwelleth farre hence, &amp; thou haſt a long jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to goe through this deſert, before thou canſt come to the place of his abode: thou muſt trauaile at the leaſte, ſeauen dayes journey, for there be ſeauen Monaſteries, ſeated in this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, neither is there any other way to paſſe, but this: yet for the loue of the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering, I ſee thee ſo deſirous of him, I will di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect thee a ſhort way to goe, by the which thou ſhalt ſooner come where he is, wherefore, it is requiſite that thou follow my aduiſe. <hi>Deſire</hi> hearing what ſee ſaid, rejoyced greatly, but eſpecially, becauſe ſhee ſaide ſhee would doe it for the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> and ſaide to her. DE. I will doe, what ere you bid me, ſo I may finde the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> VIR. Here, within this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, there are eight Monaſteries, whereof, this which is the houſe of <hi>Humility,</hi> is the firſt, the ſecond, is of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> the third, is of <hi>Wiſedome,</hi> the fourth, of <hi>Fortitude,</hi> the fift, of <hi>Tempera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,</hi> the ſixt, of <hi>Faith,</hi> the ſeauenth, of <hi>Hope,</hi> the eight, of <hi>Charity:</hi> in this laſt of <hi>Charity,</hi> remaineth the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> and there diſchargeth the office of a porter. This whole journey, thou muſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake, if thou wilt be ſure to go the right way, but as I ſaide, I will teach thee a ſhorterway, by which, thou mayeſt ſooner come to him: yet notwithſtanding, it is of neceſſity, that thou abide a time here in this Monaſtery, that thou
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18006:9"/>maiſt learne, marke, and remember, all our or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and be acquainted with our Miſtris, &amp; all herd daughters, and learned, and remember their names behuiours, &amp; lius. Moreouer, thou muſt diligently note, al things in this Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, &amp; carry to the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> Certaine rules of ours, for the great loue he beareth to this our Monaſtery before others, then will he without delay, moſt willingly receaue thee, the rather, if thou bring letters of commendation from our Miſtris. DE. What is the reaſon, the <hi>Loue of God</hi> ſhould ſo preferre you; conſidering (as me ſeemeth) you are the pooreſt, meaneſt, &amp; few<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in number. VIR. This was the firſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery that was founded in this Deſert, and all the other are depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding on this, beſides our chie feſt founder, &amp; gouernor, the builder, &amp; work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of this Monaſterie, maketh his abode and dwelling amongſt vs: And although he walke vp &amp; downe this Deſert, to viſit &amp; keep in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the other Monaſteries, yet will he not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit himſelf to be otherwaies called, then a child of this Monaſtery, &amp; firſt of al, we gaue him an habit. <hi>deſire</hi> was ſo much delighted with the diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>courſe of this virgin; that he felte his hart infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with loue, for he noted her words well, &amp; ſaide, he deſired nothing more, than to ſpend long time in this place, &amp; with great diligence to note &amp; marke their orders. Then the virgin
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18006:10"/>taking him by the hand ſaid, let vs now goe in.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPER. 7.</hi> The purpoſe, or intent of Humility, and her talke with Deſire.</head>
               <p>THe building of this houſe much pleaſed <hi>Deſire,</hi> and he admired the beauty thereof, conſidering it was playne, without any cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fet: for neither was it builte high, not yet ſet forth, with any imagery or painting; but lowe, &amp; conuenient, not founded vpon ſand, but on a firme rocke. After <hi>Deſire</hi> had a time atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded his deuotions in the Oratory, the Virgin brought him to the chamber of their Miſtris, or mother, who receaued him curteouſly, ſeeing him ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, &amp; deuoted to Gods ſeruice, and making him ſit, ſaid vnto him, what cauſe my Son hath brought thee, amongſt vs, conſidering we are ſo poore, ſo meane, &amp; ſuch abjects? DE. Lady mother, I ſeeke after a knight, called the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> And as I am inſtructed, I canot finde him, except I make my abode here ſome time with you: wherfore (if it be not troubleſome to you,) I deſire to liue vnder your obedience, &amp; gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. HVM. Your deſire and purpoſe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth me well, but firſt conſider, and weigh with your ſelfe, what it is that you goe about to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake, leaſt hauing once entred, you repent you of your purpoſe. DE. I beſeech God aſſiſt me with his grace &amp; helpe, that I may perſeuer
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18006:10"/>in vertue, and all goodnes. HVM. I wiſh the ſame, &amp; pray to God, to accompliſh this good worke, which he hath begonne in thee. But far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it is requiſite, that thou thy ſelfe endeuour al that in thee lyeth, that God may proſper this thy good purpoſe. DE. What think you need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for me to do? HVM. My Sonne, I will tell thee. If thy deſire be to remayne here amongſt vs, and not to be expelled from hence by my Virgins; thou muſt take my yongeſt daughter, which brought thee in hither, who is called <hi>Nihili-penſio,</hi> that is, contempt of al vnneceſſary cares: &amp; her thou muſt obey as thy gouerneſſe or Miſtris, to whome, purpoſly we haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the charge, to entertayne ſtrangers, and be the directix of nouices, &amp; whoſoeuer refuſe to be obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to her, neuer perſeuer in that they vndertake. DE. Moſt willingly I admit her, and receaue her my gouerneſſe; and deſire to know of you Lady mother, your name, ſtocke, conditions, and degree, &amp; how, you come to be mother ouer theſe <hi>Virgins?</hi> For as it is tould me, I muſt knowe, and learne, the properties, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, &amp; ſtate, of all theſe Virgins vnder your gouerment to the intent, that the better I know them, the more I may loue them; &amp; that when I ſhall depart from he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, I may the better be able to anſwere, &amp; direct thoſe that ſhal aſke, or ſeek to learne any thing of me. HVM. My name is
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18006:11"/>
                  <hi>Humility,</hi> my Father, <hi>Contempte of him ſelfe, Knowledge of himſelfe,</hi> my Grandfather, and his wife is called <hi>Knowledge of God.</hi> My fore na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Grandfather, commeth from a citty, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>To marke, and conſider</hi> what I am, what I haue beene, what I ſhall be. My Grandmother from a towne, called <hi>Conſideration of the Loue of God.</hi> There are but two wayes, to goe to the country of my Grandfather, &amp; only two gates, whereby to enter in, the firſt is, <hi>Man himſelfe,</hi> the other <hi>All creatures,</hi> and men ſay, no man can enter into either of theſe gates, but by fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: and that our Lord God himſelfe builded this citty, with his owne hands, conſidering, that none but he, could finiſhe ſo commodious, ſo beautifull, &amp; ſo firme a building. DE. Would our Lord God, whoſe majeſty, and excellency is ſo great, put himſelfe to the building, of ſuch ſtony, and clay workes? HVM. Yea truely, for he is an excellent workeman, and both a ſtilfull maſon, and carpenter, and taketh great delight in making earthen works, &amp; buildings. DE. What is the cauſe that he doth this, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that he hath need of nothing? HVM. Nothing, but his owne goodnes, doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayne, or moue him to do this: whence it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth, that he neuer ceaſeth to benefit others, neither ſeeketh he, or ſtudieth with all thinges that he maketh, and goeth about, anie other
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18006:11"/>thing, but the benefit, felicity, and ſaluation, of all men, the honor and prayſe, to himſelfe alone reſerued. And for this cauſe, doth he make of ſo baſe, and vile a matter, ſo goodly, and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full workes, as he doeth, that the worthines of the worke, being compared with the baſenes of the matter, all men might admire him, prayſe him, and loue him. DE. I meruail that ſo excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t a Lord as he is, would ſeeke for prayſe, conſidering thereby he may be touched with vaine-glory? HVM. There is nothing leſſe to be feared, than that in him, he being ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, that no greater perfection can be added to him, and all honor and glory, that can be yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to him, cannot be ſaid vaine, being only proper to him; And how great honor ſoeuer we can giue to him, yet in regarde of that which beſeemeth him, &amp; is due to him; we can neuer honor him, anſwerable to his dignitie. And for that cauſe will he be exalted, and prayſed, not that he deſireth glory, but becauſe he is moſt iuſt, and will, that euery one, haue that which is due to him: then ſeing all prayſe, honor, and glory is due to him alone, being only good, his will is, that all prayſe, honor and glory, be yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded only to him. But if anie other ſhall ſeeke or deſire after glory, they may iuſtly be called vaineglorious, becauſe they take it from him, to whome it only appertayneth, and he may
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18006:12"/>truly be called a theefe, that taketh to himſelfe, an other mans goodes, againſt the will of the true owner.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 8.</hi> Humility continueth her ſpeech.</head>
               <p>DESIRE. Now Lady Mother, that you haue tolde me your parentage, &amp; ſtocke, I deſire to knowe, how you came to be chiefe Gouerneſſe of this houſe: for in my opinion, it is a great honour and dignity, and I my ſelfe, in time may come to be a gouernour: for there is greate difference, betweene com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding, and obeyinge, <hi>Humility</hi> hearing what he ſaide, beganne to weepe, of whome, <hi>Deſire</hi> demaunded the cauſe of her weepinge. HVM. My Sonne, I cannot conteyne my teares, to ſee, that outwardly thou ſeemeſt clad with the habit of humilitie, and yet inwardly thou appeareſt naked, &amp; bare, &amp; that in ſhew, thou ſemeſt religious and virtuous; but in hart, and minde, voyde of virtue, and deuotion. In vaine haue we vſed our paſſed diſcourſe, ſeing theſe thoughtes, and deſires of thine, are ſo cleane repugnant from the wil of my father, &amp; moſt dearly beloued Lord Ieſus, who neither in word, nor deed, euer ſought, or deſired rule or gouernment, &amp; came not into this world, to be ſerued, but to ſerue. From which path who ſoeuer turneth, and ſtrayeth: walketh the way
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18006:12"/>of damnation, not ſaluation. But Oh vnhappy &amp; miſerable creaturs that we are, to whom it is alotted, to rule and gouerne others: conſidering how hard a taſke we take in hand, if we wil but commaund our ſelues as we ought. Such ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor is in deede but miſery, and full of cares, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors, wearines, afflictions, ſorowes, dangers, &amp; moſt horrible feares and which if it be not well ordered &amp; gouerned, is in the end accompany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ignominy and ſhame. Oh ouer heauie burthen of rule &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement: in which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is found, put labor, and trouble, wherein hatred, repining, &amp; il wil is receiued from thoſe that ſhould acknowledg, and yeeld obedience and thanks. If thou remaineſt any time here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, thou ſhalt finde by experience my ſayings true. Now, to anſwere thy demaund, how I came to be gouerneſſe: I will, for the <hi>Loue of God</hi> acquaynte thee with the meane. When firſt, I entered into this houſe: I purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and ſo perſwaded my ſelfe, that I was but a labouring beaſte, and the ſeruant of the other Virgins: and this determination of mine, I ſo reſolued to performe, and imprinted it, deeply in my minde, and hart, continuallie calling it freſhly to my minde, and prayinge to God, to make mee ſtill deſire it, and that it woulde pleaſe him to make mee worthie to bee his Spouſe, and ſo through his appoynte-ment
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18006:13"/>I came to be gouerneſſe, although of my ſelfe, I neither would, or deſired it. <hi>Deſire</hi> hearing <hi>Humilities</hi> diſcourſe, thought her a Virgin, of very rare vertue, in that for the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> ſhee had ſo dejected, and debaſed her ſelfe; and perceauing her to be yet a Virgin, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the Matrimony that ſhee ſpake of, to be ſpirituall, and not carnall, and ſaid. DE. Then I perceaue, who ſo will be a Superiour, &amp; ruler, muſt according as you haue done, firſt humble and debaſe himſelfe. HVM. It is true my Son as by experience thou mayeſt finde it. DE. And how may I try it? HV. By ſeeing thoſe that humble themſelues to be exalted: yet, to take heede, that thou humble not thy ſelfe to that end, that thereby thou deſire to be exalted, for ſo, thou ſhalt ſinne in pride: And pride, &amp; humility are open enemies, and euer oppoſe themſelues, one againſt the other. For what ſo euer thou doeſt, if thou truely humble thy ſelfe, thou canſt not, in the ſame action, exalte thy ſelfe. But if thou humble thy ſelfe, becauſe thou wouldeſt be exalted, thy ſhewe, is humble, but thy acte, is proud. And becauſe, the action is to be taken, according to the intent of the mind, ſuch humility is called pride. By which reaſon, humilitie, may diuerſly be termed pride. For if wee haue reſpect to the action of ſuch a man outwardly, he carrieth a ſhew of humility, but
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18006:13"/>looking to the end of his humble action, wee ſhall finde it, wholy to proceed from pride. And to ſpeake properly, humility it ſelfe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth not with pride, but the ſpirit of humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and it is impoſſible, to haue theſe two a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in one: for humility is but an act, but the ſpirit of humility, conteyneth both the act, and the cauſe, and intention, of humbling, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting our ſelues.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 9.</hi> Humility continueth her diſcourſe, and teacheth how to ſtriue againſt vice.</head>
               <p>NOw my forenamed husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, (I meane my purpoſe I vndertooke to humble my ſelf, like a labouring beaſte, and the ſeruant of all men,) aſſiſted me faithfully, in a certayne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict I had with an other Lady, and her mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, of the houſe of <hi>Pride,</hi> whoſe gouerneſſe was called <hi>Pride of life:</hi> which daily endeuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to ſcrach out mine eyes, and ſtill brauleth with me: An ſhe bringeth with her, both the vnder gouerneſſe of her houſe, called <hi>Concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of the fleſh;</hi> and her ſteward, <hi>Concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of the eyes.</hi> To theſe three aſſociates, her ſelfe a lewde maide, both mother, and nurſe of them, called <hi>Negligence,</hi> who beinge often weake, and feeble, is eaſily ouercome: but ſometime ſhe ſo filleth her ſelfe, with eating, &amp; drinking, that ſhee becommeth fatte &amp; ſtrong,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18006:14"/>and then is ſhee very dangerous. Shee hath at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending on her, a certayne maide, dull, fooliſh, and will brought vp, called <hi>Malice:</hi> with whome come hither, three other Maides, <hi>Anger, Sloath,</hi> &amp; <hi>Enuy.</hi> And vnto the three laſt, aſſociate them ſelues, two other, that is, <hi>Naughty Suſpition,</hi> and <hi>Raſh Iudgement.</hi> All theſe, are at mortall enmity with me, and ſtill oppoſe them ſelues againſt me, with whome I am daily, to contende, and fight. Therefore, ſo oft as they enter in here, I with the aſſiſtance of my husband, ſtraite driue them out, and force them to flie. And then haue we can other feare, leaſt the Maide which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually watcheth at the gates, I meane <hi>Vaine-glory,</hi> preſently ſteppe in. For if once, we giu her opportunity to enter, ſhe robbeth vs of the fruite, and benefit which we got, by expelling our other forenamed enemyes: ſo that then we are barraine of all goodnes, and looſe the labour we tooke in our former con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicte. DE. How then chanceth it, that when theſe other your enemies enter in here, ſhe ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding at the gates, doth not alſo enter. HVM. This is the reaſon, thoſe other Maydens, vſe the benefit of winges, &amp; enter not by the gate, but flie ouer the walles, &amp; often they hide them ſelues, ſo ſecretly in ſome corner of the houſe, that when we leaſt ſuſpect them, they walke &amp; wander vp and downe amongſt vs, wherefore
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18006:14"/>we are of neceſſity, to keepe a carefull watch, leaſt ſuddainly they come vpon vs, and ſpoile vs vnlooked for. DE. Let vs diſcourſe, yet longer of this matter, and tel me why? You are at ſuch debate, &amp; contention with them, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering how il a thing it is, to giue ſuch example to worldly me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when they ſhal ſee ſuch diſcord, &amp; diſſention amongſt Religious perſons; who they knowe, ſhould be gentle, pittiful, &amp; milde, for the Loue of God to all men? HVM. The cauſe of our ſtrife, and diſſenſion with them, is al only for that cauſe, we expel them our houſe, becauſe they are open and profeſſed enemies, to the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> who is our chiefe Lord &amp; Maſter, and whoſoeuer is an enemy to the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> we wil haue neither friendſhippe, or familiarity by any meanes with him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 10.</hi> Of Concupiſcence of the fleſh.</head>
               <p>DESIRE was greatly pleaſed to heare, how great confidence <hi>Humility</hi> had, in the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> and deſired of her, to inſtruct him, by what meanes and helpes they ouercame, and expelled: thoſe dangerous Maydens, their profeſſed enemies. HVM. I would willingly doe it, but becauſe I am not yet fully acquainted with thy nature, life, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions and minde, but only goe vpon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures and imaginations; I reſt yet doubtfull,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18006:15"/>whither I may inſtruct thee herein or no. For conſidering the contrariety, and difference of mens natures, the ſweeteſt hony, taſteth not ſweet to all men. DE. What ſoeuer I ſeeme in ſhewe to your iudgement: or what opinion ſoeuer you haue of me: yet I wholy ſubmit my ſelfe to your will, and yeelde me to be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by your direction, only deſiring to be inſtructed by you, what meanes to vſe, to finde the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> HVM. Vpon that condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I will ſatisfie your deſire, and will impart and make knowen to you my exerciſes, and courſe of life. Firſt that holy purpoſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of myne, which I ſpake of before, hath made me Miſtris of the whole world, ſo long as I ſhall contemne, and deſpiſe it. And Miſtris ouer my owne body by faſting, and diſcipline, and by my voluntary and willing humility? I ſay, not only Miſtris and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandreſſe ouer my ghoſtly enemy, but ouer all the world and yet farther which is greateſt Miſtris and commandreſſe ouer my ſelfe, for when the world ſeeth me to labour, and endeuour, with all my diligence to pleaſe the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> it repugneth me and all my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, yet I ſtill reteyne, peace and tranquillity with my forenamed husband. Now <hi>Deſire,</hi> greatly admired the vertue and force of him, whome <hi>Humility</hi> ſo often had named her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18006:15"/>and ſaid. DE. I beſeech you Lady Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, inſtruct mee by ſimilitudes that I may more playnely conceaue your meaning. For I am but of dull and ſlowe concepte, and by examples I ſhall better conceaue your ſayings. This requeſt of <hi>Deſire</hi> pleaſed <hi>Humility</hi> well, finding that by acknowledging this owne dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, he was now become both modeſt and humble, wherevpon ſhe ſaide to him. HVM. So ſoone as I ſee, any of my before named enemies enter in hither, I thus behaue my ſelfe, if it be the firſt which is <hi>Concupiſcence of the fleſh.</hi> I foreknowe already her conditions, and behauiours, which are to be exceedingly giuen to gluttony, and to pamper her body by exceſſe of eating &amp; drinking. Therefore firſt I take from her all kinde of delicate diet, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I allowe her, her fill of ordinary meate and drinke; And becauſe I am not ſtrong e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of my ſelfe, to tame and maſter her, in regarde that my domeſticall ſeruants aſſiſt her, I vſe others helpe, and place on my right hand. <hi>Gods grace,</hi> which may ſtrengthen and defende me from this dangerous enemy. I alſo craue the ayde and aſſiſtance of my husband, and then ſay to her. Siſter, I haue my ſelfe deſpiſed my fleſh, and make no better accompte of my ſelfe than of a labouring beaſt, and beaſts ſeeke not after dairity and decliate fare, but only that, as
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:18006:16"/>may be ſufficient to ſuſtayne nature, and are content with that, which is allowed them, by the diſcretion of their Maſter. And if the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter finde him to be wanton and deuouring, he muſleth him, that he neuer eateth, but when &amp; what in his diſcretion he ſhall like of. And ſo Siſter, in this reſpect I am content to be vſed and ruled like a beaſt, beſides the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> hath giuen me a bridell, which is made of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety, that I cannot eate but at wonted times, and that I deſire not, or looke to haue any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meate, or more daintely dreſſed then ſuch as ordinariley is ſet before me, and therewith I ſatisfie and content my ſelfe. Farther the <hi>Loue of God</hi> hath enjoyned me to this alſo, if I will ſerue and pleaſe him as I ought, to eate tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, and moderately, and only for neceſſary ſuſtenance, of that, what ſoeuer it be that is ſet before me: &amp; that for good manners I alwayes leaue ſome what in the diſh, thereby to ſhewe that more is allowed me, then I can well eate. For when all is eaten that is ſett before vs, it is as much as if you ſhoud ſay, my allowance is not ſufficient for mee, neither am I content therewith, therefore I deſire to haue more ſet on the table. And yet farther this rule is giuen mee to obſerue for the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> That I would and ſhould deſire leſſe to bee allowed mee, and the ſame worſe dreſſed, then the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:18006:16"/>allowance of my Siſters: and alwaies to wiſh ſomething to be wanting about me, &amp; therein to rejoyce for the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> By theſe &amp; like meanes, this malepert wanton maide is ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and driuen away from oleſting me. But when againe ſhee ſhall prouoke and ſturre me, to wanton pleaſure, not only by my owne fleſh, but alſo by others. I then fly from her, as faſt as I can ſecluding my ſelfe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, as may allure or entice me to pleaſure or concupiſcence. And againſt this aſſault, I find that to ſeclude my ſelfe from co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, is a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent remedy and moſt ſoueraigne preſeruatiue. Neither, doth this enemy aſſault me only in my body, but in my ſoule alſo, by ſuggeſting many ill thoughts. Againſt which alſo I vſe, the remedy of flight and hide my ſelfe, either in ſome corner of a rocke, or els in ſome vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frequented and ſolitary place, and there ſettle all my thoughts and cogitations, vpon my moſt ſweete Sauiour IESVS, calling to minde his moſt holy life, his paſſion, torments, and moſt bitter death. Alſo meditating vpon the cruell torments of Hell, the ſeuere and iuſt Iudgement of Almighty GOD. My owne departure from this miſerable world, and that of neceſſity I muſt appeere before the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeate of God: there to giue accompt of al my thoughts, wordes, and deeds. By theſe and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18006:17"/>like means, I ouercome, and put to flight, this forenamed maiden, who is the Lieuetenant of the caſtle of <hi>Pride.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHPATER 11.</hi> Of the concupiſcence of the eyes, and pride of life.</head>
               <p>YEt farther, to ouercome and cleane ſubdue this enemy, it is alſo requiſite to vanquiſh and conquer her companion, I meane <hi>Cocupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of the eyes,</hi> the ſteward or gouernour of the houſe of <hi>Pride:</hi> who alwaies giueth winges to <hi>Concupiſcence of the fleſh.</hi> For continually ſhee miniſtreth occaſion to her companion, who not-withſtanding, I ouercome with my holy purpoſe. For ſo ſoone as ſhee commeth, I ſay thus to her. Siſter, I am no better then a labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring beaſte, who neuer deſireth ſuperfluities, or more then is allowed him, but alwaies is contented with ſo much as is neceſſary, neither expecteth curioſity in that which is to be had of neceſſity, litle regarding whether his ſaddell and bridle be guilded or imbrodered, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſtable be curioſly adorned, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent if conueniently he may ſtand &amp; lie. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering then, that for the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count my ſelfe no better then a beaſte: I will alſo vſe my body as if it were a beaſt. And as the breaker, and rider, of a ſtiffe necked horſe, with the raines of a bridle, enforceth him to ſtoppe &amp; turne: ſo the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> hath brid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deled
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:18006:17"/>and tide me, with the bridell and chayne of <hi>Schamefaſtnes</hi> and <hi>Baſhfulnes:</hi> that I ſhall not curiuouſly ſee, &amp; couet the vanities of the world. For I ought not behold: that I ought not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire. And the <hi>Loue of God</hi> hath taught me to ſay, when I ſee a thing beautiful, pleaſing rare, ſinguler, or curious, I neuer will ſettle my loue on thee, but refuſe thee, and hold thee but as a meere vanity, therefore remebring the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines of my creation, I will not beſtowe my loue or fix, my affection, on ſo vile, ſo baſe, &amp; ſo tranſitory a thing: but on that which in it ſelfe is the only treaſure, and goodnes, and a beauty which neither age or ſickenes can ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh, I meane on my ſweete Sauiour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer IESVS; who demandeth of me my loue and affection, and may iuſtly chalenge the ſame as his owne. By theſe and like meanes this other Maide is ouercome. Now theſe two be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vanquiſhed in manner as I haue told you, there yet remayneth the laſt which is Miſtris of theſe, one more terrible, crafty and more ſuttle than the other, euer lying in wayte to hinder good actions, her name is called <hi>Pride of Life,</hi> who when ſoeuer ſhee commeth in hither a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, is alwayes attended with one or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand-maide, and ſtill bringeth with her ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Good or euell eſtimation.</hi> But ſtraight I ſay to her, a beaſt is no better to be accompted of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18006:18"/>than a beaſt neither is to be thought, worthy of honour, or eſtimation, but rather ignominy, and baſe contempt. Then ſometime ſhe commeth complayning to me, and ſaith: ſee how my ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours behaue themſelues towardes me, and vſe me, both in age, witte, and judgment: I am not their inferiors, yet they vſe ſuch and ſuch a one, with better reſpect then me. But pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently I finde out her craft and ſubtelty, and preuenting her, reply: A beaſt is not to be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed but baſely, and according to his Maſters diſcretion, to be whipped and beaten. For If at any time his Maſter ſhall vſe him but gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and play with him; he preſently will kicke, and forgette the duety due to him. Therefore a wiſe Maſter, and men of good gouernment, although they loue their beaſtes neuer ſo well: yet will neuer vſe extroardinary, and vndue familiarity to them: but alwayes carry them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with a kinde of ſeuere grauity; conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering ſuch familiarit6y is neuer attributed to humility, curteſie, loue, or affability, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſimplicity, and meere fondneſſe. For ſuch familiarity, doth rather hurt, then bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitte a beaſt. But a diſcreete, and wiſe Maſter, will rather endeuour with all poſsible dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, that his beaſt, or horſe, keepe his right way in their journey, and carry carefully, the burthen laide on their backes, then that the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18006:18"/>world ſhoulde thinke him fonde of them, or expect to be held a kinde, and louing Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and one that ſhould ſeeke to be prayſed of them. For by theſe meanes it might hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, as oft we ſee it, that either the Maſter to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the beaſt, or the beaſt forgette himſelfe towardes the Maſter, when the Maſter vſeth not ſuch reaſon, moderation, and diſcretion, as he ought: and that indiſcretion may giue occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the beaſt, to ſtray out of their boundes, farther then is allowed, and ſo by little and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, vſing an ill cuſtome, the Maſter ſhall not dare to direct, or gouerne according to the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority he hath ouer his beaſt; but if hee chaunce for their negligence to ſtrike or beate them, they preſently will reſiſt, and kicke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine at him. And then if the beaſt happen ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to caſt off his burthen, or elſe to carry it contrary to his Maſters minde, he muſt needes winke at it, and ſuffer him to goe, where, and as hee will himſelfe, and ſo, he to be obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to the beaſt, not the beaſt to him. Euen ſo Siſter, were it like to prooue vvith mee, if I ſhould yeelde to my owne ſenſuall affections, and be carried away with worldlie pleaſures, and vanities. But hee that loueth me, and hath care ouer me, doth with his diſcretion correct me, and bridle my vvill; that I fall not to open ſhame, and ſo bee vndone, but
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:18006:19"/>for the loue he carrieth to my ſoule, he doth chaſtice &amp; diſcipline my body at his diſcretion. Neither doe I my ſelfe wiſh to be vſed better then a beaſt. At ſome other time the ſame <hi>Pride of life,</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to me vnder the colour of <hi>Enuy,</hi> and complaineth thus. See how ſuch and ſuch an office is giuen to this, and that body: But no reckening or accompt is made of me. One is made gouerneſſe, and an other vndergouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the third the ſtewarde, and an other ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary; but my ſelfe, which am inferiour to none of them in yeares, or deſert, am neglected and nothing regarded at all. No place of credit is committed to me, wherein I might rule or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand ouer others: but alwayes I am dejected like a baſe kitchen Wench: Yea, I am made the vnderling of the meaneſt mayde in the houſe. And now I finde it true that they of beſt deſert; are commonly and for the moſt part leaſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered. For which cauſe hence forth, I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue leſſe: for I ſee, they that counterfette to be lambes are deuored of Wolues. Such and like complaints, doth ſhee oft make to me, as though I knew not the grounde from whence it came. To whome I anſwere; Siſter, I haue not giuen ouer and forſaken the world, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken my ſelfe to this ſolitary, and ſequeſtred life; thereby to rule others, and to moderate their cauſes. For ſince my firſt entrace heather,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18006:19"/>I haue vowed obedience: and therefore will performe that which I came hither to doe, and for which I was called, and which I vndertoke to accompliſh at my entrance. For God will neuer demande or aske accompte of me, how much I haue commanded and ruled others, or with how much honor, or how great offices I haue bin exalted in the world: but how hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and dutifully, I haue obeyed his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, and how willingly I haue humbled my ſelfe to my ſuperiours, and ſubjected &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſed my owne wilful &amp; ſtubborne rude mind. Therefore Siſter, I looke only to diſcharge and performe my owne office, in that place and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, to which I am called by God, and ſuffer others to looke likewayes to that charge of theirs, to which by Gods prouidence they are as my ſelfe called. Meane time this one thing I knowe for certayne, that I liue in the ſtate of aſſured ſaluation. (That is vnder true obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, humility, and ſubjection;) from which no man can fall, except he firſt clyme higher. And ſo hereof I haue no juſt cauſe to complayne, but rather to rejoyce, prayſe, &amp; yeelde daily thanks to Almighty God in that he hath debarred, and as it weare taken from me, the meanes and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of falling into the great perils and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; into which high offices and places of dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and preferment: are wonte to drawe, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:18006:20"/>throwe headlong men that ſeeke not after per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. Which is truely verified by this ſaying of Saint AVGVSTINE. <hi>I neuer founde Gods ire &amp; indignation more againſt me: then that it pleaſed him to appoint me a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mander ouer others.</hi> which truely <hi>Deſire</hi> ought not ſeeme ſtrange to thee. For as this wicked Wench, which beareth ſuch ſway in the houſe of <hi>Pride,</hi> is more prone ti wickednes, then all her fellowes: ſo muſt we (if throughly we will ſubdue her) vſe greater pollicy, ſtrength, and exerciſe of vertue. And to the end I protract not the time with circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, I now will deliuer no vaine diſcourſe to thee, but will inſtruct thee, by what meanes and groundes, thou ſhatl be able: to ouercome and put to flight, this crue of wicked Maydens. When any of theſe which ſo euer ſhee be ſhall come: and ſeeme to complaine as I haue decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before: be thou ruled by me and follow my example; As if <hi>Concupiſcence of the fleſh</hi> ſhall come &amp; ſay, I am allowed both to little meate, and yet that is cold, and not cleanly dreſſed: my wyne is ſowren, &amp; euery thing in our houſe is ſluttiſhly ordered, anſwere her but thus, ſhe that hath more then ſhe deſerueth, hath no cauſe to complaine: But thou deſerueſt not browne bread, &amp; cold water, which moſt holy &amp; Religious men haue beene contented to liue with. Therefore thou, which art ſo wicked, ſo
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:18006:20"/>ſloathfull, ſo diſdainefull, &amp; redy to complaine, voide of all deuotion, inconſtant, enuous amd vnthankefull to God: doeſt not deſerue the courſeſt bread and water. Which being true, &amp; yet hauing good bread, wyne, and other meate. Why ſhouldeſt thou complaine and haſt more then thy deſert? anſwere her a like if ſhe finde falte with her apparell. The like reply make alſo to <hi>Concupiſcence of the eyes,</hi> if ſhe ſeeke after or wiſh for this thing or that, &amp; ſay, O wreatch that thou art, who by thy owne deſert, art not worthy to enjoy the leaſt good that is. Yet haſt thou the vſe, of many deuout and vertuous books, by reading of which if thou wouldeſt, thou mighteſt become good. And although (neuertheles) one where ſufficient for thee. Yet haſt thou holy books of prayers and meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Tell me what is it thou deſireſt more? truly vnder a ſhewe of deſiring things of neceſſity: thou longeſt after and ſeekeſt for thinges of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluity, then the which nothing can be more oppoſite to the vowe of <hi>Pouertie.</hi> And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though thereby thy merit be not clearely loſt: Yet aſſure thy ſelfe, it is much impaired. And nothing can more diſhonor &amp; ſhame him, that profeſſeth in pouerty to imitate our Sauiour, then to haue leſſe vertue and taſt of Religion, then the Heathens who profeſſed the worſhip of falſe gods. Amongſt whome <hi>Seneca</hi> ſhewed
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:18006:21"/>him ſelfe a worthy Captayne and teacher of <hi>Pouerty,</hi> as we may finde if we reade what is writen of him. The ſame anſwere giue I to the third, that is, <hi>Pride of life,</hi> when ſhee commeth to me, with a deſire to be honored, loued, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pled of, exalted or preferred to ſome office. For then ſay I to her. Thou wreatched Wench, thou haſt more honor alredy then thou deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt: what haſt thou not through the number of thy ſinnes deſerued, to be throwne headlong downe, into the bottomoleſſe pit of hell? here to be partaker of the paynes of the damned, and yet behold, how much thou art honored of God, who not only doth tollerate thee, to liue amongſt his creatures, but hath admitted thee, alſo into his houſe and family: and willingly would haue thee, not only his ſeruant, but alſo if thou wouldeſt one of his daughters. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though thy owne vnworthineſſe be ſuch, that thou deſerueſt not to be reckened amongſt his inferiour ſeruants; yet hath he admitted thee into his priuate chamber: and willingly would haue thy preſence, both night &amp; day, that thou mighteſt freely talke with him, prayſe him, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him, and ſerue him; and that yet liuing here in this mortall life, thou amiſt be honored with the office of Angels, be choſen as one of his moſt ſpeciall Friends, ſit at his owne table, and feede on the foode him ſelfe feedeth. And
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:18006:21"/>now proude Wench what is it thou wouldeſt more, whither wouldeſt thou, through thy pride clyme? wouldeſt thou aſcend againe from whence thou once dideſt fall? that thou migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt be plunged as deepe in the bottomleſſe pit of hell, as is <hi>Lucifer</hi> thy father, whoſe pride threw him thither, what wouldeſt thou deſire? wouldeſt thou be God? Truely thou canſt not ſay that thou wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teſt any thing, open thy blinde eyes, and willingly confeſſe, that thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued greater benefits from God: than thy baſe deſerts, could any way chalenge, content thy ſelfe with that, which it hath pleaſed God to beſtowe on thee, and reſt ſatisfied with that eſtate and degree; which God by his ſeruants hath allotted to thee, and aſſure thy ſelfe that all thinges haue their effect: according to the prouidence and permiſſion of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER 12.</hi> By what meanes the other forenamed naughty Maides may be ouercome.</head>
               <p>NOw theſe thee principall enemies being cleane ouercome, <hi>Negligence</hi> their nurſe is eaſely vanquiſhed, who by a thouſand ſecret corners ſtealeth in here amongſt vs. Sometime at time of prayer: and ſometimes againe when we ſhould attend our works and labours. But ſtill I anſwere her with this or like anſwere. Siſter, a labouring beaſt, or a horſe, is not kepte
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:18006:22"/>in the ſtable, to be idle, liue eaſely, eate, drinke and ſleepe: but ſtill contentedly to labour, and take paynes. For except he be accuſtomed to labour, watch, and faſt; he groweth reſt and taketh ſtomacke, and will ſtrike at his Maſter, who ſo ſone as he perceaueth the ill conditions of his beaſt, preſently will beate him, and kicke him with a ſpure; Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo the <hi>Loue of God</hi> doth giue me a ſpurre, I meane <hi>Feare,</hi> wherewith when I wax ſloathfull he pricketh me. And I my ſelfe, who am but a ſeruant and a baſe vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall of this houſe, doe finde by proofe, that the Maidens of this place muſt be made to labour, and that they muſt not be fauoured, in that, which is commanded them, neither are to be ſuffered to liue idelly and wantonly, leaſt they growe to haue willes and repugne their ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours. For no creature is worſe then a proude and naughty ſeruant. Farther I demande whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhee thinke the Kingdome of heauen is to be obteyned, by eating, drinking, ſleeping and liuing idlely, which ſhee for ſhame cannot affirme. For our Sauour IESVS Chriſt walked a cleane contrary way. And if hee choſe a different way, to come to perpetuall felicity, and would ſuffer his bitter paſſion, and that way enter into glory: we likewiſe if we deſire to be partakers with him in glory, muſt alſo walke the path of patience, perſecution,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:18006:22"/>and pouerty. For ſo long as our head will goe one way, and our foote an other; our whole body can neuer bee directed the true way. Therefore, except we walke the path of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, affliction, labour, and contempt; we cannot thinke to be incorporated with him, but like corrupt members, muſt looke to be cut of, and throwen into hell fire: there to be conſumed. For except we be pertakers of our Sauiours paſſion, and ſeeke him, and ſuffer with him on the <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Croſſe: we muſt not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to pertake with him, any part of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or of his reſurrection. And to conclude ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we be partakers in this life with our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour IESVS Chriſt, who was whipped, ſpit vpon, deſpiſed, wearied and toyled with daily labours, poore, continually ſuffering hunger and thirſt, and at laſt enduring for our ſinnes his bitter paſſion, and ſuffering like an offender his paynes on the <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Croſſe; when not withſtanding hee was voide of all faulte, and of all innocents the moſt inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent that liued, except I ſay we imitate him herein: wee ſhall neuer finde him a ſweete, gentle, and friendly King of glory, and Prince of peace. Sometime this naughty Wench, I ſtill meane <hi>Negligence,</hi> creepeth into our O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratory, and there being weary, through laſines and ſloath, is perplexed as if ſhee where caſt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:18006:23"/>into a pariſon. Then ſay I, Siſter, true and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Religion, neuer complaineth of trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomnes or wearynes. What can I giue againe to our Lord, for the many benefits he hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed no me? What ca I doe or ſuffer enough for my ſweete Sauiour and redeemer IESVS, who of this exceeding loue and voluntary will, continewed on the <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Croſſe, not ſitting as I doe, but ſtreatched thereon, not clothed, but naked and trembling with cold, not in a houſe as I am, but in the open cold ayer: not hauing ſhooſe on his feete to keepe them warme, but nayled to the Croſſe, with great, boyſterowes, and cold yron nayles; all which paynes &amp; tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, he ſuffered for my ſake. Why then ſhould I ſhew my ſelfe ſo vngrate: that althopugh not all: Yet I will not ſuffer ſome what againe for him? he ſuffered here for my ſake, moſt excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding miſeries and painefull laboures, and thoſe not for an houre a night or a day, but all his life which was 33. yeares: he hong a liue three houres vpon the Croſſe, in exceeding paynes, moſt bitrter torments, and vnſufferable griefes, ſuch I ſay, whoſe like was neuer felte of man: &amp; yet he a moſt louing Sauiour eſteemed them but ſmall in regarde of his loue and kindnes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes me; and willingly would haue ſuffered yet greater than theſe, if neceſſity any wayes had vrged him to it. Conſidering then that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:18006:23"/>he is a King, and I no better then a moſt baſe bandſlaue; he God, and I durte, duſt, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption; he moſt holy and innocent, I a ſinner worthy of nought but puniſhment, then he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſuffered all this for mee: ſhall I grudge or repine to ſuffer a little for him? What? is the ſeruante to be regarded aboue the Maſter? No. Away then <hi>Negligence.</hi> For I muſt be buſied in thoſe thinges which are my fathers. Smale is the merit we ſhall receaue here: if we be not free from all wearineſſe of the place. For cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is he that doeth the workes of God ſloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and negligently. For God ſeeketh not ſeruice that is done him by compultion, neither is he delighted with vnwilling ſacrifices: but with that which is done with a willing minde, and proceedeth from a ſincere &amp; perfect hart. Now this old accurſed Wench, being put to her flight, we muſt alſo baniſh her fooliſh had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maydes: who by how much the more they be wicked and dangerous: by ſo much the more are they vehemente and ſtrong: and the leſſe we labour to mortifie and ſubdue them: the harder ſhall we finde it to baniſh and expell them. The firſt of them which is <hi>Malice,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companed with her daughter <hi>Anger.</hi> I anſwere in this manner, ſo ſone as ſhee aſſaulteth me. Siſter, <hi>Charity</hi> is patient and gentle, then taking the aſſiſtance of my husbande: <hi>my Purpoſe,</hi> I
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:18006:24"/>ſuppreſſe her &amp; againe. Nothing can be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted to this beaſt ſo ſeueare, but that ſhe hath deſerued farre greater correction. If then I haue deſerued greater puniſhments, I may juſtly ſay, I am fauourably ſpared, not being vſed in rigor according to my deſerts. And it is the part of a gentle beaſt, not to behaue himſelf ſtubbournly or rudely to his maſter, &amp; his whole family; but farre co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to that, quietly, modeſtly, &amp; gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to all men. For although perhaps to day his Maſter beate him: Yet to morrowe againe he will feede him wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tonly, &amp; wil behaue himſelfe toward him, like a louing &amp; kinde Maſter. And although perhaps outwardly he make no ſhew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es of affection; Yet inwardly doubtles he eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth him hightly; but yet diſſembleth his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and loue, leaſt hee take ſtomacke being pampered, and ſo kicke againſt his Maſter. BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides a beaſt doth ſone forget: any wrong or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury, &amp; is pleaſed againe, if his maſter but ſtroke him on the head, or the necke. So I my ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing iniured by any one of my Siſters, imagining I am a beaſt &amp; a baſe vaſſall, beare it paciently for the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> and ſuffer them to vſe me according to their pleaſures, aſſuing my ſelfe, that I cannot endure ſo many iniuries from them; as my owne vnworthines doth daily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue. And knowing farther, that our lord per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth for the heynouſnes of my ſins: that I be
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:18006:24"/>afflicted of them here in this life, ſo to learne to ſuffer afflictions for his ſake. And now ſe this maide, who thou ſayeſt doth wiſh me nothing, but hurt &amp; offence, &amp; that other who thou ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt doth ſecretly backbite me, &amp; al theſe other, of whom I am ſo hated as thou ſayeſt. Theſe I ſay hate not or malice me: but my vices, faultes, defectes, my malice, my ill manners and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, &amp; moſt of al my obſtinate, &amp; ſtubbourne will. Therefore I haue cauſe rather to thinke they loue me; for what herein they do, procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from zeale and a moſt holy purpoſe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue they any agreement with <hi>Malice,</hi> or thinke her meete to comfort with <hi>Vertue.</hi> Let vs now therefore conſider more iudicially. If I be, or would be thought the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dmaide of God. I muſt hate &amp; deteſt (euen from my hart) al my ſins, defectes, offences, &amp; imperfections, &amp; the proneſſe of my fraylty, which draweth me to theſe, which being true, why ſhould I malice or ſtomacke thoſe, which doe but that which my ſelfe am bound to. To conclude. Know that theſe who thou ſayeſt ſpeake ill of me, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract me, yet not withſtanding are my ſiſters, whom I am co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded to loue, not to hate. And therfore wil I do that which I am enioyned. Yet meane while let them conſider, and weigh with themſelues, why and to what end they afflict &amp; iniure me. Now againe at ſome other time ſhe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:18006:25"/>trieth me with <hi>Enuie</hi> a maide who vſeth a two edged ſword &amp; hurteth her Siſters both in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoule. This Wench is indeede a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous enemie, whoſe chiefeſt felicitie is in her Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters hurt: and is neuer more grieued then at there vertue and good life. Therefore when ſhee commeth to aſſault me, I ſay Siſter you complaine and ſeeme to be grieued that others in this world poſſeſſe greater riches, that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, are endued with more rare bewtie, that others haue more abundantly the giftes of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture then your ſelfe, but I take comfort and reioyce euen in that, and think my ſelfe happy in wanting them. For neither in this life or the life to come: Deſire I any thing but IESVS Chriſt my Sauiour, he is my treaſure, and the treaſure of Angels, he is my beauty, and the beauty of all creatures, he is my gayne, and the fountayne of all goodnes. Let others fix their loue where beſt it ſhall like them; I deſire only my Sauiour IESVS, and his loue euer doe I thirſt after with him is no difference twixt ritch and poore, he neuer diſtinguiſheth twixt beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull and fowle. Yet here thou complanieſt &amp; ſayeſt to me: this and that body abounde, and excell in wealth and beauty: ſuch &amp; ſuch hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines is giuen them, and not me. But on the contrary this I reply. Although theſe parties are poſſeſſed of theſe pleaſures; yet haue I my
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:18006:25"/>ſelfe thinges of greater eſteeme. For ſo noble and ſo great is the minde that I carry, that it skorneth to beſtowe loue or affection: on ſo baſe, ſo abject, and ſo tranſitory pleaſures. And conſidering that my name is called <hi>HUmility,</hi> by humility meane I to conquer my ſelfe. And I finde the ſeruants and children of God, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounde with theſe, and greater bleſsinges: but not my ſelfe, who am a baſe vaſſall, and no way worthy to be partaker thereof. Now <hi>Enuie</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhee preuayleth little with her former ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, vrgeth in an enuious manner, the gift of ſpirituall vertues, ſaying, beholde ſuch a ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter who thou knoweſt right well, is more gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to vertue and deuotion, then thou art; is more conuerſant with God, and more exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in contemplation, and is a Virgin of noted ſobriety, and modeſty. To whome I ſtreight anſwere. For what cauſe deſire I to be religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, or to be vertuous and deuoted to prayer? becauſe others ſhould thinke better of me, then they doe of my ſiſters, praiſe me, honour me, or admire my vertues? or elſe becauſe I would be more daintely fedde, cladde more coſtly, or abound in worldly pleaſures. No truely, but for this cauſe only, that I may ſerue and pleaſe God, and that my ſweete Sauiour Ieſus, may by me, and in me, be prayſed and honoured. Therefore is it my dutie, and that which I am
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:18006:26"/>bound to rejoyce in, when I ſee that my moſt louing Lord and Maſter, hath ſuch vertuous deuout ſeruants, that be wholy giuen to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and prayer, and endued with moſt rare ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines of life, and ſpende their time in Religious exerciſes. And I hold it my duety to pray to God, to giue them greater perfection, &amp; more abundat grace, whereby he may be more high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honored of them. For if I had but the leaſt taſt of Gods loue in me, wherein not my part &amp; duety to labour what I cold: that he might be knowen, honored and loued of all the world, &amp; to pray that he would beſtowe his grace on all men, whereby he might of them be continually honored? Therefore moſt accurſed Wench, flie farre from my ſight. Thou knoweſt not what charitable Loue is, conſidering thou art the daughter of that wicked, damnable, and falſe <hi>Apoſtata.</hi> For I would if it pleaſed God, that he depriued me of all ſpirituall &amp; corporall good, which of his bountie he hath beſtowed on me, and giue them to others, who with them would honor, and prayſe him more then I doe, who am ſo barraine and vnfruitfull a ſoyle, and haue receaued his grace and giftes in vaine. For I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire nothing in this world, but Gods prayſe and honor; and will daily ſeeke it, how dearely ſo euer I obtayne it. See then wreatched Wench how farre thou art deceaued. Markeſt thou
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:18006:26"/>not that God knoweth what he doeth? he ſeeth plainely that theſe veſſels, into which ſo abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly he infuſeth his bleſſings: be farre more pure, &amp; of a more humble ſpirit then I my ſelf. And therefore iuſtly hath denyed mee ſuch grace, ſeing right well that I am full of pride, &amp; a veſſell filled with anger and malice, which through haughtines of minde would proudely attempt: to ſcale (if it cold) the heauens them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, which duely pondered, I reſt contented with the will and pleaſure of my ſweete Lord IESVS, neither deſire I to finde ought elſe but him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 13.</hi> By what meanes we may expell all Malice from our ſelues.</head>
               <p>THe third daughter of <hi>Malice,</hi> is called <hi>Sloath,</hi> a moſt dangerous enemy, who is cold and laſie in ſpirituall exerciſes, and the ſeruice of GOD: Wherein conſiſteth the ſumme of our ſaluation. Her am I wonte to anſwere in this manner. Thou deſireſt Siſter and willingly wouldeſt perſwade me, neither to frequent the ſeruice of GOD: nor to vſe at all anie ſpirituall exerciſes. And therefore of purpoſe to conquer and ſubdue thee: I will ſpende more time, in watching, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and diume contemplation, where vnto ſhe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:18006:27"/>thus replyeth. Seeſt not thou thy ſelfe euen frozen with a cold deuotion, and to feele no whitte at all any zeale of Gods ſeruice in thee, but to vſe thy exerciſes, againſt thy owne vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary diſpoſition, which prouoketh iuſtly the indignation of God. Neither doeſt thou ought els but tempt God therein: who deſireth no vnwilling, or impulſiue ſeruices; but ſuch as proceede from a chearefull and willing minde. Then reply I againe. Away thou wicked wreatch, I perceaue thy meaning. Knoweſt thou not that at ſuch time I ſhew my loue grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to God, when I ſerue him with my owne will be it neuer ſo ſmall: then when I finde my ſelfe endued with extraordinary deuotion by him? art thou ignorant that God ſometimes of purpoſe withdraweth his grace: thereby to try and prooue our ſtrength? And then when he perceaueth vs to offer vp, and beſtowe on him that little deuotion which is remayning in vs: he doubleth his grace, &amp; heauenly conſolation in vs. Yet ſo, that finding our ſelues voide of inwarde ſenſible grace, we caſt not cleane away our good will, &amp; harty deſire. Therfore where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as thou askeſt why being ſo cold, and cleane voide of deuotion, yet I goe to pray (conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring as thou ſayeſt, that is but to tempt God) aſſure thy ſelfe, although I felt in me farre leſſe deuotion, and will to ſerue God: yet that not
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:18006:27"/>withſtanding I would frequent my prayers, and would ſet my ſelfe in the ſight of our Lord, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would I ſpeake or deſire ought of him, but ſtanding before him, would yeeld to him al due honor and reuerence, imagining him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be preſent in my ſight, and that I beheld him, and that there I ſtoode before his high, diuine, and fearefull Majeſty. That he who is the fire of loue would inflame my harte when he ſhould thinke conuenient. Therefore ſubmit I my ſelf to his holy will, &amp; am content with that which it ſhall pleaſe him to graunt me. And the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, fainter, and colder I finde my ſelfe, ſo much the nearer I will come to this fire. For if I will depart from it, then ſhall I finde my ſelfe farre colder then before. Therefore depart from me thou naughty Wench. For I doe not vſe &amp; fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent my daily prayers, my deuout contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ſpirituall exerciſes for my owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment, comfort, or delight; but only to this end, thereby to ſerue my Lord God &amp; honour him, conſidering I know we it to be his holy will and pleaſure, that I ſhould do ſo, and that I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe my ſelfe in all vertue, and holines to the honour &amp; prayſe of his holy name. Now when this wicked mayden with her practiſes cannot withdrawe me from the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> She ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a new courſe, and laboureth to winne my loue from my fellow Siſters. And taking the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:18006:28"/>aſſiſtance of her before named Nouices, <hi>Suſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and <hi>raſh iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> aſſaulteth me againe, &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwadeth me to hate and malice my ſiſters, and to carry a ſiniſter opinion of them, whereby I ſhould, either ſuſpect ſome ill in them, or elſe raſhly without ſome juſt cauſe condemne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: hence proceede contempt, repining, murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and detraction. But my ſelfe with the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of my <hi>Purpoſe</hi> marking her; preſently anſwere. It beſeemeth not ſo baſe, and ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject a maide as my ſelfe, to judge amiſſe of my ſiſters, or Superiours: neither lawfull for ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to intermeddle with ſacred veſſelles, or for beaſtes to come nigh the holy mountaine. It beſt beſeemeth me to account all my ſiſters, vertuous, and holy: but my ſelfe moſt wreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and full of foule ſinne. For it is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret to me, what all men are in the ſight of GOD, or in what manner they ſhall ende this mortall life. As for my ſelfe, I knowe right well, that my proneſſe to ſinne, and naughty appetites and deſires, woulde drawe me headlong to the pitte of hell, were I not preſerued by Gods diuine grace and mercie. Therefore knowe I right vvell what I may feare of my ſelfe and ſuſpect, that is, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my conſcience, my wordes, and deedes, be good: for I know my ſelfe, but am a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to others. And therefore ſo much as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertayneth
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:18006:28"/>to my fellowes, I will chooſe the ſafeſt courſe, that is, to thinke, and ſpeake all good of them; aſſuring my ſelfe thereby to gaine, but neuer to looſe. For nothing is more dangerous, then to be ruled by our owne will, and to refuſe a certainty, for an vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainety. Charity neuer thinketh amiſſe. And I finde it a charge great enough for me, to judge and diſcerne mine owne conſcience, my affections, my wordes, and deedes: and not to buſie my ſelfe in cenſuring theſe, not curiouſly to intermeddle in others actions. For vvho made me a Iudge, betweene God and my ſiſters? or betweene them and their owne conſciences? Truly no man. Avoide thou therefore, or haſt thou ought elſe to ſay? I plainely ſee thou art nowe ouercome, in ſeeking to ſuggeſt to me a ſuſpition of my ſiſters, vvhich is a moſt damnable, and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thing, and wholy repugnant to holy, and true meaning ſimplicity, whereof God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is the chiefeſt Author: with vvhome, no man may, or can at any time diſſemble. And if any man will ſay, that miſtruſt, or ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition may be admitted, and allowed in a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour, or any one that hath rule ouer o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and that my before alleadged rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons bee not ſufficient to refute him, let him aſſure himſelfe, that greate diligence,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:18006:29"/>much wiſedome, and carefull circumſpection, muſt therein be vſed: and that for this reſpect, as experience teacheth vs. If a man wil be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious of his wifes loyalty and honeſty, &amp; ſhe ſhall perceaue her husbandes diſtruſt: although perhaps before ſne were true to him, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt; yet may ſhe thereby be moued to diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty. Whereupon <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith, <hi>Suſpition is the cauſe of many mens ſinne.</hi> Therefore conſidering their intention and purpoſe is good: vvhy ſhouldeſt thou ſay their actions are naught, when in all likelihoode they might erre, either through ignorance, or ſimplicity, or want of experience, by ſome ſodaine motion, or hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane frailitie, or by ſome naturall imperfection which they are ſubject to. And in all theſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, no malitious, or fooliſh raſh judgment is to be giuen. But rather we muſt pittie and be ſorrowfull for ſuch imperfections, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them charitably for <hi>the Loue of God.</hi> But if this anſwere in reaſon will not ſuffice thee, becauſe thou ſaiſt their offences be too appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, then I ſay, God by his ſecret judgment ſuffereth ſuch thinges to happen, through whoſe prouidence, all thinges happen, that exceede our groſſe capacities. And as he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ceaſeth of himſelfe to doe good in vs: ſo ſometime permitteth he that we fall into ſuch temptations, which notwithſtanding hee oft
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:18006:29"/>turneth, either to the good of him that offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, or elſe, to the good of others, that haue ſeene it. Take thou heede therefore, thou proceede no farther herein. For hee that will take vpon him to judge others, vndertaketh that which appertayneth to GOD, or rather deſireth that himſelfe were GOD. Marke then wicked wreatch, what befell thy Father, when he aſpired to be like vnto GOD. Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a horſe, or any other labouring beaſt, is not of ſo malitious, or enuious a nature, that he ſuſpect, or holde in jealouſie his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe beaſtes, or cenſure their actions in a wronge vnderſtanding. But hath his minde onlie fette on his journey, and that hee may carry his burthen according to his Maſters minde. Neither regardeth hee if any of his fellowes erre in their way, but with an honeſt emulation will labour to his power, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe, or goe before thoſe he ought to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate: which if he cannot, yet will he keepe the way that he is directed, and not intermeddle with any but himſelfe. Neither will he ſeeke at any time to goe backe againe, or reſt in his journey; except thereby he may performe what he vndertaketh the better: neither grudge or repine at that he is commaunded, or back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite, or ſlaunder his Maſter, or any other. Conſidering then, that I haue made my ſelfe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:18006:30"/>a beaſt for <hi>the Loue of God:</hi> I muſt humble and carry my ſelfe like a beaſt, and intermedle with nothing but with my ſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 14</hi> Of other exerciſes of Humility.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DEſire</hi> hauing with admiration attentiuely marked the exerciſes of <hi>Humilitie,</hi> ſaid vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to her. Now finde I that true Lady Mother, which I haue heard: that <hi>Humilitie</hi> contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in her ſelfe, all juſtice, vertue, peace, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe, and happineſſe, and all ſpirituall, and temporall comfort, and contentation. Yet far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I deſire to know one doubt; whether theſe naughty wenches, when they come in here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, be knowne by ſight: or whether they take the habit of your Virgins, and ſo by ſubteltie intermingle amongſt them: or what meane and way you haue to diſcouer them. HVM. Truly Son, thy queſtion is a matter of great importance. Knowe therefore that the <hi>Diuine goodneſſe</hi> hath hanged vp a Lampe in the mideſt of our chamber, called <hi>good Conſcience,</hi> which burneth day and night, beeing kindled with the oyle of his <hi>Mercy,</hi> and the wicke, or cotton of <hi>holy Scripture.</hi> Farther, this Lamp is to be tyed with a rope, called <hi>Watch ouer our harts,</hi> to a nayle, which is called, <hi>Watch ouer our ſences:</hi> Now ſo long as this Lamp is kindled and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth: we neuer feare them, becauſe we doe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:18006:30"/>know them. And although they inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingle themſelues with the good: yet by their gate, we eaſely diſcerne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For they be croke ſhouldered, and hault, and limp in their paſe, ſo that they neither can goe ſpeedely, nor accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the vowe they made. But if through our ſinnes this Lampe be extinguiſhed, or by our negligence the nayle ſlippe out, or the rope chaunce to breake, or our Lord for our deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits withdrawe the oyle (which he neuer doth except we firſt ſhedde it) then are we in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and all things fall out to the worſt for vs. Therefore pray wee dayly to our Lord God, that it will pleaſe him of his goodneſſe, to lighten our Lamp, ſaying with the Prophet <hi>Dauid: For thou O Lord doſt lighten my Lampe: lighten</hi> O <hi>God my darknes.</hi> DE. God I beſeech him, giue you his grace &amp; charity: for you haue greatly comforted my ſpirits. HVM. Take nowe for thy companions theſe Virgins here, &amp; let them ſo long accompany thee, vntil thou be throughly armed with true feare: that if by chaunce theſe wicked we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches fortune to meete thee, they aduenture not to ſhew their hate &amp; malice againſt thee, nor endeuour to withdraw thee from among vs. Here haſt thou <hi>Seueritie</hi> againſt <hi>Concupiſcence of the fleſh</hi> the firſt. <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood or ſtrength</hi> againſt <hi>Concupiſcence of the eyes</hi> the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. <hi>Humility</hi> againſt <hi>Pride of life</hi> the third.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:18006:31"/>
                  <hi>Diligence</hi> againſt <hi>Negligence,</hi> the fourth. <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> againſt <hi>Malice,</hi> the fift. And now the grace of God be alwayes with thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 15.</hi> Of the vertues, that be daughters of Humilitie.</head>
               <p>HVM. Thus by the grace of Almighty God, and the helpe and aſſiſtance of my forenamed husbande: Iouercome and ſubdue my enemies, and my ſelfe. <hi>Deſire</hi> much pleaſed with this diſcourſe of <hi>Humility,</hi> ſaid to her: DE. I entreate you Lady Mother, that it may ſtand with your good likeing, that I may viſit and be acquainted with the Virgins of this ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety. HVM. Proceede my Sonne aſſiſted with Gods grace, moſt willingly I aſſent to thy deſire. And thou daughter, which art ſteward of this houſe, accompany him, and ſhewe him the houſe, and bring him to the Celles of euerie Virgin. This ſaid, <hi>Deſire</hi> departed chearefully out, of the Lady Mothers chamber, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with <hi>Nihili-penſio</hi> or <hi>Contempt of all vnne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary cares.</hi> Who was ſteward of the houſe, &amp; gouerneſſe of the Nouices, and was carried by her to the Cell of a Virgin, who was the firſt, &amp; eldeſt daughter of <hi>Humility,</hi> called <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> of whome he asked the manner, of her life and conditions. CONF. I am the daughter of our Mother <hi>Humility,</hi> and the ſcholler of this
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:18006:31"/>Virgin here our gouerneſſe, with whome I oft frequent, and am much delighted with her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity, and acknowledge my ſelfe what I am, according as I finde my ſelfe in examining my conſcience. <hi>Deſire</hi> thought this Virgin of rare and ſinguler vertue, and departing from her was brought into the Cell of an other daughter of <hi>Humility,</hi> whoſe name was <hi>Deſire of Conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt,</hi> who receauing him courteouſly, was asked of <hi>Deſire,</hi> both her name and conditions. VIR. my name is <hi>Deſire of Coutempt,</hi> becauſe I deſire, not to be honoured or eſteemed of any man. <hi>Deſire</hi> wondered hearing this Virgin deſire to be ſo much contemned, conſidering how diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent it was from the mindes of moſt men. But admired her vertues, finding, ſhe did it for the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> And leauing her, was brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Cel of an other Virgin, whoſe name was <hi>To reioyce in being contemned.</hi> Of whome <hi>Deſire</hi> being entertayned, demaded likewiſe her name and conditions. VIR. My name is <hi>To reioyce to be contemned.</hi> For I wiſh to be deſpiſed, ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and iniured for the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> DE. Inſtruct me I beſeech you how I may attayne to this vertue, for ſuch is the haughtines of my proude minde, that I doe not only reioyce: but am grieued and repine if I be contemned, ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, deſpiſed, or iniured, VIR. That pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from want of <hi>Humility,</hi> whoſe vertue
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:18006:32"/>is to contemne, and neglect her ſelfe for the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> And truely this is an apparant token that thou aboundeſt vvith pride, and ouer much ſelfe loue. But ſeing thou art by GOD conducted hither into this Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, we will willingly inſtruct thee, in all kinde of vertue, and altering thy habit, will make thee a newe man, and will direct and inſtruct thee, how to ſpeake with the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> for other wayes thou ſhalt be ſure for to looſe thy labour. Therefore if thou wouldeſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne to my vertue, thou muſt imprinte in thy hart my Siſter, <hi>Deſire to bee contemned,</hi> thinking and determining thus with thy ſelfe, henceforth will I deſire to be ſcorned and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, and to be neglected of all men for the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> This deſire once throughly fixed in thy hart, thou ſhalt by degrees at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne to my vertue, through prayer ſtudy, and diligent endeuour. And although at the beginning thou ſhalt endure ſome la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and payne: by ſtriuing to ſubdue and maſter thy owne appetites: Yet perſeuer to the end, and thou ſhalt gette the victorie. In ſo much that thou ſhalt rejoyce; when any thing is ſaid or done to thee, contrary to thy likeing. Farther thou muſt by degrees enforce thy ſelfe to deſire, to be ſcorned, deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſed and contemned. For it is moſt true, that
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:18006:32"/>no man can be humble, that is not juſt. And he that ſhall not deſire, to be deſpiſed, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, mocked, and debaſed, this man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be called juſt. DE. How may that be, that whoſoeuer deſireth and wiſheth not to bee deſpiſed, ſhould bee ſaid to bee a man vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt. For by that accompt, wee ſhall finde but fewe juſt men, and in my opinion this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be true. VIRG. I will eaſely prooue what I haue ſaid. It cannot be denied but that hee is juſ, which giueth to each man, that which is right: if therefore man can chalenge nothing elſe for himſelfe, but to be contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſcorned, mocked and debaſed; hee is not juſt which deſireth, not to bee ſo vſed. DE. I would heare you prooue that, and ſhewe plainely how, nothing but contempt is due to man. VIRG. I will. Firſt there is no queſtion, but that all that which is good, ought be loued, honored, deſired, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and how much greater and better it is, ſo much the more it ought to be loued: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie wayes, that what ſo is naught, ought to be deſpiſed, hated, rejected, and ſuppreſſed. Now if it be true that euery men is ill, it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth that of right hee muſt bee contemned and deſpiſed. DE. Tell mee how all men are to be ſaid to be naught. VIRG. Only GOD is good, therefore all men are naught.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:18006:33"/>DE. I cannot yeald to that concluſion. VIRG. Logitians ſhall proue, that none is good but God: and whatſoeuer is not God, is not good, but ill. And if man be ill, that all ſhame, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, and contempt is due to him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 16.</hi> How all creatures are good, and yet none is good, but God himſelfe.</head>
               <p>DESIRE. I am not yet reſolued by thy alleadged reaſons, conſidering thou ſaiſt that God is good, and that whatſoeuer is not God, is not to be ſaid good. And the holy Scripture ſaith, that God ſawe all thinges that he had made, &amp; that they were not only good, but very good. Farther, conſidering God is good (as indeede he is the chiefe goodneſſe it ſelfe, and the efficient cauſe, and beginning of all thinges created) all things that he hath made muſt of neceſsity be good, that the worke be anſwerable to the workeman that made it. Whereupon it followeth, that whatſoeuer God hath made muſt of neceſsitie be very good. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, conſidering man is the moſt excellent of all corporal creatures, it is plaine, that he is not only good, but very good. And then if he be good, by thy owne rule it followeth, that both honour and loue, are due to him. VIRG. I will not maintaine a long diſputation with thee, for that diſagreeth with the rules of <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility,</hi>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:18006:33"/>only I will open what I haue ſaid more at large, that thou maiſt better vnderſtand my meaning. The ſcripture ſayeth, that none is good but only God. Which is thus to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, that only God is eſſentially good; &amp; to be good is only proper to him. And what ſoeuer he hath made, may be ſaid to be good, participating in goodnes, giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to them by God: For whatſoeuer goodnes they haue is Gods, not their owne. So when thou ſeeſt good giftes beſtowed on any creature from aboue, thou muſt honor and loue ſuch a creature; But this honor and loue muſt be referred to God, and not to the creature. Therefore our ſelues and all creatures are to be loued of vs, becauſe they be good in their eſſence or being, as the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God &amp; this is, to loue God in his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Let not therefore any man deſire, to be prayſed or honored for his owne ſake: but for the goodneſſe which God hath beſtowed on him: attributing and referring it all to GOD. For it is one thing that man hath from God, but an other which he hath of him ſelfe. From God he hath what good ſoeuer is, but from him ſelfe whatſoeuer is ill. He hath from God that he repreſenteth, and carrieth his Image &amp; like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. But of him ſelfe through wicked life and euell manners, he is made altogither diſlike to God. Alſo it is giuen to him by the grace of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:18006:34"/>God, to deſire to be good and endued with ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue: but of himſelfe hee deſireth ill, and doeth thoſe thinges that moſt diſpleaſe God. From hence we learne that thoſe thinges which are beſtowed on man from aboue, are greatly to be honoured, and highly to be loued, which are the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditions of his creation &amp; his natural bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, &amp; yet not to be loued for his owne ſake, but for the honor of God: co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary thoſe things to be hated, which are in man himſelfe, as his vices offences &amp; al other imperfections. So that diuerſly we honor &amp; deſpiſe, loue &amp; hate ſome thinges, in one &amp; the ſelfe ſame man. And be he endued with neuer ſo great vertue &amp; deuotion: Yet let him be aſſured, that of himſelfe he hath nothing that is good, and ſtill let him deſire that in regarde of the good giftes beſtowed on him by god, be they vertue, deuotion or other ſpirituall benefits, that God alone be honored and loued for them, and that all prayſe be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to him as to the fountayne of all goodnes. But for the ſinne in him, which he knoweth to be his owne, let him deſire to be deſpiſed, hated, and contemned of all men. This doing I ſay he is to be accompted iuſt. But if euery iuſt man ſhall deſire to be contemned after this ſort, how great is the iniuſtice of a man deſiled with ſinne, not only not to deſire to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned as I haue ſaid: but to deſire and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:18006:34"/>to be honoured and extolled: Let not therefore a wreatched ſinner thinke and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that he hath ſhewed much <hi>Humility,</hi> in deſiring to be contemned, or let him not be the better perſwaded of him ſelfe, therefore conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the moſt holy, vertuous, and deuouteſt man is bound of duty to deſire as much.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 17.</hi> Of the ſame.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DEſire</hi> was not a little pleaſed herewith, and ſaid to this Virgin. DE. I beſeech you Siſter inſtruct and direct me, by what meanes I may attayne to this holy Deſire. VIR. Two wayes there bee, by which thou maiſt obtayne it, which are the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> and a <hi>holy Purpoſe,</hi> to object &amp; imbaſe thy ſelfe like to a labouring beaſt: to which <hi>holy Purpoſe</hi> our <hi>Gouerneſſe</hi> hath wedded her ſelf. And if thou wilt be ruled by my directions, thou ſhalt finde thy ſelfe not a little aſſiſteth thereby. DE. Moſt willingly will I be inſtructed by you. VIR. Then aſſure thy ſelf that the <hi>Loue of God</hi> whome I perceaue thou art ſo deſirous to finde, hath no more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous &amp; hurtful enemy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is thy owne body, Inure thou thy ſelfe therefore daily to this cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome that euery morning thou ſay to thy ſoul. Let me ſee now ſoule, how thou wilt this day hate thy body, which is ſo great an enemy, to thy ſweete Sauiour and Creator IESVS,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:18006:35"/>and how much thou wilt deſire, that it may be deſpiſed, afflicted, tormented, and ſcorned. At night likewayes ſay thus againe. Now ſhewe me my ſoule how this day, thou haſt deſpiſed, thy body ſo rebellious againſt thy moſt ſweete Lord IESVS, &amp; how thou haſt deſired that it might be afflicted, and iniured of all men, and haſt laboured that nothing be pardoned it, but haſt carried thy ſelf moſt ſeuere againſt it. This doing deare Brother, and ſtill conuerſing in theſe good thoughts, and euer perſeuering in this thy deſire, this only exerciſe in time will bring thee, to an exceeding perfection of perfit <hi>Humility,</hi> and will teach how to ouercome, and put to flight the moſt dangerous enemy, and be trayer of thy ſoule; and in concluſion thou ſhalt thereby attayne, to ſo greate hatred of thy ſelfe: that thou ſhalt wiſh &amp; labour to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned and deſpiſed. And when hereafter thou ſhalt happen to be contemned of ſome man; then ſticke faſt to me, &amp; forſake not my ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. But with rejoycing and thankes giuing to God, ſay thus to thy ſelfe. Now thankes be to God, who hath reuenged me of my enemie. <hi>Deſire</hi> being much contented with the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Virgin, tooke leaue of her, and was brought into the Cell of an other daughter of <hi>Humility,</hi> whoſe name was <hi>Simplicity,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauing him louingly, was asked by him her
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:18006:35"/>name, vertue, and conditions. SIMP. My name is <hi>Simplicitie.</hi> My office and conditions is to behaue my ſelfe ſimply, ſincerely, and plainely towardes all men: and to conceane no hurte or ill meaning of any thing, that I ſhall happen to heare or to ſee: but to thinke all thinges to be done rightly and holylie, and to thinke ill of no body but my ſelfe: For I euer ſuſpect and feare my ſelfe, and continually watch ouer my thoughts and deſires, ſtill loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king into my ſelfe, and holding open the right eye of perfect wiſdome, whereby I may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewe and auoide all euell, and our Mother <hi>Humility,</hi> be made more ſtrong in her vertue. DE. What? is not <hi>Humilitie</hi> endued with all kinde of vertue, except thou hold, and keepe open thy eye. SIMP. No conſidering <hi>Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity</hi> without <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> is of no eſtimation, but hurteth rather then helpeth. For the <hi>Loue of God</hi> loueth no man, but ſuch as ſhall came with true knowledge and <hi>Wiſdome.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 16.</hi> Of the manners and conditions of Simplicitie.</head>
               <p>DESIRE. Now then I deſire to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed by you my Siſter, how and in what manner you behaue your ſelfe, ſimply towardes all ſortes of people. SIMP. In three thinges, which are, in thought, worde, and deede. Firſt I neuer vſe to thinke vpon thoſe
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:18006:36"/>things: which are aboue my knowledge &amp; ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, neither deſire I, th honors, eſtimations, &amp; vanities of this world, but ſtil perſeuer in this humble thought, that I am the moſt abject of al the world, and vnworthieſt that liueth to be the ſeruant of God: thinking all other holy &amp; ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, &amp; repleniſhed with al kindes of grace &amp; vertue. Secondly I reſolue to vſe no flattering, feyned, or deceiptful wordes, but a playne affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation or elſe a deniall, that is only, yea, yea: or no, no. For whatſoeuer is more, proceedeth not of good, but from the roote &amp; grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of vanity. Thirdly I haue determined to buſie my ſelfe, in no worldly, curious, or vayne workes, but in ſuch only as are ſimple, and yet neceſſary, leaſt thereby I be drawne to vanity of ſingularity, &amp; thereby be expelled &amp; kept out from he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. For to doe an action ſimply, bringeth <hi>Humility of hart,</hi> but otherwayes to doe is moſt ful of perils. DE. As how. SIMP. Thou ſhalt vnderſtand <hi>Deſire,</hi> that our gouernes &amp; Lady Mother <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie,</hi> hath ſet me here, &amp; impoſed this charge on me, to keepe ſafely in this Monaſtery two rare Iewels which are remayning here, which are the one, <hi>Purity of hart,</hi> the other <hi>Innocency</hi> The valew whereof is of ſo high eſteeme, that they cannot be priſed according to their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines. For the obteyning whereof this mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, &amp; the other ſeated in this deſert: where at
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:18006:36"/>the beginning fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded &amp; built. And what good ſoeuer we doe, is referred to the getting &amp; kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping theſe Iewels. But if <hi>Curioſity, Vanity,</hi> or <hi>Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularitie</hi> ſhould enter by the gate of our hart, our mouth, or elſe our action they would ſteale &amp; carry away both theſe Iewels fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if any of our Virgins ſhall not imploy all their thoughts, words, &amp; workes to get &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue theſe: we accompte them fooles, not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtading what they vndertake. DE. Why do you ſo carefully preſerue theſe Iewels conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that by your profeſſion you haue vowed pouerty? it is dangerous leſt you ſhould offend in couetouſnes, keeping ſuch vnneceſſary and pretious iewels, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering many poore people may ſterue through want of them. SIM. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou art deceaued: For although in poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, louing, or deſiring ritches or goods, a man may ſin in couetouſnes, according to the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for which he ſhal deſire them: yet can there be no ſin in poſſeſſing theſe Iewels, in regarde that we deſire, keepe, &amp; preſerue them only for the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> therwith to honor &amp; ſerue him, at ſuch time as it ſhal pleaſe him to come hither amongſt vs; or when we conuerſe with him in his holy houſe. Ruſt and canker, conſume and ſpoile other worldly Iewels: But theſe that are kept &amp; layde vp in our harts, no ruſt, no ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ker, no corruption can conſume. For no man can ſe
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:18006:37"/>them but he, which doth poſſeſſe them. DE. If he ſhall lay them open, cannot ruſt then hurt them? SIMP. No: for if purpoſely hee ſnew them, that others ſhould ſee them, then doth not he poſſeſſe them any longer. For he that hath them doth not thinke, he hath them but laboureth ſtill that he may get them. And many times our Sauiour doth ſo beſtow them, that he that hath, them doth not know he hath them. Which our moſt louing Lord doth to this intent, that preſumption and ſelfe liking which lurke in mens harts, ſhould not ſecretly ſteale them and take them away. Therefore whoſoeuer doth moſt of all other poſſeſſe them: doth with al ſecrecy that he can conceale them, and hide them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER 19.</hi> How Purity of hart, and Innocency may be preſerued.</head>
               <p>DESIRE much delighted with this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of <hi>Simplicitie,</hi> ſaid to her. DE. tell me by what meanes theſe pretious Iewels may be preſerued. SIMP. There is one thing amongſt others very neceſſary, for nouices and young folkes, and the ſame not vnprofitable for thoſe that be of more yeares, which is to fly and to locke, and to keepe cloſe our gates from much company. For if a man will vſe the familiarity, and fellowſhippe of many, and take
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:18006:37"/>delight to heare and to ſee many things, he ſhal hardly be able to preſerue theſe Iewels, for our mindes many wel be compared to a looking glaſſe, which repreſenteth the likeneſſe of anie thing ſet before it, or to wax which reteyneth the impreſsion of a zeale. DE. But how can one fly or ſhut the dores that liueth continually in a Religious ſociety? for ſuch a perſon hath occaſion to goe into many places, and the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth ſometimes one thing, ſome times an other, and ſuch a party is enforced to talke, with many &amp; often commanded to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe with all ſortes of people. For other wayes he ſhall be accompted ſinguler, and ſingularity although it be couered with a ſhew of holines and vertue: Yet is it hatefull, and ought to be eſchewed and ſhunned. SIMP. It is true as thou ſayeſt, we muſt heare, ſee, and ſay manie thinges for obedience, which if we did of our owne accorde and deſire, we ſhould offende. But when obedience and charity doe moue vs there vnto (prouided we be not negligent but doe our beſt endeuours,) there is no doubt to be had for looſing theſe Iewels. DE. What muſt we doe in doing our endeuours? SIMP. It is needful that whoſoeuer would keepe theſe Iewels of <hi>Puritie &amp; Innocencie,</hi> &amp; either for obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience or neceſſity cannot be ſecluded, nor liue in ſolitary or vnfreque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted places, it is neceſſary
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:18006:38"/>I ſay that he make me his companion, who tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting to my fellowſhippe, (he trauaile all the world about) yet needeth not feare to looſe theſe Iewels. DE. I deſire you to explaine your meaning by ſimilitudes, for ſo, ſuch as be but ſimple ſhal the better vnderſtand you. SIMP. It is requiſite for a man, that will haue <hi>Puritte of hart and Innocencie,</hi> (which are the eſpeciall manes to attayne to all vertues, and by which meanes to attayne to all vertues, and by which we may readily come to all perfection, perfect charity, and the chiefe marke which we ſtoote at, that is the <hi>Loue of God.</hi>) It is neceſſary as I haue ſaid to attayne to theſe vertues, to fly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, &amp; ſhut the gates againſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany. If he cannot do ſo, then let him take me a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panion, and in all thinges that he ſhall heare or ſee, ſtill keepe me in his right eye. And when the left eye ſhall ſeeke to behold any thing, that may taſt of couetouſnes, or of fooliſh, or of raſh judgement, then let him behold the ſame with the right eye of <hi>Simplicitie,</hi> thinking &amp; perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thus ſimply with himſelf. That euery man and woman, brother &amp; ſiſter &amp;c. is the Angell and Sonne of Almighty God, &amp; that all other thinges are certayne inſtruments or Organnes, which without intermiſſion doe laude &amp; praiſe their Creator. And by the ſame rule what ill ſo euer he ſhal heare, or ſe of his neighbour, let the right eye excuſe it, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſter it to the beſt. And
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:18006:38"/>let him prayſe &amp; glorifie God, for all his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which the laſt eye of couetouſnes ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure him to deſire, calling to minde the beauty, comlines &amp; goodnes of his Creator, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his proprieties, ſaying thus to him ſelfe. I will not deſire, or loue any thing created to any other end, but that in them, and with them I may loue and prayſe God, likewiſe in all his wordes and actions, it is very neceſſary that he aſſociate himſelf with me. DE. How ſhall we ſay, all the actions of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are done in ſimplicity. SIMP. When their intention ſhal be ſimple, pure; and right, and all that they doe being of it ſelfe good, ſhall be alſo juſt &amp; right, in all cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of time, place &amp; perſon, &amp; ſhal not do any thing, but either for the honor &amp; prayſe of God, or for the good of the ſoule, or body of himſelfe, or his neighbour, or els for the benefit of the whole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth, he that doth thus, walketh ſimply in al his actions. And whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhal chooſe &amp; keepe <hi>Simplicity</hi> for his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, he liueth &amp; walketh ſecurely &amp; happily.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 20.</hi> Of Pouertie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DEſire</hi> much pleaſed with this diſcourſe of <hi>Simplicitie,</hi> taking his leaue of her was brought to the Cell of an other of <hi>Humilities</hi> daughters, whoſe name was <hi>Pouerty,</hi> of whome being louinglie entertayned, he ſpake
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:18006:39"/>to her as followeth. DE. I am not a little de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted with your fellowſhip &amp; acquaintance, aſſuring my ſelfe, how dearely you are beloued of <hi>the Loue of God,</hi> &amp; therefore deſire to know your conditions and courſe of life. POV. I contemne &amp; refuſe for <hi>the Loue of God,</hi> to haue or poſſeſſe any worldly or tranſitory goods. DE. In what thing then, conſiſteth your joy and only comfort? POV. My only treaſure and riches is for <hi>the Loue of God,</hi> to be poore, and poſſeſſe nothing. DE. I cannot but great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meruaile thereat, conſidering that as I haue heard of others, this Monaſtery was firſt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and built by a Lord, that is the moſt noble, rich, and bountifull of al the world. What then ſhould be the reaſon, or his intention, that the inhabitantes of it, ſhould be ſo poore and nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy? neither vnderſtand I how your pouertie can be ſo acceptable to him. POV. I will tell you. That Lord, which is founder &amp; buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of this Monaſtery, is King and Maſter of all the world, and hath, and keepeth his riches and treaſures all in his owne handes. And yet notwithſtanding, it is his will and pleaſure, that we ſhould liue in continuall pouerty, to the end we fixe not, or ſettle our loue and affection, on any other creature, but on himſelfe. He could if it ſo pleaſed him, beſtow abundance on vs: but to his beſt beloued, he doth not; becauſe they
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:18006:39"/>ſhould loue him only, and hate this world, and the vanities thereof. And wee cannot aske a more manifeſt token of his loue towardes vs, then that he ſuffereth vs to bee in neceſsity in this miſerable life, &amp; ſendeth vs not thoſe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, which fraile fleſh would couet. And yet farther, he will haue vs ſpend our liues in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty, leaſt temporall, and needles cares ſhould ouercome our weake mindes; but will, that we ſhould ſerue him, with quiet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented thoughts and not be mooued, either with loſſe, or gaine of worldly commodities, or too much rejoyce or lament, in proſperity, or aduerſity, with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer great mirth, or exceeding ſorrow: but haue our harts ſtill vnited to him; in peace, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentation? without any miſlike. For ſuch is the diſpoſition of <hi>the Loue of God,</hi> that he will not inhabit but in ſtill and ſequeſtred places. DE. What is the eſpecial vertue that is in you. POV To conforme and frame my ſelfe according to my ſiſters, amongſt whome I liue. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I deſire to poſſeſſe nothing: yet to keepe out and expell an enemy of ours, that ſeeketh daily to enter amongſt vs, and deſtroy our garden, and eate vp our fruit, whoſe name is <hi>Singularity:</hi> our Lady Mother will haue mee liue like my other ſiſters. And yet that I looſe not the reward of my vertue ſhee hath mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried me to a holy <hi>Purpoſe,</hi> whoſe mame is, <hi>to
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:18006:40"/>aske nothing.</hi> And farther, ſhe telleth me if I will attaine to perfection, that I muſt reſt content with that which is giuen me, be it much, or litle; and accept as thankfully, of groſſe and homely diet, as of that which ſhall be prouided at the coſtlieſt price, and to leaue part of that which is alowed to me, and to be content for the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> to take ſo much only, as neceſsity ſhal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire. DE. That is, as if one ſhould deſire to be better then good, or labour to doe more then he were bound to doe. For if I rightly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it, that Lord which hath founded and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected this Monaſtery, commaundeth you to haue the ſpirit of pouerty, as the Prophet ſaith. <hi>If thou abound in riches, beware thou ſettle not thy loue on them.</hi> Whereby I gather, that the vertue of pouerty, doth not conſiſt in hauing, or poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsing much, or little: but in the loue, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt we take in them. POV. I doe not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but that the ſpirit of pouerty conſiſteth in the minde, yet notwithſtanding it is much ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> to poſſeſſe nothing: conſidering our loue and affection to rich and beautifull thinges, is ſo fraile and prone, that hardly can wee haue them, without fixing our loue on them. Leaſt therefore ſuch worldlie riches ſhoulde gayne ſome parte of our loue from <hi>the Loue of God</hi> which is already but ſmal towards him, it is good (as the ſaying is) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:18006:40"/>the ſtrawe farther from the fier. For the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> doth chalenge of duety all the loue of man wholy to him ſelfe, and manie there bee that herein flatter themſelues, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I doe not immoderatelie loue this or that thing, neither would I to much ſorrow if it where taken from me. But beleeue mee affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and loue is ſo ſubtle a thing, that hardly are men founde not louing what they poſſeſſe. Neither can we haue a better example hereof then our SAVIOVR CHRIST him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, who when he could haue poſſeſſed the whole ritches of the world, without feare to loue or affect them extraordinarily: yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member how needely, and poorely not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe liued, but alſo his Bleſſed Mother and his Holy APOSTLES. Which, howe can we anie other wayes conceaue: but that we muſt neither affect, or poſſeſſe any world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ritches: For which cauſe I haue clearely forſaken all ſuch vnneceſſary thinges, as I v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to haue with me in my Cell reteyning no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſ, but the Image of my ſweete SA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VIOVR hanging naked on the <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Croſſe, thereby to remember his great loue to mee. I once vſed to keepe many books with mee, but nowe poſſeſſe only a Bible, the life of SAINCTES, and the life of my SAVI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OVR IESVS, with ſome fewe other for
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:18006:41"/>my deuotions. And reſt fully contented to meditate on ſweete Ieſus, and to buſie my ſelfe with the booke of his holy life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 21.</hi> Of Obedience.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DEſire</hi> receauing no leſſe contentment from this Virgin, tooke leaue of her, and weas brought to the Cel of an other daughter of <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mility,</hi> called <hi>Obedience.</hi> To her <hi>Deſire</hi> yealded very great reuerence, in that ſhe ſeemed to him to be of high dignity, and authority, &amp; of great eſtimation with <hi>the Loue of God,</hi> and more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued of him, then her other ſiſters. Now <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire</hi> for reuerence ſake, offering to kiſſe her hand, was denyed of her, in regard that being the daughter of <hi>Humility,</hi> ſhe would not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe either reuerence or honour, to be ſhewed to her, but willing <hi>Deſire</hi> to ſitte downe by her, he asked of her, her orders and conditions. OBED. I am married to a holy <hi>Purpoſe,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>to omitte nothing I ought to doe.</hi> Hee is a mighty, ſtrong, and worthy Knight, who alone is able to ſubdue &amp; put to flight, the moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous beaſt in all the world, called <hi>Selfe Will.</hi> Which beaſt doth deſtroy, kill, and ſwallowe vp: all that loue and obey her; and ſhee doth with a kinde of flattering allurement, entiſe and drawe to her al obſtinate people, of which, few forſake her, vntill ſhe drawe them into hell, &amp;
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:18006:41"/>vtter damnation. The greateſt part of people, and almoſt all forſake me, notwithſtanding it is moſt certaine, that without me, no man can finde the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> who is a Lord of ſo great dignity, and excellency, that the whole world canot be compared with him. And in regard it hath pleaſed almighty God: to beſtow ſo good and noble a husband on me, I do not any thing but what he ſhall command me. Neither doe I deſire to be eaſed, or remitted, from that is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded me, except ſome vrgent neceſsity con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine me thereunto. And in regard of theeues and robbes, which lie ſo ſecretly amongſt vs, that hardly they can be diſcried, or diſcouered by vs, I neuer dare to walke alone. DE. What companion doe you vſe? OBED. Firſt I take with me my dogge for a companion, called as yours is, <hi>Good will.</hi> Next I joyne to me my ſiſter <hi>Simplicity,</hi> and my daughters <hi>Douotion, Chearefulneſſe, Diligence, perſeuerance,</hi> and <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi> But chiefely our Lady Mother <hi>Humility,</hi> doth alwaies aſſotiate her ſelfe with mee. All theſe of neceſsitie muſt I haue with me, if I will ſecurely walke to doe that, which I am commanded. DE. Tell mee I beſeech you, How doth your Mother <hi>HUmility</hi> joyne her ſelfe with you for that as yet I doe not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand? OBED. In any thing that I vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take and doe, be it neuer ſo great, I doe not
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:18006:42"/>flatter my ſelfe that I haue done it well, neither haue I any confidence in that I doe, or by do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing well, growe into pride of minde. Neither perſwade I my ſelfe, that others could not doe it beſides my ſelfe, or that they could not doe it ſo well as my ſelfe, neither thinke I my ſelfe good, if I doe any thing that is good, or woulde be prayſed for doing it, or thought by others apt and fitte to doe it; but with all humility I giue the thankes to God, in that it hath pleaſed him, to beſtowe vnderſtanding, wiſedome, and ability on me: for the loue of him to doe ſo good a thing. And I ſay to my ſelfe, in regard it hath pleaſed God to beſtowe his grace on me, to execute ſuch a worke, for this thing eſpecially I holde my ſelfe bound to him. And therefore deſire I nothing elſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but that they will honor and praiſe God. And that vntill the laſt day of my life, nothing but labour and paine be allotted to me, all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and praiſe be to Almighty God, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefitte, and all good vnto my neighbour. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in this worlde as Iſay, I wiſh to my ſelfe: being aſſured, I deſerue nothing that is good of my ſelfe, neither deſire I any thing elſe, but that it woulde pleaſe our Lorde to beſtowe his loue on me, that thereby I may daiely encreaſe in vertue, and good life, and neuer offend him, but that in the laſt houre of my death, it will
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:18006:42"/>pleaſe him (as I hope) to ſhewe himſelfe lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and mercifull to me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 22.</hi> Of Chaſtitie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DEſire</hi> taking great comfort in this confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with <hi>Obedience,</hi> leauing her, vvas brought to the Cell of the laſt daughter of <hi>Humility,</hi> whoſe name was <hi>Chaſtity.</hi> Of whome as before deſire demanded her conditions. CHAST. I am as thou knoweſt the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Humility of hart,</hi> and haue attending on me two Virgins or handmardes the one called <hi>Abſtmence,</hi> the other <hi>Baſhfulnes.</hi> My ſpouſe or husband is called <hi>Watch of hart,</hi> who is alwayes attended with a body, called <hi>Watch of ſences.</hi> DE. I beſeech you bring mee to the ſight of this Boy. CHAST. I will doe that willingly. <hi>Deſire</hi> now much meruailed at the furniture of this Boy, for in his hand he held a bridle and a ſtone, a kerchiefe or a vaile, and a chayne with a locke, to whome hee thus ſpake, I deſire thee my Sonne to declare to mee the true ſignification of this furniture of thine. BOY. This bridle is to reſtrayne a naughty beaſt of my Maſters, vvhich al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſhe be little, yet when ſhee breaketh loſe ſhee ouerthroweth all men, neither can
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:18006:43"/>any man rule her but our Porter the <hi>Feare of God.</hi> DE. What is the name of this naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty beaſt? BOY. <hi>The Tongue.</hi> DE. What doeſt thou with this ſtone? BOY. I ſtoppe holes with it, which are in this houſe, called the <hi>Eares,</hi> leaſt theeues enter thereat, as often they doe, when it chaunceth that they be not ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped; and ſometimes alſo, I put it in my mouth, that thereby I may enjoyne my ſelfe to ſilence. De. By that meanes, others will ſay thou art dumbe. BOY. I am not dumbe, but for the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> I make my ſelfe dumbe. DE. What ſeruice canſt thou ſhewe to him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by? BOY. Much. Conſidering that by this dore thoſe two jewelles are loſt, which <hi>Simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city</hi> ſpake of, I meane <hi>Innocencie</hi> and <hi>Purity of hart,</hi> and ſo long as I continue dumbe, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide, that the wine which our Virgins vſe, runne not out, or be ſhedde. DE. What? Couldeſt thou not looke to that, if thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſpeake: BOY. No. For the ſpygotte cannot be pulled out, but the wine will bee ſhedde. DE. Might not a veſſell be ſette vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to ſaue the wine that runneth out? BOY. There might, but great wiſedome, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and fortitude, is to be vſed. And I am yet but little and young, neither can eaſely performe that office, and ſo ſoone, al the wine might runne out of the veſſell, and nothing
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:18006:43"/>but winde remaine in it. DE. What ſignifieth this kerchiefe, or vaile? BOY. It is called <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> and it ſerueth to couer the left eye, which cauſeth ſenſuality. DE. Do you couer the right eye alſo? BOY. No. for that is the eye of <hi>Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity,</hi> which not only doth hurt, but alſo brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth forth all good, and fruitfull things. But the left, is the eye of <hi>Senſuality,</hi> which is of a more ſharp ſight, then the left, and annoyeth vs with many diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities: &amp; finally, bringeth death it ſelfe: wherfore it is of neceſsity, that it be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered with this vaile, that thereby we may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue al things with purity. DE. Deliueer it more plainely, how we may ſe al things more purely and clearely. BOY. All things are ſeene with a pure hart: when they are beheld with one of theſe three eyes. Either with the eye of taking good edification for our ſelues, or with the eye of honoring &amp; glorifying God, or with the eye of excuſing &amp; pitying our neighbor DE. This yet is obſcure, declare your meaning more plain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly. BOY. I know thou doſt vnderſtand me ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently. DE. Although my ſelfe vnderſtand it, yet peraduenture others would expect to be in ſtructed more plainly. Boy. I alowe this wil &amp; deſire to profit others, to be both vertuous, and worthy praiſe: conſidering it is a ſigne of no ſmall vertue &amp; charity, both to ſeeke our owne good &amp; benefit: &amp; alſo that which may be the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:18006:44"/>good of all men. And thou haſt heard manie thinges ſpoken in parables amongſt vs, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition whereof, is both profound &amp; fruitfull: therfore when thou ſhalt returne hither againe, thou maiſt make a certaine co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mentary of ſuch thinges as thou haſt heard, and ſeene: whereby thou maiſt draw them out more at large and (as S. <hi>Greg.</hi> did vpon holy <hi>Iob</hi>) explaine them more copiouſly. DE. You ſay well, &amp; doubt not but (God aſſiſting me) I wil performe as much. For notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding to the learned, theſe ſimilitudes may ſerue, without farther explanation: yet to the ſimple ſort, it will bee neceſſary to haue a more plaine expoſition. And it will be a verie great encouragement to me, to vndertake it: if I be aduiſed to it by your councel. But now pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceed to tel the meaning of your furniture. Why doe you carry this chaine with a locke? BOY. It is called <hi>Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perance of the mouth,</hi> wherewith we locke the gates of this houſe, leaſt the Virgins that dwell here, might wander abroade. For if we had not this chaine &amp; this locke, ther would be no religion amongſt vs, but all things would be vaine. And this know for certaine, ſo long as I keep my left eye couered, although my eyes be open, yet I ſee nothing. DE. How can that be, that your eyes being open yet you ſhall not ſee? BOY. Becauſe my eyes are fixed in my head, and although ſometime I looke downe to
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:18006:44"/>the earth: yet the reflection of my eyes retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to my head.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 23.</hi> The Concluſion of the firſt part.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DEſire</hi> hauing diſcourſed after this manner with <hi>Chaſtity,</hi> departed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her with great contentment. And being guided out of this Mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naſtery by the forenamed Steward, who tolde him he had now ſeene al the virgins of this Mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naſtery, he asked if there were no other thing to bee ſeene. ST. If thou ſhalt well obſerue what thou haſt here heard, and ſeene, and ſhalt with thy beſt endeuour ſeeke to put them in ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ecution, thou art ſufficiently furniſhed to finde out the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> But yet before thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part hence, I will ſhew thee a tree, that groweth in our garde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Deſire</hi> beholding this goodly tree, beganne much to admire it, and the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it carried two ſorts of fruit, and ſaid to the <hi>Steward.</hi> DE. What kinde of fruit is this? ST. The fruit that groweth on the lower boughes, which are pale, and of diuers colours, is called <hi>Diſtruſt of our ſelues.</hi> But that which groweth on the toppe of the tree, and is of a pleaſant red colour, is called <hi>Truſt in God,</hi> with which fruit all that come hither are to be fedde. For except they ſhall feede vpon this fruit their labour is in vaine, and to no ende come they hither. DE. Wil it pleaſe you to beſtowe part thereof
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:18006:45"/>on me, that I may eate thereof in my journey, I am to take. STEW. I will eate thereof, of the fruit of the lower boughes which is, <hi>Diſtrust of thy ſelfe,</hi> as much as ſhall be neceſſary: and fill all thy pockets with the fruit of the higher boughes, that thou maiſt eate therof in thy jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney &amp; this wil ſerue thee, vntil thou come to the houſe of the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> Now <hi>Deſire</hi> ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently ſatisfied, with the fruit of the lowe boughes, filled his pockets and boſome with the fruit of the higher boughes, and ſaid. DE. I beſeech you Siſter, now ſhew to me the ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieſt and moſt ready way to the houſe of the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> STEW. I rejoyce to ſe thee ſo furniſhed, and deſirous to vndertake the jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to finde the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> Yet not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, I feare if thou trauaile alone, thou wilt hardly finde out the readieſt way, therefore wil I giue thee truſty companions of our ſociety who ſhall doe, and guide thee the right way thou art to take. DE. Is not <hi>Good wil</hi> my dogge ſufficient for that? STEW. No truely. For although he be very good, yet is not he ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for ſuch a journey, wherein are encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, not only many dangerous wilde beaſts, hollowe pittes, rough wayes, buſhes &amp; bryers: but theeues, ſpoylers, and robbers, and ſuch as ſeeke to kill and deſtroy all paſſengers, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is wiſdome not to truſt, to thy dogge
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:18006:45"/>alone DE. For theſe alleaged reaſons I pray you, appoint me ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panions as you thinke neceſſary. STEW. Then take in thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany our Porter, the <hi>Feare of our Lord,</hi> who is a worthy and excellent man, whoſe company if thou wilt not forgoe, take likewiſe with thee his daughter <hi>Baſhfulnes,</hi> whome to be ſure to keepe, take an herbe with thee, called <hi>Humble caſting downe of thy eyes.</hi> And yet farther take with thee an other companion, called <hi>Simplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</hi> And now <hi>Deſire,</hi> goe on thy way being garded with Gods bleſſing. But yet marke well this one leſſon, although thou chaunce to looſe the <hi>Feare of God,</hi> or <hi>Simplicitie;</hi> Yet be ſure to keepe warely thy dogge about thee, for he will ſerue to finde them againe. And ſee that thou giue him of the fruit in thy pocket, to eate of. And when thou art gone hence, keepe the way which leadeth on the left hand, where thou ſhalt finde a path, which is a nearer way, then others, which will bring the directly to the houſe of <hi>Charitie,</hi> wherein dwelleth the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> DE. What is the name of that path, that if I happe to miſſe my way, I may aske it of other. STEW. It is called <hi>Patience,</hi> which is the ready and neareſt way to the houſe of <hi>Humilitie</hi> and <hi>Charitie.</hi> †.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:18006:46"/>
            <head>THE SECOND PART.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 1.</hi> Of Patience.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>ESIRE being now well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed with the aboue named fruites, and accompanied with <hi>Good will</hi> his dogge, and the <hi>Feare of God</hi> the Porter on the one ſide, and with <hi>Simplicity</hi> on the other ſide, &amp; hauing alſo his pockets filled with the fruit of <hi>Confidence in God,</hi> departed chearefull out of the houſe of <hi>Humility</hi> &amp; wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly vndertoke the way of <hi>Patience.</hi> Which although he were told to be ſhort &amp; pleaſant: Yet found he it rough, had and vnpleaſant by reaſon of many brables &amp; buſhes, which made him co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaine, &amp; ſay to <hi>Simplicitie.</hi> DE. O good God how hard, and difficult a way is this, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that I thought it to be. SIMP. Let not that ſeeme ſtrange, to thee <hi>Deſire</hi> for there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is it called the way of <hi>Patience,</hi> which if it were not ſharpe &amp; full of difficulties, it ſhould not be calloed, and knowne by that name, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould the houſe to which it leadeth be held in ſo great eſteeme: if the way were playne and eaſie, and paſſible for all people. But as it
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:18006:46"/>is, none paſſe it but thoſe that be throughly exerciſed. And haſt thou not heard the old pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerbe. That no good thing can be obteyned without labour and paine; or pleaſant, but firſt by taſting the ſower? wherefore hauing now vndertaken and entred the way: thou muſt of neceſſity endure the hardnes, comforted with this, that it will not long continue. For whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer will ſeeke to take the fiſh, muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to wette his foote. And coldeſt thou imagine, that a thing ſo pretious as the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> cold be obteyned without labour and payne. Remember the ſaying of <hi>Seneca</hi> the Philoſopher. <hi>A thing of worth cannot be bought for a trifle. For with great labours wee atchiue great matters.</hi> And thou art deceaued, <hi>Deſire</hi> if thou thinke to get ſo rich a treaſure with no labour, neither wouldſt thou make any great accompt, of the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> if thou coldeſt finde him without any trauaile. Goe to there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore coragiouſly and feare not labour, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that after it, thou ſhalt reſt and bee comforted vvith the <hi>Loue of God,,</hi> and thou wilt eſteeme the greatlier of him, and loue him better; for the more payne thou endureſt in finding him out: the greater will be thy joy and contentement after. And if thou fortune to be weary in the way, eate of the fruit which thou haſt, called <hi>Confidence of God;</hi> and thou
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:18006:47"/>ſhalt finde thy ſelfe to be ſtrengthned againe. But if thou wilt not feele the wearieſomes of thy journey, do as trauailers do, that paſſe ouer the paine with ſinging as they goe. <hi>Deſire</hi> ſome what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted with this direction of <hi>Simplicitie</hi> ſaid. DE. How can we ſing, being accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with this reuerend and graue old Father. SIMP. It is his cuſtome to ſhewe himſelfe graue in geſture and apparell: but otherwiſe he is ſociable and pleaſant in conuerſation, for he is the brother of the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> &amp; ſingeth ſweetly, eſpecially when he heareth vs ſing, not for wantonnes and leuity, but to cheare vp our ſpirits, and comfort our ſelues, being weary in our journey. DE. How ſhall I ſing that haue no voyce. SIMP. Thou canſt not lacke voyce, that art a voyce thy ſelfe. <hi>Deſire</hi> mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed to heare her ſay, he was a voyce and anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wered. DE. How can you ſay that I am a voyce? SIMP. Thou, as all other creatures waſt created by Gods word, &amp; it is plaine that a voyce doth follow a word, conſidering there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that ſo ſone as God had ſpoke the word, preſently all creatures were made: it followeth that all creatures are voyces. DE. Explayne this yet more plainely. SIMP. Speech and the word are but one thing. For ſpeech is not that which is deliuered with the mouth: but which being conceaued in the minde, is retey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:18006:47"/>within. But that which is expreſſed with the mouth, is a voyce, declaring the ſpeech or word, conceaued in the hart. As for example if I conceaue ſuch a thought in my minde, that thou art a man, this is a word or ſpeech, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I vtter it not, yet I hold it within mee. But if I ſhall expreſſe it with my mouth, &amp; ſay thou art a man, this is a voyce, explayning the ſecret conceyte of my minde. De. If I be a voyce, whoſe voyce am I. SIMP. Thou art the voice of God, by whome thou waſt created to this prayſe, honor &amp; glory. DE. What thing then do I ſpeake of my ſelfe, if I be a voyce? SIMP. Thou ſayeſt God is good, by the goodnes of that eſſence, which thou haſt of God, euen ſo by thy owne beauty, thou giueſt a witneſſe that he is beautifull, through whoſe beauty thou haſt attayned to ſuch goodnes and beauty, to conclude, whatſoeuer God hath cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated in thee, it is but a certayne voyce explay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the vertue &amp; goodnes of him. De. How can you ſay that, whatſoeuer is in me created by God is a voyce: &amp; not abſolutely whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is in me is a voyce. SIMP. Thus, this ſins and wickednes which God hath not made, are not his voyces, but thy owne, which ſpeake and declare that thou art filthy, nought, impure, and wicked. For as by the creatures of God we are ledde and brought to the knowledge of
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:18006:48"/>him: ſo by thoſe things which we do our ſelues, we may attaine to the knowledge of our ſelues.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER 2.</hi> How God may be knowne by his creatures.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DEſire</hi> noted this diſcourſe of <hi>Simplicity,</hi> not without great admiration, who although ſhe ſeemed in ſhew but ſimple: yet found he her moſt wiſe in theſe high and ſecret miſteries, and ſaid to her. DE. To what end wold you haue vs to ſing. SIMP. To the end we may forgett the difficulties, and ſorrowes of this miſerable ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment we liue in: and looſe not our hope to come to the houſe of Gods <hi>Charitie.</hi> Wherevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to to attayne, we ſhall finde no ſmall helpe in meditating vpon Gods creatures, which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely I haue placed in this journey of <hi>Patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,</hi> that thou maieſt the ſoner come to the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> if thou ſhalt be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſant in this booke of his creatures. For by <hi>Patience</hi> we conceaue a greater hope of the diuine ſcripture which is the whole world, which is no other thing then the booke of God. DE. Conſidering then that we muſt ſing, let vs do that for which cauſe we are made voices, that is let vs prayſe God. SIM. I am well contented, for ſo many voyces will joine with vs in ſinging. Sometime deſfca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſome time the Tenor, ſometime the treble wil meete vs, &amp; in the beginning the Baſſe, in the middeſt the Tenor &amp; deſcant, in the end the Treble, &amp; all ſortes of voyces, according to the multitute
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:18006:48"/>and variety of creatures, farther it is neceſſary (if we will doe according to the preſcript of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke) that we endeuoure to bee skilfull in our ſong, for conſidering we haue voyces, we muſt learne &amp; vnderſtand the knowledge of ſinging DE. Who ſhal teach vs that? SIM. Our owne voyces. For ſome creatures ſhall declare his power and highnes, others his goodnes, others his wiſdome, others his ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlenes, others his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auty, others his ſweetnes, others his greatnes, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers his iuſtice, &amp; others his liberality: &amp; to this end God hath beſtowed on vs a kind of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of him ſelfe, according to euery mans ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity and nature, that thereby we may ſing &amp; deliuer his prayſe. For which cauſe I entreate thee, endeuour in this thy journey to become as expert in ſinging as thou ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt, &amp; the rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in the houſe of the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> to which thou doeſt trauaile, there is nothing but ſinging whither when thou ſhalt come, I would haue thee ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly inſtructed in this arte. For who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhall haue a good voyce in this jorney, &amp; ſhall often exerciſe it, it is thereby ſo amended, that it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not change. And as euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> through daily exerciſe ſhall learne to ſing in this life, ſo ſhall he bee there more excellent then others. DE. Teach me I pray you, how I muſt ſing by Gods creatures; for of my ſelfe I ſhall not eaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly learne it. SIMP. I will willingly do it. Now meane time <hi>Deſire</hi> hauing trauailed far through
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:18006:49"/>the deſert: learned and proued many vertues and excellencies of our Lord and Sauiour IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVS Chriſt and the better, by the ayde, aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and direction of his guide <hi>Simplicitie.</hi> Yet was he to paſſe many great, dangerous, and hard labours: ofte did he ſtumble, but <hi>Simplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> ſupported him, that he could not fall. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſometimes he fell, but preſently <hi>Simplicity</hi> gaue him her hand. Sometimes he fell ſo dangerouſly, that except he had beene lifted vp againe by the helpe of the <hi>Feare of God</hi> hee neuer woulde, or coulde haue roſe againe. Sometimes when he ſhould goe forwarde, he retyred backe, and when he ſhould haue recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued benefit by Gods creatures, he became much worſe. For he was not ſufficient careful to try out the ſecret vertues of voyces, neither did he greatly regard his ſong, but ſuffered him ſelfe to growe hoarſe, vntill being pricked and put forward with the <hi>Feare of God,</hi> he laboured to goe forward. Oft times did thornes and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes run into his feete, but <hi>Simplicitie</hi> held him vp, and the <hi>Feare of God</hi> plucked them out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Sometime was he mch oppreſſed with ſleepe, but the <hi>Feare of God</hi> awaked him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Oft times being weary, he ſate downe to reſt him, but <hi>Good Will</hi> his dogge neuer left barking, vntill he aroſe againe. Sometime we he ſo weary, that through inconſtancie of mind
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:18006:49"/>he determined to goe backe: but preſently ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the fruite in his pocket, he recouered ſtrength and kept on his way. Sometimes as he trauailed in the darknes of the night: hee loſt both the <hi>Feare of God</hi> and <hi>Simplicity,</hi> ſo that he wandered out of the right way, of his journey: but ſo ſone as the ſunne beganne to ſhine by the help of his dogge, he found his way againe. Now after they had trauailed thus many dayes, they came to a pleaſant &amp; delightful meadow, in the middeſt whereof was ſeated a princely Palace, called the houſe of <hi>Charitie,</hi> the Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter whereof was the <hi>Loue of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <head>THE THIRD PART.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 1.</hi> Of the probation and exerciſe of the <hi>Loue of God.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen <hi>Deſire</hi> had beheld this goodly Palace, he rejoyced much, that his long weary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and painefull journey, was come at laſt to ſo joyfull an end. Wherefore comming to the gates, and finding them locked: he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to call and knocke thereat. But not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:18006:50"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding his calling &amp; knocking, no man appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that would giue him an anſwere. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpake <hi>Simplicity.</hi> And told him it were requiſite that he cryed lowder, for by that meanes he ſhould be hard, although they with in were a ſleepe or elſe deafe, &amp; bidde him take the two hammers: that hong at the gate, &amp; preſently ſome would come, &amp; open it for him. Theſe two hammers were called, the one <hi>To ſigh.</hi> The other <hi>To cry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore ſhe bid him, knocke &amp; cry a lowde for theſe dores, ſhould not be here if they were not to be opened, &amp; therefore are theſe hamers hanged at them, that ſuch a ſhal knocke may be admitted in. Thus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued <hi>Deſire,</hi> ſtil crying &amp; knocking long, before the <hi>Loue of God</hi> would o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the gate, neither did <hi>Deſire</hi> as yet know him, To whome the <hi>Loue of God</hi> at length ſpake as foloweth. What ſeek you here brother, or what lack you to knocke &amp; call thus? peraduenture you are weary with your long expectation. But it is our cuſtome and manner to feigne our ſelfs deafe, therby to try their patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that come hither. And it chaunceth often, that when we ſo any wax weary &amp; perſwade the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues that the gate muſt be opened to them, ſo ſone as they come: we ſuffer them to depart euen as they came, for none are admitted to enter hither that ſhall thinke themſelues worthily to deſerue the place, &amp; that we ought to receitie them of right
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:18006:50"/>and duety. Therefore tell me, art thou one of thoſe? De. No Sir, I am not. For notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding I haue paſſed &amp; ouercome many labours, yet am I ſure, that I haue no way deſerued to be admitted in here: but altogither vnworthy, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it ſhall pleaſe you to receaue me vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your owne goodnes &amp; mercy. LOVE. &amp;c. What is the cauſe thou deſireſt to be admitted? or what ſeekeſt thou to find here within this houſe. DE. I am come ſir hither from the houſe of <hi>Humility</hi> accompaned with theſe graue &amp; honeſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, &amp; haue paſſed my jorney by the path of <hi>Patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</hi> Only to ſeeke the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> who as it is told me dwelleth here within. LOV. &amp;c. Doeſt thou bring me no token whereby I may knowe that thou commeſt from the houſe of <hi>Humility.</hi> DE. I bring two tokens. The one wherof was giuen me in the houſe of <hi>Humility,</hi> and it is called, <hi>Knowledge of my ſelfe.</hi> The other haue I got my ſelfe in my journey, and that is called <hi>Knowledge of God.</hi> LOVE. &amp;c. I am very well pleaſed to ſe thee ſo prouided, but yet tell mee this one thing, doeſt thou perſwade thy ſelfe, that by reaſon of theſe two knowledges we ought of duety to receaue, and admit thee. DE. Be it farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me to haue ſuch a thought. I deſire to be receaued only through your grace and mercy. For I am not ſure whither both theſe knowledges, wherwith I am inſtructed be
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:18006:51"/>trulie written or no. This I know for certaine, that I continued ſometime in the houſe of <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility,</hi> and there I learned and knewe the houſe, the Virgins, and their conditions, they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues telling me. But whether I haue well di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted the fruit I eate there, or whether they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree well with my ſtomacke, although they be ſweete in taſte, I confeſſe I knowe not, Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther am I ſure whether I reaped any benefit by my journey. For often did I fall, the buſhes and brambles oft pricked me, and in a manner I was drawne hither by force of my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panions. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore Sir, there is none of theſe thinges that I bring with me, that I can tell you any certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of, but mine owne malice, vilenes, ſloath, and imperfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And amongſt other things which cauſe me to come hither to ſeeke the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> one eſpeciall cauſe is, that I vnderſtand he is a ſingular good Chirurgion, of whome I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be purged, and to be let bloud. And far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, men ſay, that with his only looke he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently diſcouereth the imperfections and faults in the hart, and whoſoeuer he toucheth he doth preſently cure. LOVE. &amp;c. Why doeſt thou deſire to be made ſo pure, and ſound? DE. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (as I haue learned of others) it is allowed to none to enter in hither that ſhal be vncleane, but to ſuch as ſhall be only pure, ſounde, and vndefiled. LOVE &amp;c. Conſidering them, that
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:18006:51"/>thou putteſt thy whole truſt and confidence in vs, ſtay here a while. For thou canſt not enter in, or ſpeake with the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> except firſt thou talke with a Boy of his: tarry here there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and I will call the Boy, who will direct thee what thou art to doe, and how thou maiſt come to the ſpeach of his Maſter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 2.</hi> Of the loue of our Neighbour.</head>
               <p>HEre <hi>Deſire</hi> ſtayed, expecting greatly the comming of the Boy, that ſhoulde bring him in, to the ſpeach of his Maſter: who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently came forth. His name was caled the <hi>Loue of our Neighbour,</hi> whome when <hi>Deſire</hi> behelde, he could not through joyrefraine from weping for the exceeding great loue hee carried to his Maſter. LOVE &amp;c. What is the cauſe that thou weepeſt thus, conſidering in this houſe all are chearefull and merry, and none is heard to weepe or lament? DE. Ioy, not ſorrow maketh me to weepe. LOVE. &amp;c. Who do you ſeeke for here? DE. The <hi>Loue of God.</hi> LOVE. &amp;c. I am his Boy: therefore if thou ſeekeſt my maſter thou muſt firſt talke &amp; be acquainted with me. For my M. maketh ſo great account of me, that he wil not ſpeake with thoſe that loue not me. DE. I moſt willingly would learne and knowe thy conditions, and for the loue of thy M. be acquainted with thee. LOVE &amp;c. If thou
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:18006:52"/>wouldeſt be admitted amongſt the number of my friends. Thou muſt euery morning giue me in ſteed of my breakfaſt, a certaine ſawce called <hi>Hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble thought,</hi> &amp; an other at noone, called <hi>Hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſpeach,</hi> &amp; a third at euening, caled <hi>Hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble work</hi> DE. Where ſhall I find out, or get theſe ſawces? LOVE. <hi>Humility</hi> &amp; her husband <hi>holy Purpoſe</hi> maketh the firſt, which is <hi>Humble thought,</hi> wher by ſhe thinketh and eſteemeth her ſelfe more vile, baſe, and inferiour than any other, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counteth of her ſelfe no better then a labouring beaſt. This <hi>holy purpoſe</hi> prepareth a certaine Ele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctuary for <hi>Humilitie,</hi> called <hi>Conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of our ſelfe,</hi> &amp; to make this ſwace which we now ſpeake of, an other hearbe is to be added, called <hi>Good opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our neighbour,</hi> of which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poundes <hi>hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble thought</hi> is made. And in all this prouince, is not a skilful ler man to make this ſwace, then the forenamed husband of <hi>Humilitie,</hi> whome ſo ſoone as thou ſhalt get thy friend, he will inſtruct thee how to make this ſawce. The other called <hi>Hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble ſpeach</hi> is made, &amp; compounded of three other hearbes, which are, <hi>Humilitie, Gentleneſſe,</hi> and <hi>Affability,</hi> which muſt be ſtrowed with a fine powder cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Slownes,</hi> and <hi>Sparing.</hi> The third which is <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble worke,</hi> is compounded of many herbes. The chiefe whereof, are <hi>Chearefulneſſe, Loue,</hi> and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence.</hi> When thou ſhalt bring me theſe three ſawces to eate, then ſhall our friendſhip and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:18006:52"/>be firme, and ſoone after will I bring thee to the ſpeach of my M. <hi>Deſire</hi> much deligh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted with this direction of this boy, ſaid to him. DE. Conſidering you haue acquainted me with your condition &amp; deſire, I wil labour to make theſe ſawces, &amp; giue them to you. Thus <hi>Desire</hi> continued long in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ference with this Boy, trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting &amp; diſcourſing many matters with him, &amp; be ga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be familiar with him, &amp; deliuering to him, the fornamed ſawce, at laſt he deſired him to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the gate, that thereby he might haue acceſſe to his M. LOVE. Thy requeſt is reaſonable, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſidering thou doeſt what lyeth in thy power, ſtay but a little, I will goe call my M. and ſee if he will come forth to ſpeake with thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER 3.</hi> Of the Loue of God and our Neighbour, and of an other degree of loue, and of the of fiee and exerciſe thereof.</head>
               <p>NOw <hi>Desire</hi> began to thinke thus with him ſelfe, whether the <hi>Loue of God</hi> would come forth to talke with him or no, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering he was ſo vile, miſerable, &amp; wretched &amp; altogither vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, with whome ſo great a Lord ſhoulde voutſafe to talke: and whilſt he weas thus deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with himſelfe, he perceaued one comming towards him, who aſked him, what he would, or with whom he would ſpeake. DE. Sir I ſeeke to ſpeak with the <hi>loue of God</hi> LO. I am he which ſo
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:18006:53"/>ſoone as <hi>Deſire</hi> heard, he fell to the ground, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing loſt his ſtrength. Then the <hi>Loue of God</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him by the hand, raiſed him from the ground which made <hi>Deſire</hi> to weepe ſo abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly for joy, that hardly could he pronounce any word. Whereat the Loue of God being ten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der of hart, through the compaſſion he had of him beganne to weepe alſo, noting the great loue and good will which <hi>Deſire</hi> had towardes him, &amp; ſai. LOVE. &amp;c. Ceaſe off to weepe, for I cannot without griefe behold the teares of him that loueth me; but tell me, who told thee that I was abiding in this houſe? DE. A cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſheepheard, that I mette on the way, who directed me to this place, where I ſhould finde you. LOVE. &amp;c. What did he tell thee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning me? &amp; what is the cauſe why thou lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt me ſo greatly, and haſt ſo great a deſire to finde me out? Is it becauſe thou haſt heard of others, that I beſtowe many great giftes on my friendes, and vſe to rewarde with greate bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fittes, ſuch as ſerue and obey mee? DE. No. But for this cauſe doe I loue you, becauſe you are, a good, a noble, and a famous Lord. And becauſe you bring your friendes and ſerauntes to the place where they may ſee, and beholde God: then the which, there is no greater hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, and felicity in the world. The Loue of god hearing what <hi>Desire</hi> had ſaid, was much ple<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:18006:53"/>to heare his holy purpoſe &amp; inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; began to loue him now more then before, to whome <hi>Deſire</hi> ſaid, I cannot ſufficiently meruaile my Lord, that you being ſo mighty and potent a Lord, and the Sonne of ſo great a King, admit ſuch as follow, and ſeeke after you, to finde you with ſo great labour &amp; difficulty. LOVE. &amp;c. Doe not ſo. For this is a miſtery not knowne to all men. For many there be that thinke they haue not found, or knowe not me: when not withſtanding, I am neare vnto them, and then themſelues abounde with me. And againe there be others that perſwade themſelues, that they haue found and obteyned me, when notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they be farre from me, and haue not the leaſt knowledge, and vnderſtanding of me. DE. I beſeech you acquainte me with your conditions, and office that I may vnderſtand whither I be neare or farre of from you, for I hould and eſteeme of you, as of my Lord and friends. LOVE. &amp;c. My office and duety is to loue God, for I am called the Sonne of the Knowledge of God. DE. How do you loue God? LOVE. &amp;c. I haue a vehement de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to loue him with all my hart, with all my ſtrength, and with all my power, and with aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaying any thing, whereby I may feele him in ſuch manner, as may pleaſe him, in referring all thinges to his honour, prayſe, and glory, and
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:18006:54"/>the health and benefitte of mine owne ſoule. And likewiſe doe I wiſh, that the whole world may know &amp; vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, him for his exceeding great goodneſſe, and that all creatures may honour him, and yeeld him daily thankes. And I enforce my ſelfe with my earneſt deſire, that neither in great or ſmall thinges, much or lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle I offend or diſpleaſe him, or that I doe any thing contrary to his pleaſure. And if through mine owne frailety and imbecillity I chaunce to offend him: I preſently craue and aske for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of him: and by that meanes our loue is repayred againe. And although my Lord and Maſter be ſo good, ſo noble, and ſo gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious to me: yet am I not content with this firſt ſteppe, and degree: but yet proceede farther, and according to my power and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, endeuour to execute, nor only what hee commandeth: but whatſoeuer the meaneſt in this Monaſtery, ſhall commaunde mee in his name. And this accuſtome I my ſelfe to doe, with all reuerence, denotion loue, joy, humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ready will: and that euer, in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and in euery good action. And hereby doe I knowe how greatly I loue him: when I doe that thing which hee commaundeth mee: For thus I perſwade my ſelfe, that nothing in the worlde is ſo gratefull to him, (bee it to talke with him, doe him reuerence, or to ſhewe all
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:18006:54"/>ſeruice to him: as to doe that thing which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther himſelfe or ſomeother ſhall command me in his name. For my Lord and Maſter ſaith thus to me. How thinkeſt thou that thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices can be acceptable to me, or that thou canſt bee loued of mee, if thou doeſt not that which I ſhall commaund thee to doe? Or how canſt thou ſay thou loueſt me? For this knowe for certaine, that in no other thing thou canſt ſo vnite thy ſelfe to me, or conforme thy will ſo neare to mine, as if thou willingly and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly execute what I commaund thee?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 4.</hi> The Loue of God proceedeth in his diſcourſe.</head>
               <p>IN this degree of loue, I haue reſolued with my ſelfe to performe whatſoeuer, I holde my ſelfe bound to, by my vocation and office. For ſince I firſt profeſſed my ſelfe (of which I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer repent me) I holde my ſelfe by vow bound to performe that, which before I might either haue done or omitted. And for that cauſe I vſe diligently to thinke vpon my duety and office, reſoluting, and determining ſtill with my ſelfe, to execute and diſcharge, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer I am bound to by vertue of it, according to the direction of holy write, and learned men. Being moſt aſſured, that many offende through ignorance of that, which they are bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:18006:55"/>to by duty. And if they know what they ought to doe: and yet neglect and omit it; then is their offence farre greater and more grieuous: for then they offend through malice, and not ignorance. Farther ſuch thinges as I haue vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed &amp; promiſſed to do (which to performe I am bound by duety) thoſe with all my endeuours, I labour to execute. And I haue promiſſed and vndertaken to my Lord and Maſter, to keepe for euer the faith, I haue giuen to three Virgins which abide &amp; dwell in this Monaſtery, which are <hi>Obedience, Chaſtity,</hi> &amp; <hi>Pouerty,</hi> which three he hath giuen and aſſigned me as wiues, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore morning and euening, I conſider with my ſelfe, how that day following I may beſt ſerue and pleaſe them. Saying to my ſoule. Let me ſe now my ſoule, how thou wilt endeuour with thy ſelfe this day to obey, and pleaſe theſe Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, and at night, ſhew me my ſoule how thou haſt performed this day, what thou dideſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe to doe towards theſe Virgins, &amp; whither thou haſt grieued or offended any of them. Thus doe I ſtill endeuour, to ſhewe my ſelfe a faithfull ſeruant to them. DE. Wherefore do you thus? LOVE. &amp;c. Becauſe theſe be the chamber-keepers of my Lord and Maſter, and none are admitted or can talke with him, except theſe Virgins procure him entrance. DE. Tell me I pray you, what ſpirituall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:18006:55"/>haue you, whereby you ſerue and keepe promiſſe with theſe Virgins. LOVE. &amp;c. Three thinges I propounde, and determine to my ſelf, which night &amp; day I offer vp to them, and which conſtrayne me to ſerue, and be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to them. The firſt is called, <hi>To aske or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand nothing.</hi> The ſecond <hi>To couet or deſire no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi> The third. <hi>To thinke on nothing.</hi> This firſt <hi>Purpoſe</hi> of mine ſerueth <hi>Obedience</hi> if ſo be, it be ſeaſoned with a ſawce, called <hi>To doe,</hi> and then may you cal <hi>it to aske to do nothing.</hi> With which foode Obedience is ſuſteyned, &amp; by how much more abundantly and purely I offer this vp, by ſo much the more am I in grace, &amp; fauour with my Lord, &amp; the greater affection doth he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to me. This ſelfe ſame foode, called To aske, if I ſeaſon it with another ſawce, called To haue is called, To aske or deſire to haue nothing, and with that doe I feede the ſecond Virgin, called Pouerty. DE. Stay here a while, I pray you. May I not aske to haue any thing that I want, and haue neede of? LOVE. &amp;c. No, except the thing, you deſire be moſt needfull. For if there be any thing neceſſary for thee to haue, thou haſt thy Superiour, who by himſelfe or his Officiall ſhall prouide for thee, that thou needeſt not aske, what thou mayeſt not lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aske. For he whoſe charge it is to looke to the whole houſe: will prouide neceſſaries for
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:18006:56"/>all as it becommeth the Superiour, to the intent they may more freely ſerue GOD and attend their ſpirituall meditations, neither ſhall there be neede that any aske or craue ſuch thinges as be neceſſary for them. And it ſhall be no little fault in the Superiour to want that diſcretion, as not to giue thinges neceſſary for thoſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his charge except they dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d them. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that which I ſaid of asking or demanding, ought to be doubly vnderſtoode; that without offending one may aske, if ſuch thinges as ſhall bee neceſſary, bee not giuen without asking, which thing may juſtly be reprehended, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in Religious perſons, and if it be a thing of great neceſſity, and not rather to ſatisfie our contentement. For in asking otherwiſe it may proceede from ſuperfluity, curiouſity or ſome other temptation. And aſſure thy ſelfe that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a colour of neceſſity, many vices are often couered, eſpecially in thinges that appertayne to the ſuſtinance of the body as meate, drinke, cloathing, and ſuch like. DE. How ſhall I know whither, that which I deſire proceede of neceſſity or rather to ſatisfie my contentement. LOVE. &amp;c. If thou maiſt forbeare that which thou askeſt, and if thou canſt liue without it, and art not conſtrayned to ſuffer ſome great or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table hurt in thy body or thy ſoule, which may hap to thee in not asking. For if thou ſhalt bee
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:18006:56"/>ſure in not flattering thy ſelf that in not asking, ſome great perill or danger may happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to thee, then not to aske is a great offence, and to aske, a merit if thou referre it to God. But if thou maiſt conueniently liue without that, which thou askeſt, and endure no great hurt or dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger thereby, admit thou ſuffer ſome labour or griefe in forbearing it, prouided ſtill thou ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede not the boundes of diſcretion; in this caſe not to aske, althopugh that which thou as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt be ſome what needefull, it ſhall be a great merit to thee, &amp; a token of thy vertue, although without offending thou maiſt aske as I haue ſaid. For happy in my opinion is the man that ſuffereth any thing for the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> But if that which thou wilt aske be but ſuch a thing, which without hurt of thy body or ſoule thou maiſt eaſely miſſe: thou maiſt thinke then, that to aske is but to ſatisfie thy minde and pleaſure, although it be couered with a pretext of ſome holy purpoſe. For ſinne doth not alwais ſhew, it ſelfe openly, but is ſhadowed often with a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of holines. And thus maiſt thou knowe if thou askeſt any thing, whither it proceede of neceſſity or an vanſatisfied will. And leaſt thou be deceaued through they partiall Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it will be neceſſary for thee, to keepe a diligent watch ouer thy ſelfe, and to bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed in vertue. Which if thou doeſt not,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:18006:57"/>it will be good, that thou be ordered by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe of diſcret men, and holy Scripture.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER. 5. <hi>Of the other two Purpoſes of the</hi> Loue of God, <hi>to wit</hi> To deſire nothing, <hi>and</hi> To thinke on nothing.</head>
               <p>LOVE. &amp;c. hauing breefly explayned my firſt <hi>Purpoſe,</hi> wherewith the firſt two Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, <hi>Obedience</hi> &amp; <hi>Pouerty,</hi> are as I haue ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore nourriſhed, I muſt ſhew and declare to thee the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditions of the other two, <hi>To deſire nothing,</hi> and <hi>To thinke nothing.</hi> Know therefore for moſt certayne that this former <hi>Purpoſe to aske nothing,</hi> is grounded vpon the ſecond, <hi>To deſire nothing.</hi> For it is moſt certaine that, <hi>To haue,</hi> proceedeth only from <hi>To deſire.</hi> Then the cauſe take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away, which is <hi>To deſire;</hi> the effect fayleth, which is <hi>To aske.</hi> And by that is effected that which is contrary to this, which is <hi>Not to aske.</hi> This is the other <hi>Purpoſe</hi> wherewith <hi>Chaſtity</hi> is nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which is the third Virgin, whoſe office is, <hi>To deſire no worldly or carnall thing.</hi> But becauſe this herbe hath an other roote, from whence it ſpringeth, which is <hi>To thinke on nothing,</hi> (for the thing cannot bee deſired, which is not firſt thought on) I adjoyne a third <hi>Purpoſe,</hi> which is <hi>To thinke nothing.</hi> But in this place <hi>To thinke,</hi> muſt be vnderſtood of that <hi>Thought,</hi> which is perſeuerant &amp; ſettled, with a conſent &amp; liking
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:18006:57"/>of reaſon and will. For to thinke nothing, doth not conſiſt in the power of man. But it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in man not to continue, or perſeuer in ill thoughts: but ſone to collect himſelfe, and to turne to God. Now when this herbe <hi>To thinke,</hi> is watered with the water, called to <hi>See.</hi> Wee muſt then adde to theſe holy <hi>Purpoſes</hi> a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne powder, that is called. <hi>Strict garde of our eyes.</hi> For this is moſt neceſſary. Theſe three <hi>Purpoſes,</hi> doe not only purge and make cleane my ſoule from all worldly affares, from al ſelfe-will, and from all ſpot and ſtayne: but beſides (that I may with greater zeale ſerue my Lord God) procure me great purity of hart, &amp; ridde me of all priuate affection and loue, and joyne, and vnite me wholly to my Lord God and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. And to theſe three <hi>Purpoſes</hi> I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced all my other ſpirituall exerciſes, as well thoſe which are appertayning to <hi>Humility:</hi> as ſuch as are agreable to al other vertues, becauſe I knowe, perfection to conſiſt in them. And ſuffer not thy ſelfe to bee perſwaded that in vayne, I yeeld obedience to theſe three Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, for I finde their fauour and goodnes, great towardes me, who plentifully beſtow on me all kinde of goodnes. The one of them called, <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty,</hi> hath lately beſtowed on me a ritch orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. DE. I deſire to ſee it, where doe you keepe it? LOVE. &amp;c. I keepe it in two
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:18006:58"/>places, in my hart, and in my chamber. And it is ſo great, and of ſo high eſtimation, that I could not poſſibly keepe it in my hart, vntill I baniſhed, and vtterly excluded thence, all worldly loue, affection, and deſire: neyther could it poſſibly be conteyned in my chamber vntill I had caſt thence all ſuperfluous thinges, reſeruing only the <hi>Crucifix,</hi> and ſome few other bookes. DE. What is the name of this orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? It is called <hi>Nothing at all,</hi> and it is the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciall and chiefeſt treaſure of <hi>Pouerty</hi> who is the richeſt Lady of all the world, and who poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth ſo much treaſure, as here ſelfe doth deſire.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 6.</hi> Of the office of the Loue of God, and of prayer in the ſame degree.</head>
               <p>IN this foreſaid office of <hi>Loue,</hi> which is to doe that which my Lord and Maſter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth, and my duety bindeth me to I muſt vſe a certaine condition or circumſtance, which is, that if at any time according to my office and place I am ſet in (as being attendant in his chamber) I come vnto him, either to doe him ſeruice, or to craue ſomething of him, or elſe to to ſpeake to him; I endeuour to ſhew and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent my ſelfe, with as great purity and humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of hart, as I can. For by how much clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in hart I preſent my ſelfe to him, by ſo much more clearneſſe I ſee and beholde him.
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:18006:58"/>And I accuſtome to craue the fellowſhippe of my Brother the <hi>Feare of God,</hi> that he with an Aunte of mine called <hi>Reuerence,</hi> woulde goe alſo with me. De. What is the reaſon you take <hi>Reuerence</hi> with you? LOVE. &amp;c. I weigh and conſider with my ſelfe who I am, and who my Lord and Maſter is. I think vpon his moſt ſacred Majeſty, who of right, and deſart, ought to be reuerenced, and feared as one moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of all honour, and loue. Father, I vſe to contemplate how al the bleſſed ſoules fall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate before him, adore him, and praiſe him, and that by admiring, and prayſing his ſo great and excellent goodnes and Majeſty, they be rauiſhed, and in a ſort transformed into God himſelfe. Yet farther, I am wont to conſider, how my hart, thought, wil, &amp; purpoſe, or intent is laide open before him, and how he ſeeth, and knoweth my ſecrets, better then my ſelfe. Alſo how according to the pleaſure of his diuine ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly will, he is able to doe, alter, eſtabliſh, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſh all things: and how life and death, being and not being, the ſaluation, or damnation of the whole world, is in his hands. I farther me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate with my ſelfe, how he is wholy and all good: &amp; the chiefeſt, higheſt, &amp; pureſt goodnes it ſelf, which conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plating rightly, I oft tremble in hart, feare, &amp; almoſt faint: eſpecially behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding my ſelf, ſo wicked, ſo vile, ſo abhominable
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:18006:59"/>and ſo filthy a ſinner, to preſume, to ſpeake to a Lord of ſo great Majeſtie, &amp; that he will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me to come to him, ſpeake with him, and eate with him, as though I were vnited in great friendſhippe with him. Often doe I vſe this or like ſpeech to him. What neede haſt thou, O my Lord and Maſter that ſuch ſinners as my ſelfe, ſhould preſent themſelues before thee? Is it ſeemely, O my Lord, that ſuch vnworthy perſons ſhould preſume to ſerue or attend on thee? where is the honor and reuerence, that is due to thy Princely Majeſty. DE. What anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were do you receaue againe from him? LOV. I cannot certaynely tell thee, ſauing that he makes me weepe for joy, and ſayeth. Care not thou much for that, let not this thing trouble thee, conſdering thou haſt not of thy ſelfe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured this place, nor intruded into it, but art called to it, and choſen by mee. My ſelfe beſt knoweth why I haue placed thee in it. Let thy only care be, diligently to diſcharge thy office, and with thy vttermoſt power to performe, what thy duety bindeth thee to, in the place thou art appointed, and then take thou care for no other matter. DE. What ſay you to him, when you come before him, accompanied with your aſſociates <hi>Humility, Feare,</hi> and <hi>Reuerence?</hi> LOVE. &amp;c. Firſt I diſpatch thoſe prayers, and diuine ſeruice which this order of life, my
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:18006:59"/>vowe, and profeſſion binde me to, and that not ſadly or vnwillingly, or only for neceſſity: but with as great attention, deuotion, diligence, willingnes, chearefulnes, &amp; reuerence as I can. And although I be bounde of neceſſity to ſuch prayers. Yet chaunge I may neceſſity into a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy will; and moſt joyfully performe what I am bound to doe. Then, that I may craue ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of him, and may moue him to graunt it me; I endeuour with all my power to prayſe and laude him, and ceaſe not to honour him, aſſuring my ſelfe that, that is acceptable to him. And in prayſing him, I deſire his miraculous workes which he hath done, pleaſing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting my ſelfe in remembring them, and exerciſe my ſelfe in telling his mighty power, high wiſdome and exceeding goodnes. And farther I rehearce the great grace &amp; large boun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties, which he beſtoweth on his ſouldiers and ſeruants, honouring exalting him for the ſame. Neither paſſe I in ſilence his exceeding great mercy, which he euer hath and ſtill doth ſhew towardes his enemies, and am much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſed at his gentleneſſe and clemencie. That not only he doth not reuenge himſelf on them: but beſides beſtoweth great rewardes vppon them. Beſides I render great thankes to him for the great goodnes, which is in himſelfe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyte and number his vertues, and renowne his
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:18006:60"/>beauty, wiſdome &amp; exceeding goodnes, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him for them, and rejoycing, and trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phing that he is ſo exceeding great and good. And this doe I often, knowing ſufficiently his will herein, and not doubting, but that it is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to him, and that it is his pleaſure that man ſhould be conuerſant with himſelfe, that is with God, and conferre with him of pleaſant, joyfull and ſecret miſteries: whereof they are ignorant, that be careleſſe thereof, and will not enter into his ſecret chamber with him, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they be in his houſe, and attend vpon him. DE. Wherefore doe you prayſe him with all theſe high titles? LOVE. &amp;c. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the more I extoll, commend, and prayſe him, the more I diſpleaſe, deſpiſe, and ſet at nought my ſelfe: which how acceptable it is to him, cannot be declared with tongue. And this is his will &amp; pleaſure, that we continually haue ſet before our eyes his goodnes, his excellency, and his infinite greatnes: and our owne malice, our baſenes, and exceeding miſery. And far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I am certayne that I cannot be deceaued, although I prayſe and honour him all that is in my power: for he is farre more noble, more excellent, more potent, and greater, then either I or all creatures togither, both Angelicall and humaine can comprehend with thought.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:18006:60"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 7.</hi> Of the office of the Loue of God, in an other degree, and a contmuation of that, which he beganne to declare, of the manner of praying.</head>
               <p>LOVE. &amp;c. After that I haue endeuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to prayſe, and exalt him with the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of my power, I offer vp to him my whole minde and will, with a chiefe <hi>Purpoſe</hi> that I haue, that for no worldly thing I would offend or diſpleaſe him: and alſo moſt earneſtly I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate him, that it may pleaſe him to keepe and preſerue me in this will and minde, conſidering that without him, I am no way able to doe it. Then aske I forgiuenes of him, for all the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences and iniuries I haue done vnto him, and beſeech him that he will permit me to thinke vpon, vnderſtand, or loue nothing but himſelf. And yet farther I deſire of him, that conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring he hath voutſafed to admit me for his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant and friend, &amp; that into a place of ſo high a function: that it will pleaſe him to beſtowe on mee the holy ſpirit of <hi>Humility:</hi> which may withdrawe and turne away my minde, from all things diſpleaſing, and hatefull to him, that my ſeruice be not hatefull but acceptable to him. Alſo I craue of him that he will beſtow on me ſuch things as he knoweth, I ſtand in neede of, whither they bee ſuch thinges as are neceſſary for me, or ſuch as for his honour and pleaſure,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:18006:61"/>he will haue me endued with: and that, for no other cauſe, but that he would ſuffer me to liue and die in him, and not caſt me from his ſight according to my deſert. After this I pray for all thoſe that I loue moſt, and to whome either ſpiritually or corporally I hold my ſelfe bound for all this ſociety, and for all liuing creatures, that it will pleaſe him to beſtowe his grace and mercy on them; that according to their due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, they may knowe him, loue him, honour, prayſe, and worſhippe him. All this doe I labour to preſent to him, with ſincerity and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of hart. DE. How doeſt thou preſent thy ſelfe before him with this purity of heart? LoVE. &amp;c. As neare as I can, I keepe a watch ouer my hart and minde, and take a care to my ſoule, reſtrayning as much as I may all my ſenſes, and continually ſetting before my ſelfe playne ſimplicity, which doth inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret to the beſt whatſoeuer I behold. And if I would bee free and ſecure from all feare: then doe I remayne and abide with my Lord and Maſter, with whome to be preſent, and to talke and conferre, and whoſe counſaill and aduice to demand, is my chiefe good and joy, my only will and comfort. Neither can I enjoy peace, quiet, or ſecurity, or finde anie manner of contentement, or eaſe, but only when I am preſent in his company. And for this cauſe
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:18006:61"/>haue I determined with my ſelfe, to forſake all worldly pleaſures, and to dwell with him, and cleaue to him, neuer to depart from him except hee ſhall command mee. DE. Yet I thinke it very neceſſary ſometimes to be bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied in reading good bookes. LOVE. &amp;c. True it is, it is good to ſpend ſome time in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, but not with a minde to become learned and skilfull, but that thereby thou maiſt finde out GOD and his wayes, and once hauing found him, maiſt knowe and loue him. For this I ſhall not neede many bookes. This one thing I looke after, will, and deſire, that I may ſettle and fix my whole loue on GOD, and may joyne all my affection, reaſon, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to him. For his loue alone is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for me, he will teach me all thinges that ſhall be conuenient for me to knowe, and can open and diſcouer more ſecrets and miſteries to mee, how I ſhall loue and not offend him, then all the books that the whole world doth poſſeſſed. And I obtayne greater purity of ſoule, feare, deuotion, reuerence, compun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, fortitude and ſtrength, and ſeuerity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the fleſh, by being in his preſence, then by reading continually. Beſides I know for certayne, hee neuer will aske account how much I haue reade: but how much I haue lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued amd eſteemed him. Neither would I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togither
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:18006:62"/>exclude or baniſh reading, eſpecially for ſuch as are yet ſimple and ignorant, and knowe not howe to iudge of their thoughts, wordes, and workes. For to ſuch it is requiſite to ſpend much time in reading, &amp; to learne the exerciſes of the ſpirit &amp; minde. For as it would be thought great follie, raſhnes, and diſgrace to a Prince, if a rude country fellow not accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to ſpeake to a King, ſhould preſume in the preſence of all his nobility to come, and bouldly ſpeake his minde, and if in ſpeaking he ſhould vſe his accuſtomed, ruſticall and vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent termes, it could not but be thought ſo great a diſgrace to the Prince, that he iuſtly might comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d him to be thruſt out from his preſence and farre better had it beene, he had neuer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed thither, euen ſo ſtandeth the caſe in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall caſes. But to thoſe that by reading, and hearing, haue alredy attayned to the knowledg of God, and diuine exerciſes, to ſuch, the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of praying is more neceſſary then reading, as being alredy expert how to behaue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the ſpirituall Court. Farther when I preſent my ſelfe, before my Lord and Maſter. I am very carefull, that inconſtantly I turne not my head or eyes, hither or thither. For it would be taken a great diſhonour to him, to looke an other way, whileſt on ſhould talke with him. DE. Tell me your meaning more
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:18006:62"/>plainely for as yet I vnderſtand not. LOVE. When I ſpeake to my Maſter, if at ſuch time I buſie my thoughts, and reaſon vpon anie thing but only vpon him I ſpeake to: then turne I my backe not my face to him. For this cauſe when I perſwade my ſelfe, that I am preſent before him in ſight, and that he doth behold me, and neuer turneth his eyes from me, but marketh what I ſay: I vſe all reuerence, deuotion, loue and attention to him that I can. Then doe I prayſe and thanke him for all his benefits be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on mee, and all other his creatures, calling them often to my minde, and rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them, being moſt certayne that he woul not haue me in-grate and vnmindefull of his giftes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 8.</hi> Of the third degree of Loue.</head>
               <p>LOVE. &amp;c. Now although I haue ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the firſt degree, or ſteppe, of my loue, which is to loue my Lord and Maſter, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to offend him: and alſo the ſecond, which is to performe and put in practiſe all his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements: yet doe I not content my ſelfe herewith, in regarde my loue is ſo great to him, but that I adde yet a third degree, or ſteppe to his loue, which is to doe all thoſe thinges
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:18006:63"/>that I knowe are pleaſing to him, or whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer I can imagine he would I ſhould doe. DE. How knowe you, that you doe thoſe thinges that pleaſe him? LOVE. &amp;c. There be two thinges whereby I may knowe that eaſely: which are, if I loue that which he loueth, and likewiſe hate, what is hatefull to him. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the firſt, which is, to loue what he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth: I loue his Sonne, the moſt beautifull, ſweete, and noble, of all that euer were, and moſt like his Father, and ſo obedient to him, as neuer was, or ſhall be Sonne more obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to a Father. Whome the Father loueth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as himſelfe, becauſe he is more like to him, then euer Sonne vvas to a Father. And ſo greate is the loue and vnion which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them, that they two be but one; of one will, like power, and the ſelfe ſame knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Who although they be diſtinct in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, yet are they both one in eſſence. For this Sonne, the Father hath made a garment with the handes of his goodnes, like to that which Sheepheardes doe weare, which the Sonne hauing put on, departed out of the priuy Chamber of his princely Father, and yet for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer remayneth with him. And thus he liueth here in this Monaſtery, and conuerſeth with vs. For otherwiſe we could not behold him. Moreouer when his Father would ſend him
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:18006:63"/>ouer all the world, cladde with this garment, &amp; a little traueling ſcrippe: he entred alſo into this deſert, to ſeeke out his ſheepe that were wandered and ſtrayed. And as hee trauailed through this deſert, the Father permitted that he ſhould be killed of wolues, and deuoured of dogs, and would giue him no helpe although he could: but would haue him endure a moſt cruell death by theſe wolues, more painefull to him, then euer any ſffered, being his fleſh moſt tender, in that he weas the Son of a King. All this did our Lord of his exceeding loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vs, that all we that dwell and abide in his houſe, might know, and trie his charity, and thereby might loue him againe, conſidering that firſt he loued vs ſo greatly, that he ſpared not his one only Son, but deliuered him to die for the loue he bare to vs al. Whileſt the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> was relating this diſcourſe, <hi>Deſire</hi> being wholy wounded to the hart could not refraine from vehement weeping. But the <hi>Loue of God</hi> going on with his diſcourſe, ſaid farther. And although God the Father hath ſuffered his Son to be killed, yet notwithſtanding he loueth him ſo exceedingly, that by his great omnipotency, he ſoone rayſed him from death, much more beautifull, and gloriouſly triumphing, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with him, the ſheep which he came to ſeeke others being left in this wilderneſſe, that they
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:18006:64"/>might be fedde and become fat with the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of him, he hauing a perpetual and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full care ouer them. So at length returning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to his Princely Father, he ſitteth nowe on his right hand, ſpeaking and making inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for vs al, being ouercome with to great a loue towardes vs. For I am of this opinion, that except we were ſpared for his ſake, long ſince had we beene driuen cleane out of this Monaſterie: ſo wicked and miſerable we are, and ſo negligently, and ſloathfully wee ſerue him, wholy forgette him and contemne him, and ſo little care and remembrance we haue of him. But the Omnipote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t father loueth this Son ſo greatly; that in my opinion nothing can be more acceptable to him in this world, then that we ſhould loue this, his Sonne with him. For which cauſe I endeuour &amp; labour to loue him, &amp; to do thoſe thinges which I thinke pleaſing to him. DE. What is it, that you can doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to him? LOVE. &amp;c In remembring and ſpeaking of his moſt holy life, his paines &amp; laboures, his moſt bitter death and Paſsion, &amp; his holy commandements, and as neare as I can conformity my ſelf according to his manners. For who ſoeuer my Lord &amp; Maſter ſeeth moſt carefully to imitate the life of his Son, him doth he moſt loue, and holde deare to him. And for this cauſe, was it his holy will and pleaſure, that
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:18006:64"/>he ſhould come &amp; liue here amongſt vs, that by that meanes he might teach vs how we ſhould liue, who before liued no better then bruite beaſts. Therefore hath our ord ſet him before our eyes, as a mirrour, or looking glaſſe, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one may knowe, whether he doe, or omit what his pleaſure is, and may ſee and behold in the life of his Sonne, as in a glaſſe, whether his works be good or badde. Neither is there any thing in all the world, by which we may more trulie come to the knowledge thereof. And yet beſides this, there is one thing more, which my Lord and M. loueth, that is my Boy, called <hi>the loue of our Neighbour,</hi> whome he eſteemeth ſo much, and holdeth ſo deare, that whatſoeuer we doe to him, be it good or bad, he taketh as if it were done to himſelfe. DE. How doe you loue this Boy? LOVE. &amp;c. Euen as my ſelfe. And firſt I perſwade my ſelfe that he is better then I am, and although I execute a higher place, yet in all thinges that are agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to vertue, I obey him. I farther am care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that by no meanes I afflict him, or giue him occaſion of ſorrowe, but ſhewe all loue and kindneſſe to him that I can. I neuer haue ſiniſter conceite of him, but rather excuſe him all that I may. I neuer call him by anie name of diſgrace. I moſt willingly diſſemble, and hide his naturall defectes and imperfections.
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:18006:65"/>In diſtreſte and aduerſitie, I lament and bewaile him. In his abſence I detract him not, neither ſuffer others to doe if I may hinder it. I wiſh and deſire, that my Lord and Maſter be better beloued of him, then of my ſelfe: and that it would pleaſe God to make him as good, or better then I my ſelfe am. I enuie him nothing either for corporall or ſpirituall giftes beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on him by God, or for any thing which he enjoyeth in this world, but rejoyce in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, and lament in his aduerſity. Farther, I thinke him to be the Angell of God; and my ſelfe to be vnworthy to be his ſeruant. This doe I, for that I knowe him to be beloued of my Maſter. Alſo I loue thoſe thinges vvhich appertaine to our ſocietie, towardes which, I carry a very great zeale, in regarde that they appertaine to the worſhippe, &amp; honour of my Lord and Maſter, and to the preſeruation and maintenance of this his houſe. Wherefore I am very carefull, that nothing be loſt, or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed, eſpecially of thoſe thinges which belong to the ſeruice of Religion, Ceremonies, and the holy Canons of the Church. Which thinges although many doe not greatly eſteeme, yet I am fully perſwaded, that the holy Ghoſt would neuer haue inſtituted them, except hee had knowne them to be pleaſing to God. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I holde the ſmalleſt Ceremonies, to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:18006:65"/>imagining they tend to the honour of God, and moſt readely and willingly, with all humility, &amp; reuerence doe I keepe them. And this thought doe I ſtill carry in my minde, if I ſhould not honour my Lord and Maſter, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe him carefully, ſerue him dutifully, and ſhewe my ſelfe moſt zealous in his ſeruice, who ſhould doe it? conſidering I am beholding to him, more then all other creatures. For if the ſeruants and attendants of great Princes and States ſerue and obey their Maſters, ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, diligently, and with ſo great a deſire; why ſhould not I ſerue and honour my Maſter and Lord, that admitteth me to the familiarity of his chamber. Therefore if the whole world ſhould fall, and decline from his obedience, and not one ſhould perſeuer to ſhewe him reuerence: yet woulde I remayne faithfull, euen vntill my laſt moment of life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 9.</hi> Of thoſe things which the Loue of God hateth, and a concluſion of his dutie and office.</head>
               <p>THe other thing of the two, which I ſpake of before, wherewith I pleaſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent my Lord &amp; Maſter, is, to hate ſuch things as I knowe he hateth. And two eſpeciall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies I knowe my Maſter hath, which are <hi>The world,</hi> and <hi>My fleſh.</hi> Wherefore I haue reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with my ſelfe, to hate them all, that I can,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:18006:66"/>&amp; to haue neither friendſhip or peace with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which determinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to performe, I purpoſe an other thing, which is, to take no delight or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, neuer to talke or conuerſe fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miliarly with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, except it be by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my M. which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement is of more weight, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any <hi>Purpoſe</hi> I can vndertake. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haue I beſought the Superior of this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery, that he neuer ſend me abrod, into twon or contry for my recreatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or diſport, which is a thing different fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my diſpoſition, &amp; which I hate: yet when he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth it, I muſt needs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey him. And although for ſome cauſes my M. command me ſomtimes to goe abroad into the world, yet will he that I returne with all the ſpeed that I can make, for feare leſt I be caught and deceaued with the deceites thereof: being aſſured, that how warely ſoeuer men conuerſe therein, yet more hurt than good commeth euer thereby. Likewiſe do I deteſt &amp; hate my owne faultes and vncleanes, my il motions &amp; deſires, my ſodaine paſſions &amp; promiſe to ſin, not igno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rant how hatefull they be to my Lord and M. And therfore for the loue of him, I continually labor to amend my ſelfe. Beſides I ſequeſter my ſelfe from all that dwell in this Monaſtery (for his loue) except when charity &amp; neceſſitie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary. Neither doe I it for that cauſe that I contemne them, or thinke them vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:18006:66"/>of my company &amp; fellowſhip (for as I ſaid before, I eſteeme them as Saints and Angelles) but rather becauſe I thinke my ſelfe vnworthy of their preſence and conuerſation, or meete to kiſſe the ground that they treade on. DE. Why do you ſo? LO. Becauſe in theſe times Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is much decayed, by reaſon of to much familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and conuerſing of ſuch as profes monaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal liues, not only amongſt themſelues, but alſo amongſt ſecular perſons. Whereby it chanceth that ſo little prayer, deuotion and meditation is vſed. For in theſe daies ſome Monaſteries are become like Princes Palaces, and only in name &amp; habit they ſhew themſelues religious: when they treate of, and handle naught, but worldy cauſes: &amp; holines &amp; religion is ſo rare amongſt ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they neuer frequent their deuo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions, but when they meet in their <hi>Oratories,</hi> out of which they talke of nothing, but worldy bu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſineſſes, and newes, being alwaies ſo diſtracted, that they know not how to collect their minds to ſerue God: and when they are called againſt their wils to their <hi>Oratories,</hi> to ſing their ſeruice they feare they ſhall not ſoone enough depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence againe: &amp; thus they ſing their ſeruice being full of high miſteries, with litle reuerence or no deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at al, hauing their minds &amp; deſire on the end, &amp; in the kitchen. And beauſe they vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d litle of God, or what appertayneth
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:18006:67"/>to him: God likewiſe regardeth them not, but hateth them. Therefore haue I determined to inure my ſelfe to a cuſtome, and to endeuour to be alwaies ſolitary, and attend my deuotions that ſo my minde may take delight in God, and thoſe thinges that appertaine to him, and that I may learne to loue him, as in truth it is moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, conſidering that for that cauſe I haue forſaken the world, &amp; withdrawne my ſelf hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. DE. Some will ſay thou art ſingular, &amp; wil note thee for it. LOVE. I regard not that, for I ought not deſire to pleaſe men: eſpecially whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſhall diſpleaſe and offend God. And ſo long as I am not ſcandalous to others, let them think or ſpeake their pleaſures of me. That which I doe, is but my office, and dutie, if therfore thou ſeeke me, doe thou as I haue done.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 10.</hi> The Loue of God brought defire into the houſe.</head>
               <p>IN this meane time <hi>Deſire</hi> was much amazed, and bethought himſelfe of thoſe thinges which he had heard of the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> and ſaid to him. DE. When you haue done all theſe thinges, is there cauſe that you ſhoulde be in feare of any thing? LOVE. &amp;c. Yea trulie. I muſt with great care and ſtudie ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, that by doing well I fall not into vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory, and ſelfe liking. For if ſo I ſhould yeeld to them, preſently my Maſter would expel me
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:18006:67"/>this Monaſtery. Therefore haue I alwaies <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility</hi> my Mother by my ſide. DE. Carry me I beſeech you into the houſe. LOVE. Followe me, for thou haſt had conference enough with me. I will bring thee vnto an other fellowe of mine, whoſe office is higher, and more worthy then mine. DE. What is his name? LOVE. He is called <hi>Deſire of God.</hi> Now <hi>Deſire</hi> vvent with a chearefull minde, accompanied with the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> to ſeeke <hi>Deſire of God,</hi> and hauing founde him, he asked of him if he were <hi>Deſire of God.</hi> DESIRE OF GOD. I am hee thou ſeekeſt, what wouldeſt thou with me DE. I would intreat to be admitted to your ſeruice. Here <hi>Deſire of God</hi> was delighted with the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die will of <hi>Deſire,</hi> and ſaid to him. DESIRE OF GOD. If thou deſire to liue with me, thou muſt be wel inſtructed by my brother the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> For <hi>Deſire of God</hi> is made of the wine that runneth out of that veſſell of the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> See therefore thou be firſt well inſtructed by the <hi>loue of God,</hi> leaſt otherwiſe thou deceaue thy ſelfe. DE. I haue conuerſed ſometime with the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> who hath inſtructed me of all things that are neceſſary for me to doe. Which I hope through Gods helpe, to be able to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute. But I cannot aſſure you, making no doubt whether I am endued with the <hi>Loue of God</hi> or no, conſidering it is a thing known only to him
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:18006:68"/>ſelfe, who loue, or doe not loue him. Therefore herein I humble my ſelfe to his wiſdome. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can I aſſure you, I haue any thing of my ſelfe, one thing excepted which is <hi>Good will</hi> my dogge, whome neither, I dare preſume to cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge as my owne, conſidering I haue him by the gifte of another. Theſe wordes of <hi>Deſire,</hi> pleaſed <hi>Deſire of God,</hi> the rather conſidering, he perceaued that <hi>Deſire</hi> durſt not attribute to him ſelf his loue of God. DE. Now Sir, let me craue to knowe your conditions &amp; office. DESIRE. Euen as a man through true knowledge of him ſelfe, attayneth to great contempt, and hatred of himſelfe, &amp; as through true knowledge of God a man likewiſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to perfect loue of God. So by much louing of God, a man is brought to the greater deſire of God. And whoſoeuer he be that getteth me: he deſireth nothing els that this world can yeeld. For with ſuch vertue and worthines doe I adorne his minde: that he thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth himſelfe vnmeete, to deſire any thing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that moſt excellent, moſt rare, &amp; moſt to be deſired good. Which is only our lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. I ſay, I make him the moſt excellent of the world. For although he be borne but of meane parentage: yet do I make him a mighty King. For whoſoeuer is trulie endued with me, he thinketh on nothing but only on God: he ſpeaketh nothing but only on God: becauſe that wherſoeuer his treaſure is, there he ſetteth
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:18006:68"/>his hart. And whatſoeuer the hart profoundly thinketh, that eſpecially the mouth vttereth. And thoſe thinges which are deliuered by the conſent of the mouth, apparantly declare the thought of the hart. I am the foode and repaſt of that minde, which liueth, and is nouriſned by good deſire: in this houſe of <hi>Charitie,</hi> I am of higheſt dignity, and keepe the dore of the ſecret chamber of the foreſaid <hi>Charity,</hi> and haue authority to admit ſuch friendes as I allowe of. Here vſe I the office of a Cryer, or a Trumpet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and walking about this Monaſtery, make certaine cries and ſoundes, vntill ſuch time as I awake and ſtirre vp my Maſter, and cauſe him to come forth to ſpeake with ſuch as ſeek him. Who doeſ thou thinke awaked me euen now, when thou ſtoodeſt calling ſo long at the gate, &amp; knockedſt with the hammers of teares, and ſighes? truly the barking of thy dog. I am the trueſt meſſenger of <hi>Charitie</hi> &amp; come firſt to the gate, ſpeake firſt to my Mam neareſt to him, &amp; am ſooneſt heard of him. Farther, it is in me to diſtribute the fruit of a moſt rare tree, which we haue, called the <hi>ſight of God</hi> &amp;, I do giue it to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to eate. DE. Is this fruit pleſant in taſt. For in the houſe of <hi>Humilitie</hi> an other fruit was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen me, moſt bitter to eate, eſpecially at the firſt it coulde hardly be ſwallowed. DESIRE. OF GOD. This fruit is moſt ſweete, yet far
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:18006:69"/>ſweeter in the taſt of ſome men, then of others, according as men are more deſirous and hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry after it, &amp; as they haue their taſt &amp; mouthes moſt perfect. Some there be whoſe teeth are but dul or blunt: with whome this fruit agreeth not, becauſe they cannot hold it. Other ſome eate it without hunger or appetite: hauing their ſtomakes ful &amp; ouercharged with other meates; to theſe men likewiſe it taſteth not pleaſantly, neither is it lightly diſgeſted of them, yet neuer theleſſe it doth not hurt them. Some others there be, which by reaſon of ſome ague or ſome immoderate heate haue not their taſt ſo good as others, and theſe cannot judge the goodnes of this fruit, but only according as they ſhall heare by others. DE. I beſeech you, giue me leaue to taſt a little of this fruit. DESIRE OF GOD. It pleaſeth me that thou ſayeſt to taſt a little thereof: for in this mortall life no man may eate thereof his fill: only he may taſ and trie how ſweete it is. DE. Why ſo? DESIRE OF GOD. If any man might enjoy it here to the full of his deſire, he would neuer deſire to depart from this world, and to goe to heauen. Know therefore that liuing here in this value of miſery, almoſt dead through hunger, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of ſtrength, by reaſon of long penury: we ought longly to watch and deſire that day, wherein we may enter, into that great ſupper
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:18006:69"/>of our King and Maſter, deſiring and thirſting after him in no other manner, then doth the hart thirſt for the cleare fountaine in the hoteſt So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer. And ſuch is the vertue and force of this fruit, that one little morſell be it neuer ſo ſmall doth ſatiate a mans ſtomacke, bee hee neuer ſo great an eater. But being once come to the preſence of this King and Maſter, hee will make our ſtomacke better and ſtronger, that wee ſhall bee able to eate of this fruit, ſo much as we will, and neuer receaue hurt or preiudice by it. But here if any one eate more of it, then his ſtomacke can beare: he ſhall rather receaue hurt then good thereby. Therefore muſt we moderately eate of this fruit, vntill we arriue at that place of happines, where for euer we ſhall be filled all meaſure, with that ſame fruit which here we doe but only taſte.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER 11.</hi> How Deſire of God prepared, Deſire to eate of this fruit.</head>
               <p>DE. Now then Sir, I beſeech you beſtowe vpon me to eate ſo much of this fruit, as your ſelfe ſhall thinke good. DESIRE OF GOD. Firſt then conſidering, this fruit is not conteyned, but in a moſt cleane veſſell: it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooueth that thou clenſe and make cleane thy teeth, and that thou waſh thy mouth, thy eyes, thy face, thyhandes and feete. DE. Where
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:18006:70"/>may I finde water, wherwith to do it? DESIRE OF GOD. I will bring thee to a liuing foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne, that continually runneth both night and day, called <hi>Holie Religion,</hi> alſo I will aſſemble the Virgins of this Monaſtery, who ſhall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt to waſh and purifie thee. This much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented <hi>Deſire,</hi> and gladly did he expect the comming of theſe Virgins, when behould he ſawe <hi>Deſire</hi> of GOD, come and bring them with him, ſaying, theſe be the Virgins that ſhall waſh thee. The firſt is called <hi>Sweetnes.</hi> The ſecond <hi>Concord.</hi> The third <hi>Pitty or Compaſſion.</hi> The fourth <hi>Grace.</hi> The fift <hi>Clemencie.</hi> The ſixt <hi>Indulgence.</hi> The ſeuenth <hi>Mercy.</hi> The eight <hi>Beneuolence.</hi> The ninth <hi>Gentlenes.</hi> The tenth <hi>Sufferance.</hi> The eleuenth <hi>Tranquility.</hi> The twelfe <hi>Securitie.</hi> The thirtenth <hi>Ior.</hi> The four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenth <hi>Diſcretion</hi> or <hi>Moderation.</hi> The fiftenth <hi>Deuotion.</hi> Who will giue thee a certayne ſawce, that ſhall procure thee an appetite, whereby more willingly &amp; pleaſingly thou ſhalt eat this fruit. For it is only giuen to ſuch a hunger after it, but others are ſent away empty without it. The ſixtenth Virgin is <hi>Religion.</hi> The ſeuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenth is <hi>Perſeuerance.</hi> The eightenth is <hi>Prayer.</hi> The nintenth is <hi>Honeſtie,</hi> and my ſelfe <hi>Deſire of God,</hi> am the laſt, who am euer preſent at this holy Monaſtery of Virgins. And if thou wilt likewiſe aſſociate thy ſelfe with them, it will
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:18006:70"/>prepare thee not a little to eate this fruit, which ſo ſone as thou haſt eaten, thou ſhalt euer after haue theſe Virgins thy companions, who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer will forſake thee, except thou firſt aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don them. For they be very greedy to eate of this meate, and ſo ſone as they eſpie this fruit. They flie to it, as bees will doe to honny, and we cannot better knowe when a man hath this fruit, then if we ſee theſe Virgins flocking ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his gates. Now <hi>Deſire</hi> being waſhed and well recreated with eating this fruit, was won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully comforted, to whome <hi>Deſire of God</hi> ſaid, conſidering Brother that thou haſt eaten of this fruit, it is nowe expedient that thou doe ſing alſo. For the ſeruants of GOD, after they haue eate their meate vſe to ſing, giuing thankes and prayſe to GOD, and none a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth in this houſe, that is not expert in ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. DE. After what manner ſhall I ſing? DESIRE OF GOD. Wee will goe to the quyer where all the ſingers abide. The firſ is called, <hi>Benediction or Bleſſing.</hi> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Honour.</hi> The third <hi>Prayſing.</hi> The fourth <hi>Thankesgiuing,</hi> amongſt theſe muſt thou ſing, who are excellent Muſitions, and haue ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler ſweete voyces. DE. What part muſt I ſing? DESIRE OF GOD. The firſt as I haue ſaid is called <hi>Beneduction,</hi> he ſingeth the treble and prayſeth God for his high omnipotency.
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:18006:71"/>The ſecond <hi>Honur,</hi> he ſingeth the Conterte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, &amp; prayſeth God for his infinite wiſedome. The third <hi>Prayſing,</hi> he ſingeth the Tenor, and extolleth the wonderfull goodnes of God, and all his vertues, his noblenes, and excellency, &amp; all that is in him. The fourth <hi>Thankesgiuing,</hi> he ſingeth the Baſſe and giueth thankes to GOD for all his creatures, &amp; for al the benefits which he hath beſtowed on them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 12.</hi> How Deſire learned to ſing.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DEſire</hi> was now much delighted, both with the manner of ſinging, and alſo with the ſong, to whom <hi>Deſire of God</hi> ſaid, now be think the ſelfe whither thou wilt returne from hence or no. DE. Whither can I goe, that I may better my ſelfe, eſpecially, conſidering I am come hither with ſo great labour &amp; difficulty. For findingmy ſelfe to be well entertayned here, and to liue in peace, and all contentement by no meanes will I depart from hence, for the old Prouerbe ſayeth, he that is well let him not chaunge his place, therefore Sir, I cannot be perſwaded to depart, except you will by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence expell expell me. DESIRE OF GOD. It is not our cuſtome to expell any againſt their willes, rather doe we entreate ſuch as enter in, hither, that they will maketheir abodes here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs. Yet that they may knowe, that wee
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:18006:71"/>admit none for our owne neceſſity: ſometimes we aske of them whither they will depart. But ſeing thou haſt determined to continue here, thou muſt not liue and be idle here. For no idle body dwelleth here, or that doth not ſpend his time in good exerciſes. DE. What muſt I doe? DESIRE OF GOD. Whatſoeuer is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to thee. DE. If I am commanded no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, ſhall I be idie? DESIRE OF GOD. Thou ſhalt ſing, and giue thankes, and prayſe to God, for thou art admitted hither eſpecially to ſing. And whileſt thou art in doing, that which thou art commaded, thou maieſt ſing to thy ſelf leſt tho be trobled with idle thoughts. But if thou deſire to profit much, and greatly to pleaſe our Lord and Maſter, and to inſinuate thy ſelfe into his friendſhippe, as much as thou canſt, (if nothing elſe be commanded to thee,) conuerſe and conferre with him alone. Then ſhalt thou heare what he will ſpeake in thee, &amp; thou ſhalt learnemany ſecretes that he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueale to thee, andthou ſhalt become his moſt inwarde frend. DE. May any enter into his chamber, and ſpeake with him? DESIRE OF GOD. Yea truely, ſo that he be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with <hi>Humility.</hi> And farther I aſſure thee he taketh eſpeciall delight, when any will come to him and ſeeke to awake him. For it is his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture not to deſire to be alone, and be a man ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:18006:72"/>ſo meane or baſe, yet doth he delight to haue him deſire his preſence. And ſo great is his dignity &amp; worthines that he regardeth not his perſon, or maketh any diference of their birthes that ſue to him, regarding only the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility of their mindes. One man is as deare to him as an other, and he created them all of one and the ſame matter. Yea more, the more baſe and vile the perſon is, ſo that he debaſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject himſelfe; the greater doth he declare his loue towardes him. And to ſay truth thoſe which dwell in this Monaſtery amongſt vs, the greateſt part of them (ſome fewe excepted) are borne but of meane &amp; baſe parentage. For ſuch as the world contemneth as abjects, thoſe doth God chooſe for his faithfulleſt ſeruantes, that none of this ſociety ſhould flatter themſelues: that they deſerued of themſelues to be admitted hither, and not through the ſpeciall grace and goodnes of God. If therefore thou deſire to continue amongſt vs, and to ſing amongſt our other ſigners, and deſire farther that thy ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing may be pleaſing, and acceptable to God, thou muſt labour to obſerue theſe foure things. The firſt is <hi>A good will.</hi> The ſecond <hi>Humility.</hi> The third <hi>Patience.</hi> The fourth <hi>Charity.</hi> Which if thou doeſt, thou ſhalt neuer erre in ſinging. And although ſometimes thou chance to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect ſome part, yet by dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t obſeruation, thou
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:18006:72"/>ſhalt eaſely come into meaſure againe. With the firſt meaſure or tune, which is <hi>A good will,</hi> thou ſhalt ſing the plaine ſong, which is (as it were) he ground &amp; fondation of the others. With the ſecond and third, I meane <hi>Humility</hi> &amp; <hi>Patience,</hi> thou ſhalt ſing the Contertenor, for <hi>Humility</hi> &amp; <hi>Patience,</hi> are contrary to ſelfe will. With the fourth, which is <hi>Charity,</hi> thou ſhalt explayne, and declare the ſound and tune, of the Organs, and that with exceeding ſweetnes &amp; harmony of thy ſoule &amp; ſpirit. And if it fortune that thou be out of tune preſently, haue recourſe to the firſt note or meaſure. Alſo if thou chaunce to ſing contrary to thy fellowes, obſerue him that directeth thee, who will bring thee ſone into tune againe, through his helpe and aſſiſtance, and with the loue of our Lord &amp; Maſter. And in all thy ſinging obſerue this one thing dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, that thou forget not to eate the fruit, which thou dideſt gather, in the houſe of <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility,</hi> I meane <hi>Diſtrust of thy ſelfe,</hi> for the more thou attayneſt to the Loue and Deſire of God, the better thou ſhalt knowe him, and ſweeter ſhalt thou finde him. To conclude the more thou ſhalt offer of this fruit to my Lord and Maſter, the greater ſhalt thou finde his loue and friendſhippe towardes thee, for willingly doth he eate of it, and moſt pleaſing is it to him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:18006:73"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 13.</hi> How <hi>Deſire of God,</hi> brought <hi>Deſire</hi> into the chamber of his <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Maſter,</hi> and of the mannerof Praying.</head>
               <p>DE. One thing there remayneth yet which I would enteate of you, that now conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering. You haue graunted me, to be a ſeruant of this houſe, you will farther bring me, to the knowledge of my Maſter, that I may ſe him &amp; kiſſe his hand. DESIRE OF GOD. Follow me in &amp; I will graunt thy deſire. Now beganne <hi>Deſie</hi> to feare and to tremble, thinking that he muſt ſpeake with a King of ſo great Majeſty in his priuy chamber, and ſo great was his feae and his aſtoyniſhment, that neither could he or durſt he preſume to come neare him, but nowe beganne to thinketo goe back againe. But ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſing better with himſelfe, and thinking that he was a ſweete, a noble, and an affable King, and curteous, and gentle to all men, he tooke hart againe truſting wholy to he gentlenes of him. Hee <hi>Deſire of God</hi> bidde him ſtay at the dore, vntill he went in to his Maſter, and told him how <hi>Deſire</hi> deſired to ſpeake with him. And now againe beganne <hi>Deſire</hi> to be doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, how, and in what manner he ſhould ſpeake to his Lord and Maſter. When <hi>Deſire of God</hi> comming to him tould him, he had acuained his Maſter with his beingthere, and therefore
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:18006:73"/>badde him goe in, and he would ſtay for him there. Now <hi>Deſire</hi> beganne with exceeding great reuerence to enter the houſe, and goe into the haule, who ſo ſone as he eſpied his Lord &amp; Maſter, he fell proſtrate on the ground, and beganne to weepe, not preſuming to lift vp either his head or eyes. For he had not forgot, what an enemy he had beene ſometime to his Maſter, with how many wronges and iniuries he had offended him, how ill and vnreuerently he had ſometimes ſpoken of him, with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance hereof, he was not able to ſpeake, but ſtode weeping and ſighing, ſeing himſelfe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent before the Majeſty of him he had ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offended. OVR L. What meaneth this wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping? What doeſt thou here? ſpeakeſt thou nothing? riſe and ſay what thou wouldeſt haue. DE. What may I preſume to ſpeake <hi>O Lord,</hi> in preſence of thy Majeſty, I acknowledge my ſelfe vnworthy, to open my vncleane mouth in the preſence of ſuch a Lord, admit me to be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and to ſtand ſtill and ſigh, and to bewaile and lament my owne iniquity. OVR LORD. Wherefore then art thou come hither. DE. I of my ſelfe neuer came in hither, for I hold my ſelfe vnworthy to abide in thy houſe, much leſſe worthy to enter thy chamber. OVR LORD. Who then brought thee hither? DE. Thy ſelfe ſweete Lord, thou haſt drawen
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:18006:74"/>me, thou haſt made me cry, and call vpon thee, thou haſt commanded thy gates to be opened, and that I ſhould be brought in hither to thee. My ſelfe am wholy ignorant of the cauſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, or what hath moued thee to it, or what neede thou haſt of me. For I hold in more ſufficient, then that ſo vnworthy a wreatch a I am, ſhold be thought worthy to be the meaneſt of thy ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; a bondman &amp; ſlaue in this thy houſe: although of my ſelfe I cannot deſerue that, and hould my ſelfe vnworthy to obteyne it. But conſidering that it hath pleaſed thee to call me, and that it pleaſeth thee, I ſhall abide with thee, and ſpeake to thee: open thou O <hi>Lord</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee my lippes, and teach me what I ſhall ſay in thy preſence. Plant in mee thy ſpirit of feare and reuerence, that thy Majeſty be not offended by me, or vnreuerendly worſhipped, or vnhonorably entreated from this time fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ofſo vile a ſinner as I acknowledge my ſelfe. For it cannot be done without offering thee great iniurie. And rather had I kil my ſelfe then to offer contempt, ignominie or diſgrace to thy Majeſty. For therby ſhold I offer great iniury and contempt to all Angels, and Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angels, and the whole fellowſhippe of heauen, who with ſo great reuerence, and feruour doe loue and honor thee. Teach me therefore O lord, what I ſhal ſay or do to thee. For I wholy
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:18006:74"/>reſigne my ſelf into thy hands. Grant me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſweete Lord the ſpirit of <hi>Humilitie</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with I may ſerue thee, thy houſe &amp; all thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts; let my ſeruice be acceptable to thee, &amp; be thou O Lord honored and glorified in me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER 14.</hi> How our Lord inſtructed Deſire, how he ſhould behaue himſelfe.</head>
               <p>OVR LO. Riſe upandlay away all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of feare. If he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceforth thou wilt be ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and Godly, &amp; behaue thy ſelfe according to thy duety: I will neuer reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the wrongs and iniuries thou haſt done me. And that thou mayeſt henceforth amend and become, better, I will deliuer thee only foure wordes, which if thou remember, and wilt only obſerue, ſhall be very beneficiall &amp; auaileable to thee. The firſt two are. <hi>I and Thou.</hi> The other two. A <hi>Seruant &amp; a King.</hi> Theſe foure wordes when thou canſt well exerciſe and practize, will bring thee to great perfection &amp; purity of hart: and will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend &amp; deliuer thee from all perturbatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the minde, &amp; will inſtruct thee to liue peaceably &amp; friendly, &amp;conuerſe quietly with al men. DE. Voutſafe O lord to direct me, how I may exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe theſe foure words. OVR LO. Thou maiſt refer all thy exerciſes to theſe foure words, for they are of great importace, &amp; whole volumes might be written of them alone, which of them
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:18006:75"/>ſelues were ſufficient to teach great perfection. Therefore when thou eſolueſt to ſpeake vnto me, if then thou finde thy ſelf could, diſtracted, or diſconte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted for any thing that thou art co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, thinke to thy ſelfe that with theſe wordes alone I ſpeake to thee. <hi>I &amp; Thou.</hi> And then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude from thy minde the whole world, &amp; what ſoeuer thou haſt heard or ſeene in thy life, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining that none, but I <hi>I Thou</hi> are left in this world. The other two wordes, <hi>Seruant &amp; King,</hi> will auaile thee in liuing with thy Brothers in this Houſe. The firſt, wherof <hi>Seruant</hi> will profit thee herein, that thou maiſt imagine thy ſelfe, the ſeruant of all men, whereby thou ſhalt attayne, <hi>Humilitie and Obedience.</hi> The other word <hi>King,</hi> will ſerue thee to remember that thou art King and commander ouer thy ſelfe. For ſuch Kings doe I enritch &amp; loade with al treaſures. For this time be conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with this directio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; haue peace &amp; quietnes, &amp; ſo depart. DE. Wherefore O <hi>Lord</hi> doeſt thou bidde me depart, &amp; wilt that I forſake thy preſence? OVR LO. Thinke not thy ſelfe worthy to abide alwaies with me, but at ſuch times only as I wil, &amp; ſhal ſend for thee, and then take thou heede that thou doe not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend in vaineglory or preſumption. For accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my owne will &amp; pleaſure I wil cal thee. But before thou goe hence, leaue thy hart here with me, that wherſoeuer thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſe thy bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:18006:75"/>part may be with me. DE. Moſt willingly ſweet Lord, I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit my hart to thy protection. OVR LO. I receaue it from thy willing offer, &amp; yet thinke not alwaies that I will doe ſo, for ſometimes for thy benefit, &amp; to humble thee I wil refuſe to keep it. And this one thing I wold not haue thee ignorant of, which peraduenture is vnknowne to thee; That the greater comfort &amp; conſolation I deſire to ſend my friends: with the more troules, aduerſities, &amp; afflictions, I vſe toviſit them. But if thou wilt leaue <hi>Good wil</hi> thy dogge herewith me, he may continually remayne in my preſence, &amp; ſhal neuer goe from me, except thou thy ſelfe wilt, yet neuertheleſſe daylie muſt thou commend him to mee. DE. Why is it needeful that I commend him to thee daylie? ſufficeth it not that I doe it once. OVR LORD. No, and not for feare, leaſt I ſhould forget thee; but leſt thou thy ſelfe proue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindefull of me, and that thou mayeſt haue oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion euer to remember and haue mee in thy minde, whereby I may gratifie and rewarde thee daylie, and according to thy neceſſity and want may helpe and ſuccour thee. For nothing it is to me whither thou be mindefull or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindefull of me. DE. I yeeld thee moſt humble thankes my ſweete Lord and Maſter. Long ſince haue I proued thy goodnes and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolence, for which thou workeſt all thinges in
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:18006:76"/>vs only for our ſaluation and benefit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. 15.</hi> How Deſire put in practiſe the ſcure wordes of his Lord and Master, and what benefit he receaued thereby.</head>
               <p>THus <hi>Deſire</hi> departing out, of the chamber of his Lord and Maſter, &amp; leauing his hart ſtill behinde with him; he found <hi>Deſire of God</hi> without the dore, expecting his comming, to whome he ſaid. What haſt thou done ſo long time within? thinkeſt thou my Lord &amp; Maſter, taketh delight &amp; is pleaſed with many wordes? beleeue me, thou ſhalt ſometime preuaile more with him, with one word then with a hundered. DE. Me thinketh I haue ſtayed to ſhort a time with him. DE. OF GOD. Now viewe &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider all this houſe, conſidering thou art recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in hither. DE. I will goe to my chamber. DE. OF GOD. Goe in the name of God. Now <hi>Deſire</hi> did daylie reuolue in his minde the foure wordes, which his Lord &amp; Maſter had deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him, &amp; oft would ſay to himſelfe. <hi>I &amp; Theu. Seruant and King.</hi> And whenſoeuer hee ſpake them, whither he deuided them, or joyned them yet euer they agreed well togither. For joyning the firſt, which is I. With the third, which is <hi>A Seruant,</hi> he ſaid to himſelf I pronounce them rightly. For, for the loue of my Lord &amp; maſter. I am a ſeruant. Then joyning the firſt with the
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:18006:76"/>laſt which is a <hi>King.</hi> Sill he ſemed to pronounce them rightly. For being the ſeruant of God, he ſaid he was a <hi>King. For to ſerue God: that is to raigne.</hi> Againe ſpeaking them an other way &amp; joyning, <hi>King</hi> with <hi>Seruant.</hi> Still they agreed well togither. For the King of heauen to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent he might make me a King, made himſelfe a Seruant, and whoſoeuer will be a King it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that firſt he make himſelfe a Seruant. Thus did <hi>Deſire</hi> for his benefit many wayes joyne theſe foure wordes togither. For if at any time he were oppreſſed with any externall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity, preſently would he ſay to himſelfe, I nothing regard what men ſay or thinke of me, not eſteeming whither they honor or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenine me. I am a ſeruant or bondman, &amp; theſe things are meete for ſuch an on. If he felt himſelf to be tempted with any voluptuous pleaſure, then ſaid he to himſelfe. Be it farre from me, that am a King to become, the ſalue of filthy vice and pleaſure. So vile a ſeruitude befitteth not my Nobility. Thus receaued <hi>Deſire</hi> exceeding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits by theſe words: whither he joyned them in order, or placed them contrarily. For both did they que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch naughty deſires kindled in him &amp; appeaſed &amp; mitigated all his adjuerſities. But now co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering the explication of theſe words may be infinit, leaſt I ſeeme to be tedious, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the reſt to the good conſideration of others.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="152" facs="tcp:18006:77"/>
            <head>AN APPENDIX, GATHERED out of the worke of <hi>Ludouicus Blotius</hi> an <hi>Abbot,</hi> conteyning briefely, the chiefe matter of the former Dialogue.</head>
            <head type="sub">Thirteene ſhort Precepts, moſt neceſſarie for all men, that deſire to attaine to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect loue of God.</head>
            <p>The firſt. <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the loue of thy Sauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, who ſuffered moſt bitter torments for thy rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, renounce and forſake all ſenſuall delights &amp; pleaſures: whenſoeuer thou wouldeſt, or deſireſt, to heare, ſee, ſmell, taſte, touch, or ſpeake any thing: call to thy remembrance, and thinke that thou art then to obey God, and reaſon ſpeaking in thee, and not thy ſenſuall appetite, which ſhall moue and ſtirre thee. Be alſo ready, and content to want the delightes of the ſpirit, according to the pleaſure and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God. And whenſoeuer thou art
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:18006:77"/>comforted with an inward ſweetnes, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation; reſt not therein, but beware thou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe it not according to thy owne proper plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Keepe euer a moſt carefull watch ouer thy ſeeing, hearing, and ouer thy ſpeaking, that they decline not after vnlawfull, vaine and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable thinges. Thou muſt be moſt vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, and warie in ſpeaking, that thou vtter not more wordes, or in other manner, then ſhal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeme thee. Let all thy talke be ſhort, plaine, and voide of ſtrife and contention. Gouerne, and order carefully, all parts of thy body. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide, and ſhunne immoderate laughter, and all leuitie, and wantonneſſe in thy behauiour.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Loue not any creature with an inordinate affection, but mortifie thy ſelfe to all tranſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry things, and carry a minde free from ſuch al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements: for in ſuch a freedome is conteyned the moſt true, and pleaſant life.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Kill and deſtroy with all poſſible care, through a full reſignation and deniall of thy ſelfe: all thy paſſions, and finfull affections, and eſpeciall thy ſtubborne and obſtinate ſelf-will. Loue only before all thinges, the holie will of God, and ſtill wiſh that it may be done, and to that, wholy ſubmit thy ſelfe, in ſuch ſort, that whatſoeuer God will haue done, that ſame thou ſhalt deſire alſo. In all things, and at all
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:18006:78"/>all times, preferre the prayſe &amp; honor of God, before thy owne profit &amp; priuate commodity.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In all thinges that ſhall happen, wiſely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the prouidence of God, &amp; carefully com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thy ſelfe and all thine to him. Knowing that he hath a care ouer thee. All aduerſity and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation (be it internall or externall) take as ſent from the hand of God. Beleeuing for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne that he doth ſende it thee, for thy farther benefit and good of thy ſoule. Beare it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore patiently euen to the laſt houre, giuing thankes to God, and continually prayſing him, through whoſe permiſſion and ordinance ſuch a thing is befalne thee. And be not troubled or moued for any iniury, that ſnall be offered to thee, nor impatiently complaine thereof to any man: but calling to remembrance thy owne iniquity and ingratitude, hould thy ſelfe worthy of all men to be reprehended, blamed, contemned, vexed, ſcorned, and trode on. Why ſhouldeſt thou be dejected for the words of men, or for any thing that thou canſt ſuffer from them? Giue men leaue to thinke &amp; ſpeake their pleſures of thee, let the world, and the Diuell rage as they will at thee, conſidering it commeth but by Gods permiſſion. Doe thou in the meane time, leane wholy to our LORD IESVS, and ſilently keepe peace continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in thy hart. If thou doeſt truly conſider, how
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:18006:78"/>ſhamefull and ſharpe thinges, thy Creator and Redeemer IESVSCHRIST hath ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for thee, moſt patiently thou wouldeſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure any affliction whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Imagine thy ſelf more baſe, &amp; abject, than any other creature remembring thy owne vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and what thy ſinnes haue deſerued. If thou thinke any good of thy ſelfe conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thou haſt none, if vnwiſely thou like thy owne doinges and conceaue well of them, herein thou ſheweſt thy exceeding pride, for which, thou ſtinkeſt before the face of God. What good ſoeuer is in thee, it is Gods, and not thine, beware therefore in vſurping that, which appertayneth to God. Neither boaſt thereof, or ſecke to pleaſe thy ſelfe: in that vvhich ſhall ſo highly diſpleaſe almightie God. Farther, think thy ſelfe vnworthy of the ſmalleſt benefitte it ſhall pleaſe God to beſtowe on thee.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Obey and followe in all lawfull thinges, the will and commandement of other men, thy owne ſelfe-will clearely abandoned, and all appetites and deſires vanquiſhed and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come. Moſt readely ſubmit thy ſelfe to Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, for nothing is more acceptable to God then Obedience: and diſobedience the thing which God moſt hateth.</p>
            <p n="8">8 Content thy ſelfe with fewe and ſimple thinges, following the example of our Sauiour
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:18006:79"/>Chriſt and his moſt bleſſed Mother. Delight neither in vaine apparell, nor gluttenous diet. But thinke with thy ſelfe, how vnthankfull thou ſhouldeſt be, if thou ſhouldeſt murmur for thy meate, not being curiouſly dreſſed; conſidering our Sauiour IESVS CHRIST, was offered for thy ſake, moſt bitter gall and vinegre to drinke. If thou want ſometime e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thoſe thinges which are needefull for thee, yet euer honour God, and put thy truſt and confidence in him, who neuer forſaketh thoſe that ſerue him, although for their greater good he ſuffer them ſometime to want.</p>
            <p n="9">9 Loue all men ſincerely, as thy brothers and ſiſters, repreſenting the Image of GOD thy Creator: Hartely wiſh the good of all men. Shewe to all men, eſpecially to thy enemies, and perſecutors, a milde, and gentle counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and behauiour, and let all thy wordes be ciuill to them,: ſuppreſſing in thy ſelfe all bitterneſſe of hart, with a mildneſſe, and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of holy Charity. Be euer ready to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and aide all men in neceſſity. Haue pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and compaſſion vpon all in miſery, rejoyce at other mens vertues, as at thy owne: and take other mens miſeries, as the miſery of thy ſelfe, imagining thou art ſubject to as much as any other.</p>
            <p n="10">10 Contemne no man; baniſh from thy hart,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:18006:79"/>with all poſſible diligence, euill ſuſpition, and raſh judgment. Inure thy ſelfe to thinke well of all men. Interpret with ſimplicity the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and doings of others to the beſt. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre plainely all other men before thy ſelfe. Imagine thou art more vile, and ingrate, then any other man liuing. Say to thy ſelfe, ſay alſo to GOD, I am vnworthy to treade vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the earth. Oh that thou diddeſt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand how willingly thou oughteſt vndertake all ſeruile vvorkes for Gods ſake: how glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thou ſhouldeſt obey and ſerue other for him. For our Lord and Redeemer IESVS CHRIST, himſelfe being made man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a ſeruant, and with humility waſhed the feete of his Diſciples.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Labour to pleaſe God, rather then men, and wiſh rather to be deſpiſed then honoured.</p>
            <p n="12">12 Feede and nouriſh in thy ſelfe holy and vertuous thoughtes, and euery where attende the preſence of GOD, hauing thy thoughts continually fixed on him, whether thou feele ſenſible deuotion or no. Theſe wordes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, being oft thought vpon, will helpe greatly to recollect thy ſpirittes, and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendly to thinke on the preſence of GOD. O <hi>Lord God, thou art euer preſent to aide and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt me; thou inhabiteſt and art abiding in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of my ſoule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:18006:80"/> 13. Whatſoeuer is not of god, regard it not, nor thinke that it doth appertaine to thee, ſo may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou with a quiet minde attend his ſeruice; <hi>And one thing is neceſſary,</hi> which to obtayne, thou muſt labour, endeuour, and doe vvhat lyeth in thy power, yet ſo, that thou who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie diſtruſt thy ſelfe, and all thou canſt doe, but haue all thy confidence in God alone, in his mercy and goodneſſe, and in the helpe and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of his heauenly grace. For without God, thou canſt doe nothing but ſinne. Reade ouer againe, and againe, theſe ſhort rules, and examine thy life and behauiour by them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <head>AN INDEX OF THE CHAP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of this Dialogue, diuided into three partes.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <list>
                  <item>THE firſt Chapter. <hi>Deſire</hi> goeth on Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage.</item>
                  <item>2. He inſtructeth ſpiritual Paſtors &amp; Prelats.</item>
                  <item>3. Of the ſame Argument.</item>
                  <item>4. Of the houſe of <hi>Humility.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. How <hi>Vaine-glory</hi> watcheth at the gates.</item>
                  <item>6. By what meanes we may attaine to <hi>Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>7. Of the purpoſe of <hi>Humility,</hi> and her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with <hi>Deſire.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>8. Humility continueth her diſcourſe.</item>
                  <item>9. Humility ſtill continueth her ſpeach, and teacheth how to fight againſt ſinne.</item>
                  <pb n="159" facs="tcp:18006:80"/>
                  <item>10. Of concupiſcence of the fleſh.</item>
                  <item>11. Of concupiſcence of the eyes, and pride of life.</item>
                  <item>12. How the other wicked Maydens may be ouercome.</item>
                  <item>13. All malice may be expelled.</item>
                  <item>14. Of other exerciſes of Humility.</item>
                  <item>15. Of the vertues that be daughters to Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility.</item>
                  <item>16. How all creatures be good, and yet none is good but God.</item>
                  <item>17. Of the ſame Argument.</item>
                  <item>18. Of the manners &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditions of Simplicity</item>
                  <item>19. How purity of hart, and Innocency might be preſerued.</item>
                  <item>20. Of Pouerty.</item>
                  <item>21. Of Obedience.</item>
                  <item>22. Of Chaſtity.</item>
                  <item>23. The Concluſion of the firſt part.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>THE SECOND PART.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Of Patience.</item>
                  <item>2. How God may be known by his cretures.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>THE THIRD PART.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Of the probation and exerciſe of the Loue of God.</item>
                  <item>2. Of the loue of our Neighbour.</item>
                  <item>3. Of the Loue of God, &amp; of our Neighbour, and of an other degree of loue, and of the function thereof.</item>
                  <pb n="160" facs="tcp:18006:81"/>
                  <item>4. Of the ſame.</item>
                  <item>5. Of two other Purpoſs of the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> to wit, to deſire nothing, and to thinke vpon nothing.</item>
                  <item>6. Of the ſame, and of prayer alſo.</item>
                  <item>7. Of the office of the <hi>Loue of God</hi> in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther degree, &amp; a continuation of that, which he beganne of the manner of praying.</item>
                  <item>8. Of the third degree of Loue.</item>
                  <item>9. Of thoſe thinges which the <hi>Loue of God</hi> hateth.</item>
                  <item>10. How the Loue of God brought deſire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the houſe.</item>
                  <item>11. How Deſire of God prepared Deſire to eate of the fruit he gaue him.</item>
                  <item>12. How Deſire learned to ſing.</item>
                  <item>13. How Deſire of God brought Deſire into the chamber of his Lord and Maſter, and of the manner of praying.</item>
                  <item>14. How our Lord gaue Deſire good directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to gouerne him ſelfe well.</item>
                  <item>15. Deſire exerciſed the foure wordes, which our Lord taught him, and what benefit hee reaped thereby.</item>
               </list>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:18006:81"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
